<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<preface id="intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<section>
		<title>Background</title>

		<para>The C program static checker was originally developed as a
			programming tool to aid the construction of portable programs using
			the Application Programming Interface (&api;) model of software
			portability; the principle underlying this approach being:</para>

		<blockquote>If a program is written to conform to an abstract
				&api; specification, then that program will be portable to any
				machine which implements the &api; specification
				correctly.</blockquote>

		<para>This approach gave the tool an unusually powerful basis for
			static checking of C programs and a large amount of development
			work has resulted in the production of the TenDRA C static checker
			(tchk). The terms, TenDRA C checker and tchk are used
			interchangably in this document.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>The C static checker</title>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>strict interface checking. In particular, the checker can
					analyse programs against abstract &api;s to check their conformance
					to the specification. Abstract versions of most standard APIs are
					provided with the tool; alternatively users can define their own
					abstract APIs using the syntax described in Annex G;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>checking of integer sizes, overflows and implicit integer
					conversions including potential 64-bit problems, against a 16 bit
					or 32 bit architecture profile;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>strict ISO C90 standard checking, plus configurable support for
					many non-ISO dialect features;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>extensive type checking, including prototype-style checking for
					traditionally defined functions, conversion checking, type checking
					on printf and scanf style argument strings and type checking
					between translation units;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>variable analysis, including detection of unused variables, use
					of uninitialised variables, dependencies on order of evaluation in
					expressions and detection of unused function returns, computed
					values and static variables;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>detection of unused header files;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>configurable tests for detecting many other common programming
					errors;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>complete standard API usage analysis;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>several built-in checking environments plus support for
					user-defined checking profiles.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>About this document</title>

		<!-- TODO: remove this section -->

		<warning>
			<para>Much of the specifics of this document have been extended by
				<code>tcpplus</code>. Whilst everything discussed here is still
				relevant, the new C producer, <emphasis>tdfc2</emphasis>, also
				incorporates features from <code>tcpplus</code>.</para>
			<!-- TODO centralise; split off standalone bits -->
			<!-- TODO merge out OT things to their relevant areas -->
		</warning>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Chapter 2: Configuring the Checker describes the built-in
					checking modes and the design of customised environments;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Chapters 3-8: Type Checking, Integral Types, Data Flow and
					Variable Analysis , Preprocessing Checks, ISO C and Other Dialects
					and Common Errors respectively;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Chapter 9: The Symbol Table Dump deals with the detection of
					unused header files, type checking across translation units and
					complete standard API usage analysis;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Chapter 10: Conditional Compilation describes the checker's
					approach to conditional compilation;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Chapter 11: References lists the references used in the
					production of this document;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Annex A: Checking Modes gives a description of the built-in
					environments;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Annex B: Command Line Options lists the command line checking
					options;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Annex C: Specifying Integral Types describes the built-in
					integer modes and the methods for customising them;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Annex D: Pragma Syntax Specification;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Annex E: Symbol Table Dump Specification;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Annex F: Token Syntax describes the methods and syntax used to
					produce abstract APIs;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Annex G: Abstract API Manipulation gives details of the ways in
					which TenDRA abstract APIs may be extended, combined or overriden
					by local declarations;</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Annex H: Specifying Conversions with Tokens.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</preface>

