<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter id="apis">
	<title>Application Programming Interfaces</title>

	<para>Application Programming Interfaces are typically specified with a
		C mapping, which define the required contents for C header files which
		a portable C program must include by name to gain access to target
		specific implementations of an &api; library. The &tdf; approach to &api;
		specification includes using a #pragma token syntax within architecture
		neutral C header files, such that all implementation dependencies
		are encapsulated by &api; specific tokens. These &api; tokens are the
		&tdf; representation of the &api;. Both the &api; library and &api; token
		definitions are required before a &tdf; program using the &api; can be
		installed on any particular platform.</para>

	<para>Platform specific definitions for &api; tokens are produced automatically,
		with few exceptions, for any platform with a conformant implementation
		of the &api;. This is achieved by a token library building process which
		analyses the architecture neutral header files for the &api; concerned,
		together with the platform specific header files that provide normal
		(non-&tdf;) C access to the &api;. The few exceptions occur where the
		platform specific header files have been written to make use of specific
		C compiler built-in features, typically recognised by identifiers
		with a prefix such as <code>__builtin_</code>. Such cases are very likely
		to require explicit recognition of the corresponding token name in
		&tdf; installers.</para>

	<para>Generally, &api; token names and specifications are not detailed in
		this token register. The token specifications are clearly dependent
		on the associated &api; specifications. Authority for controlling the
		actual &api; token names, and the relationship between &api; tokens and
		the various &api; standardisation authorities, remain separate subjects
		of discussion.</para>

	<para>Names and specifications are given or implied below for those &api;
		tokens which frequently require built-in support from installers,
		and for other cases where an installer may be able to produce better
		code than could be achieved by normal token expansion, for example
		by inlining standard function calls.</para>

	<section>
		<title>ANSI C standard functions</title>

		<para>The set of tokens implied below all have the form:</para>

		<para><code>c89<code>.</code></code><replaceable>header</replaceable><code>.</code><replaceable>function</replaceable></para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">... :	 ...
	-&gt; EXP</programlisting>

		<para>Tokens are defined for all cases where <code>header</code> is ctype or string
			or math or stdlib, and <code>function</code> is the name of a non-ellipsis
			function specified in the ANSI C standard library, declared within
			the corresponding header &lt;<code>header</code>.h&gt;.   (Note that ellipsis
			functions, such as <code>printf</code>, cannot be represented as tokens
			since they may take a variable number of arguments.)</para>

		<para>These tokens have arguments all of <code>SORT</code> <code>EXP</code>,
			whose number and shape, and token result shape, all correspond to
			the implementation shape of the named ANSI C standard library function
			parameters and result. For the few cases where the function is specified
			not to return (e.g. <code>c89.stdlib.abort</code>), the result shape may
			be either <code>TOP</code> or <code>BOTTOM</code>.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Common exceptional cases</title>

		<section>
			<title><code>c89.setjmp.setjmp</code></title>

			<programlisting language="tdf"><code>jb</code>:	EXP
	-&gt; EXP</programlisting>

			<para><code>c89.setjmp.setjmp</code> is a token which has the semantics and argument
				and result implementation shapes corresponding to the ANSI C macro
				<code>setjmp</code> declared within &lt;setjmp.h&gt;.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title><code>c89.setjmp.longjmp</code></title>

			<programlisting language="tdf"><code>jb</code>:	EXP
<code>v</code>:	EXP
	-&gt; EXP</programlisting>

			<para><code>c89.setjmp.longjmp</code> is a token which has the semantics and
				argument implementation shapes corresponding to the ANSI C macro <code>longjmp
				</code> declared within &lt;setjmp.h&gt;. The result shape may be either
				TOP or BOTTOM.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title><code>~alloca</code></title>

			<programlisting language="tdf"><code>i</code>:	EXP
	-&gt; EXP</programlisting>

			<para><code>~alloca</code> is a token which has the semantics and argument and
				result implementation shapes corresponding to the BSD specified function
				<code>alloca</code>.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title><code>c89.stdarg.va_list</code>,
				<code>.__va_start</code>,
				<code>.va_arg</code>,
				<code>.va_end</code></title>

			<para>These four tokens are identical to the Interface Tokens <code>~va_list</code>,
				<code>~__va_start</code>, <code>~va_arg</code> and <code>~va_end</code> respectively.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>

