<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
	$Id$
-->

<chapter>
	<title>Notation</title>

	<section>
		<title>Syntax description</title>

		<para>Words enclosed in angle brackets, &lt; &gt;, form non-terminal
			symbols. Other symbols and words stand for themselves as terminal
			symbols. An expansion of a non-terminal is indicated using ::= with
			its expansion given as a sequence (possibly empty) of terminals and
			non-terminals. For example:</para>

		<programlisting language="bnf">&lt;Exp&gt; ::= * &lt;ident&gt;</programlisting>

		<para>is a possible expansion of an EXP SORT. If the word for the
			non-terminal starts with a capital letter then it will be totally
			described by a set of such expansions; otherwise the expansion of
			the non-terminal will be given by other methods in the text.</para>

		<para>The post-fix -Opt on a non terminal is an abreviation allowing
			an empty expansion. For example:</para>

		<programlisting language="bnf">&lt;Access&gt;-Opt</programlisting>

		<para>is equivalent to the use of another non-terminal
			&lt;AccessOption&gt; whose expansions are:</para>

		<programlisting language="bnf">&lt;AccessOption&gt; ::=
&lt;AccessOption&gt; ::= &lt;Access&gt;</programlisting>

		<para>The post-fix -List on a non terminal is an abreviation for lists of
			objects seperated by the ,-symbol. For example:</para>

		<programlisting language="bnf">&lt;Exp&gt;-List</programlisting>

		<para>is equivalent to the use of another non-terminal &lt;ExpList&gt;
			whose expansions are:</para>

		<programlisting language="bnf">&lt;ExpList&gt; ::= &lt;Exp&gt;
&lt;ExpList&gt; ::= &lt;ExpList&gt; , &lt;Exp&gt;</programlisting>

		<para>Both of these post-fix notations are also used with sequences of
			terminals and non-terminals within the angle brackets with the same
			kind of expansion. In these cases, the expansion within the angle
			brackets form an anonymous non-terminal.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Lexical Units</title>

		<para>The terminal symbols ( ), [ ], and { } always occur as
			parenthetic pairs and never form part of other terminal
			symbols.</para>

		<para>The terminal symbols , ; and : are similarly terminators for
			other terminal symbols.</para>

		<para>White space is a terminator for other terminal symbols but is
			otherwise ignored except in strings.</para>

		<para>All other terminal symbols are sequences of ACSII symbols not
			including the above. These are divided into seven classes: keywords,
			TDF constructors, operators, &lt;integer_denotation&gt;s,
			&lt;floating_denotation&gt;s, &lt;string&gt;s and
			&lt;ident&gt;s.</para>

		<para>The keywords and operators are expressed directly in the syntax
			description. The TDF constructors are those given in the TDF
			specification which have first-class SORTs as parameters and
			results.</para>

		<para>An &lt;integer_denotatation&gt; allows one to express an integer
			in any base less than 16, with the default being 10.</para>

		<programlisting language="bnf">&lt;integer_denotation&gt; ::= &lt;digit&gt;
&lt;integer_denotation&gt; ::= &lt;integer_denotation&gt; &lt;digit&gt;
&lt;integer_denotation&gt; ::= &lt;base&gt; &lt;integer_denotation&gt;

&lt;base&gt; ::= &lt;integer_denotation&gt; r</programlisting>

		<para>Examples are 31, 16r1f, 8r37, 2r11111 - all giving the same
			value.</para>

		<para>A &lt;floating_denotation&gt; is an &lt;integer_denotation&gt;
			followed by the . symbol and a sequence of digits. The radix of the
			&lt;floating_denotation&gt; is given by the base of its component
			&lt;integer_denotation&gt;</para>

		<para>A &lt;string&gt; is the same as a C string - any sequence of
			characters within " ". The same C conventions hold for \ within
			strings for single characters.</para>

		<para>A &lt;character&gt; is an string character within ` `. The same
			\ conventions hold.</para>

		<para>An &lt;ident&gt; is any other sequence of characters. They will
			be used to form names for TAGs, TOKENs, AL_TAGs and LABELs.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Pre-processing</title>
		
		<para>At the moment there is only one pre-processing directive. A line
			starting with #include will textually include the following file
			(named within string quotes), using the same path conventions as
			C.</para>

		<para>Comments may be included in the text using the /* ... */
			notation; this differs slightly from the C convention in that
			comments may be nested.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

