<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
  $Id$
-->

<chapter>
	<title>CAPSULEs and UNITs</title>

	<para>A CAPSULE is typically the result of a single compilation - one
		could regard it as being the TDF analogue of a Unix .o file. Just as
		with .o files, a set of CAPSULEs can be linked together to form
		another. Similarly, a CAPSULE may be translated to make program for
		some platform, provided certain conditions are met. One of these
		conditions is obviously that a translator exists for the platform, but
		there are others. They basically state that any names that are
		undefined in the CAPSULE can be supplied by the system in which it is
		to be run. For example, the translator could produce assembly code
		with external identifiers which will be supplied by some system
		library.</para>

	<section id="make_capsule-and-name-spaces">
		<title>make_capsule and name-spaces</title>

		<para>The only constructor for a CAPSULE is make_capsule. Its basic
			function is to compose together UNITs which contain the declarations
			and definitions of the program. The signature of make_capsule looks
			rather daunting and is probably best represented graphically.</para>

		<figure>
			<title><code>make_capsule</code></title>

			<graphic fileref="images/guide2.svg"/>
		</figure>

		<para>The diagram gives an example of a CAPSULE using the same
			components as in the following text.</para>

		<para>Each CAPSULE has its own name-space, distinct from all other
			CAPSULEs' name-spaces and also from the name-spaces of its component
			UNITs (see <!-- TODO: <link linkened="#11">section 3.1.2</link> -->).  There are
			several different kinds of names in TDF and each name-space is
			further subdivided into one for each kind of name.  The number of
			different kinds of names is potentially unlimited but only three are
			used in core-TDF, namely "tag", "token" and "al_tag". Those names in
			a "tag" name-space generally correspond to identifiers in normal
			programs and I shall use these as the paradigm for the properties of
			them all.</para>

		<para>The actual representations of a "tag" name in a given name-space
			is an integer, described as SORT TDFINT. These integers are drawn
			from a contiguous set starting from 0 up to some limit given by the
			constructor which introduces the name-space. For CAPSULE
			name-spaces, this is given by the <code>capsule_linking</code>
			parameter of make_capsule:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">capsule_linking: SLIST(CAPSULE_LINK)</programlisting>

		<para>In the most general case in core-TDF, there would be three
			entries in the list introducing limits using make_capsule_link for
			each of the "tag", "token" and "al_tag" name-spaces for the CAPSULE.
			Thus if:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">capsule_linking = (make_capsule_link("tag", 5),
                   make_capsule_link("token", 6),
                   make_capsule_link("al_tag", 7))</programlisting>

		<para>there are 5 CAPSULE "tag" names used within the CAPSULE, namely
			0, 1, 2, 3 and 4; similarly there are 6 "token" names and 7 "al_tag"
			names.</para>

		<section id="external-linkages">
			<title>External linkages</title>

			<para>The context of usage will always determine when and how an
				integer is to be interpreted as a name in a particular name-space.
				For example, a TAG in a UNIT is constructed by make_tag applied to
				a TDFINT which will be interpreted as a name from that UNIT's
				"tag" name-space. An integer representing a name in the CAPSULE
				name-space would be found in a LINKEXTERN of the
				<code>external_linkage</code> parameter of make_capsule.</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">external_linkage: SLIST(EXTERN_LINK)</programlisting>

			<para>Each EXTERN_LINK is itself formed from an SLIST of LINKEXTERNs
				given by make_extern_link . The order of the EXTERN_LINKs
				determines which name-space one is dealing with; they are in the
				same order as given by the <code>extern_linkage</code> parameter.
				Thus, with the <code>extern_linkage</code> given above, the first
				EXTERN_LINK would deal with the "tag" name-space; Each of its
				component LINKEXTERNs constructed by make_linkextern would be
				identifying a tag number with some name external to the CAPSULE;
				for example one might be:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">make_linkextern(4, string_extern("printf"))</programlisting>

			<para>This would mean: identify the CAPSULE's "tag" 4 with an name
				called "printf", external to the module. The name "printf" would
				be used to linkage external to the CAPSULE; any name required
				outside the CAPSULE would have to be linked like
				this.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="units">
			<title>UNITs</title>

			<para>This name "printf", of course, does not necessarily mean the C
				procedure in the system library. This depends both on the system
				context in which the CAPSULE is translated and also the meaning of
				the CAPSULE "tag" name 4 given by the component UNITs of the
				CAPSULE in the <code>groups</code> parameter of
				make_capsule:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">groups: SLIST(GROUP)</programlisting>

			<para>Each GROUP in the <code>groups</code> SLIST will be formed by
				sets of UNITs of the same kind. Once again, there are a
				potentially unlimited number of kinds of UNITs but core-TDF only
				uses those named "tld","al_tagdefs", "tagdecs", "tagdefs",
				"tokdecs" and "tokdefs".<footnote>
					<para>The "tld" UNITs gives usage information for names
						to aid the linker, tld, to discover which namess have
						definitions and some usage information. The C producer also
						optionally constructs "diagnostics" UNITs (to give run-time
						diagnostic information).</para>
				</footnote>
				These names will appear (in the same order as in
				<code>groups</code>) in the <code>prop_names</code> parameter of
				make_capsule, one for each kind of UNIT appearing in the
				CAPSULE:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">prop_names: SLIST(TDFIDENT)</programlisting>

			<para>Thus if:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">prop_names = ("tagdecs", "tagdefs")</programlisting>

			<para>then, the first element of <code>groups</code> would contain
				only "tagdecs" UNITs and and the second would contain only
				"tagdefs" UNITs. A "tagdecs" UNIT contains things rather like a
				set of global identifier declarations in C, while a "tagdefs" UNIT
				is like a set of global definitions of identifiers.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="make_unit">
			<title>make_unit</title>

			<para>Now we come to the construction of UNITs using make_unit, as
				in the diagram below:</para>

			<figure>
				<title><code>make_unit</code></title>
				<graphic fileref="images/guide1.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>First we give the limits of the various name-spaces local to
				the UNIT in the <code>local_vars</code> parameter:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">local_vars: SLIST(TDFINT)</programlisting>

			<para>Just in the same way as with <code>external_linkage</code>,
				the numbers in local_vars correspond (in the same order) to the
				spaces indicated in <code>capsule_linking</code> in
				<link linkend="make_capsule-and-name-spaces">section 3.1</link>.
				With our example,the first element of <code>local_vars</code>
				gives the number of "tag" names local to the UNIT, the second
				gives the number of "token" names local to the UNIT etc. These
				will include all the names used in the body of the UNIT. Each
				declaration of a TAG, for example, will use a new number from the
				"tag" name-space; there is no hiding or reuse of names within a
				UNIT.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="link">
			<title>LINK</title>

			<para>Connections between the CAPSULE name-spaces and the UNIT
				name-spaces are made by LINKs in the <code>lks</code>
				parameter of make_unit:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">lks: SLIST(LINKS)</programlisting>

			<para>Once again, <code>lks</code> is effectively indexed by the
				kind of name-space a. Each LINKS is an SLIST of LINKs each of
				which which establish an identity between names in the CAPSULE
				name-space and names in the UNIT name-space. Thus if the first
				element of <code>lks</code> contains:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">make_link(42, 4)</programlisting>

			<para>then, the UNIT "tag" 42 is identical to the CAPSULE "tag"
				4.</para>

			<para>Note that names from the CAPSULE name-space only arise in two
				places, LINKs and LINK_EXTERNs. Every other use of names are
				derived from some UNIT name-space.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="definitions-and-declarations">
		<title>Definitions and declarations</title>

		<para>The encoding in the <code>properties</code>:BYTESTREAM parameter
			of a UNIT is a PROPS, for which there are five constructors
			corresponding to the kinds of UNITs in core-TDF, make_al_tagdefs,
			make_tagdecs, make_tagdefs, make_tokdefs and make_tokdecs. Each of
			these will declare or define names in the appropriate UNIT
			name-space which can be used by make_link in the UNIT's
			<code>lks</code> parameter as well as elsewhere in the
			<code>properties</code> parameter. The distinction between
			"declarations" and "definitions" is rather similar to C usage; a
			declaration provides the "type" of a name, while a definition gives
			its meaning. For tags, the "type" is the SORT SHAPE (see below). For
			tokens, the "type" is a SORTNAME constructed from the SORTNAMEs of
			the parameters and result of the TOKEN using token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">params: LIST(SORTNAME)
		result: SORTNAME
		-&gt; SORTNAME</programlisting>

		<para>Taking make_tagdefs as a paradigm for PROPS, we have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">
no_labels: TDFINT
tds:       SLIST(TAGDEF)
           -&gt; TAGDEF_PROPS</programlisting>

		<para>The <code>no_labels</code> parameter introduces the size of yet
			another name-space local to the PROPS, this time for the LABELs used
			in the TAGDEFs. Each TAGDEF in <code>tds</code> will define a "tag"
			name in the UNIT's name-space. The order of these TAGDEFs is
			immaterial since the initialisations of the tags are values which
			can be solved at translate time, load time or as unordered dynamic
			initialisations.</para>

		<para>There are three constructors for TAGDEFs, each with slightly
			different properties. The simplest is make_id_tagdef:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">
t:         TDFINT
signature: OPTION(STRING)
e:         EXP x
           -&gt; TAGDEF</programlisting>

		<para>Here, <code>t</code> is the tag name and the evaluation of
			<code>e</code> will be the value of SHAPE <code>x</code> of an
			obtain_tag(<code>t</code>) in an EXP. Note that t is not a variable;
			the value of obtain_tag(<code>t</code>) will be invariant. The
			<code>signature</code> parameter gives a STRING (see
			<link linkend="sort-string">section 3.2.3</link>) which may be used
			as an name for the tag, external to TDF and also as a check
			introduced by the producer that a tagdef and its corresponding
			tagdec have the same notion of the language-specific type of the
			tag.</para>

		<para>The two other constructors for TAGDEF, make_var_tagdef and
			common_tagdef both define variable tags and have the same
			signature:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">
t:          TDFINT
opt_access: OPTION(ACCESS)
signature:  OPTION(STRING)
e:          EXP x
            -&gt; TAGDEF</programlisting>

		<para>Once again <code>t</code> is tag name but now <code>e</code> is
			initialisation of the variable <code>t</code>. A use of
			obtain_tag(<code>t</code>) will give a pointer to the variable (of
			SHAPE POINTER x), rather than its contents.<footnote>
				<para>There is a similar distinction between tags
					introduced to be locals of a procedure using identify and variable
					(see <link linkend="identify-variable">section 5.3.1</link>).</para>
			</footnote>
			There can only be one make_var_tagdef of a given tag in a program,
			but there may be more than one common_tagdef, possibly with
			different initialisations; however these initialisations must
			overlap consistently just as in common blocks in FORTRAN.</para>

		<para>The ACCESS parameter gives various properties required for the
			tag being defined and is discussed in
			<link linkend="sort-access">section 5.3.2</link>.</para>

		<para>The initialisation EXPs of TAGDEFs will be evaluated before the
			"main" program is started. An initialiation EXP must either be a
			constant (in the sense of
			<link linkend="constants">section 9</link>) or reduce to (either
			directly or by token or _cond expansions) to an initial_value:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">
init: EXP s
      -&gt; EXP s</programlisting>

		<para>The translator will arrange that <code>init</code> will be evaluated
			once only before any procedure application, other than those
			themselves involved in initial_values, but after any constant
			initialisations. The order of evaluation of different initial_values
			is arbitrary.</para>

		<section id="scopes-and-linking">
			<title>Scopes and linking</title>

			<para>Only names introduced by AL_TAGDEFS, TAGDEFS, TAGDECs, TOKDECs
				and TOKDEFs can be used in other UNITs (and then, only via the
				<code>lks</code> parameters of the UNITs involved). You can regard
				them as being similar to C global declarations. Token definitions
				include their declarations implicitly; however this is not true of
				tags. This means that any CAPSULE which uses or defines a tag
				across UNITs must include a TAGDEC for that tag in its "tagdecs"
				UNITs. A TAGDEC is constructed using either make_id_tagdec,
				make_var_tagdec or common_tagdec, all with the same form:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">
t_intro:   TDFINT
acc:       OPTION(ACCESS)
signature: OPTION(STRING)
x:         SHAPE
           -&gt; TAGDEC</programlisting>

			<para>Here the tagname is given by <code>t_intro</code>; the SHAPE
				<code>x</code> will defined the space and alignment required for the
				tag (this is analogous to the type in a C declaration). The
				<code>acc</code> field will define certain properties of the tag not
				implicit in its SHAPE; I shall return to the kinds of properties
				envisaged in discussing local declarations in
				<link linkend="defining-and-using-locals">section 5.3</link>.</para>

			<para>Most program will appear in the "tagdefs" UNITs - they will
				include the definitions of the procedures of the program which in
				turn will include local definitions of tags for the locals of the
				procedures.</para>

			<para>The standard TDF linker allows one to link CAPSULEs together
				using the name identifications given in the LINKEXTERNs, perhaps
				hiding some of them in the final CAPSULE. It does this just by
				generating a new CAPSULE name-space, grouping together component
				UNITs of the same kind and replacing their
				<code>lks</code> parameters with values derived from the
				new CAPSULE name-space without changing the UNITs' name-spaces or
				their <code>props</code> parameters.  The operation of
				grouping together UNITs is effectively assumed to be associative,
				commutative and idempotent e.g. if the same tag is declared in two
				capsules it is assumed to be the same thing . It also means that
				there is no implied order of evaluation of UNITs or of their
				component TAGDEFs</para>

			<para>Different languages have different conventions for deciding how
				programs are actually run. For example, C requires the presence of a
				suitably defined "main" procedure; this is usually enforced by
				requiring the system ld utility to bind the name "main" along with
				the definitions of any library values required.  Otherwise, the C
				conventions are met by standard TDF linking.  Other languages have
				more stringent requirements. For example, C++ requires dynamic
				initialisation of globals, using initial_value. As the only runnable
				code in TDF is in procedures, C++ would probably require an
				additional linking phase to construct a "main" procedure which calls
				the initialisation procedures of each CAPSULE involved if the system
				linker did not provide suitable C++ linking.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="declaration-and-definition-signatures">
			<title>Declaration and definition signatures</title>

			<para>The <code>signature</code> arguments of TAGDEFs and TAGDECs
				are designed to allow a measure of cross-UNIT checking when
				linking independently compiled CAPSULEs. Suppose that we have a
				tag, <code>t</code>, used in one CAPSULE and defined in another;
				the first CAPSULE would have to have a TAGDEC for <code>t</code>
				whose TAGDEF is in the second. The <code>signature</code> STRING
				of both could be arranged to represent the language-specific type
				of <code>t</code> as understood at compilation-time. Clearly, when
				the CAPSULEs are linked the types must be identical and hence
				their STRING representation must be the same - a translator will
				reject any attempt to link definitions and declarations of the
				same object with different signatures.</para>

			<para>Similar considerations apply to TOKDEFs and TOKDECs; the
				"type" of a TOKEN may not have any familiar analogue in most HLLs,
				but the principle remains the same.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="sort-string">
			<title>STRING</title>

			<para>The SORT STRING is used in various constructs other than
				declarations and definitions. It is a first-class SORT with
				string_apply_token and string_cond. A primitive STRING is
				constructed from a TDFSTRING(k,n) which is an encoding of n
				integers,each of k bits, using make_string:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">arg: TDFSTRING(k, n)
     -&gt; STRING(k, n)</programlisting>

			<para>STRINGs may be concatenated using concat_string:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">arg1: STRING(k, n)
arg2: STRING(k,m)
      -&gt; STRING(k, n + m)</programlisting>
  
			<para>Being able to compose strings, including token applications etc,
				means that late-binding is possible in <code>signature</code>
				checking in definitions and declarations. This late-binding means
				that the representation of platform-dependent HLL types need only
				be fully expanded at install-time and hence the types could be
				expressed in their representational form on the specific
				platform.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>

