<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter id="selectortoks">
	<title>Selector tokens</title>

	<para>The use of selector tokens is the primary method of adding member
		selectors to compound type tokens. (The only other method is to
		define the compound type token to be a particular structure or union
		type.) The introduction of new selector tokens can occur at any
		point in a program and they can thus be used to add new member
		selectors to existing compound types.</para>

	<para>The syntax for introducing member selector tokens as
		follows:</para>

	<programlisting language="bnf">selector-token:
	MEMBER <replaceable>selector-type-name</replaceable> : <replaceable>type-name</replaceable> :

selector-type-name:
	<replaceable>type-name</replaceable><replaceable>type-name</replaceable> % <replaceable>constant-expression</replaceable></programlisting>

	<para>The <replaceable>selector-type-name</replaceable> specifies the type of
		the object selected by the selector token. If the
		<replaceable>selector-type-name</replaceable> is a plain
		<replaceable>type-name</replaceable>, the member selector token has that
		type. If the <replaceable>selector-type-name</replaceable> consists of a
		<replaceable>type-name</replaceable> and a
		<replaceable>constant-expression</replaceable> separated by a
		<code>%</code> sign, the member selector token refers to a bitfield
		of type <replaceable>type-name</replaceable> and width
		<replaceable>constant-expression</replaceable>. The second
		<replaceable>type-name</replaceable> gives the compound type to which the
		member selector belongs. For example:</para>

	<programlisting language="c">#pragma token STRUCT TAG s_t#
#pragma token MEMBER char*: struct s_t:s_t_mem#</programlisting>

	<para>introduces a compound token type, <code>s_t</code>, which has a
		member selector, <code>s_t_mem</code>, which selects an object of
		type <code>char *</code>.</para>

	<para>Internal identifiers of member selector tokens can only reside
		in the member name space of the compound type to which they belong.
		Clearly this is also the default name space for such
		identifiers.</para>

	<para>When structure or union types are declared, according to the ISO
		C standard there is an implied ordering on the member selectors. In
		particular this means that:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>during initialisation with an initialiser-list the identified
				members of a structure are initialised in the order in which they
				were declared. The first identified member of a union is
				initialised;</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>the addresses of structure members will increase in the order
				in which they were declared.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>The member selectors introduced as selector tokens are not
		related to any other member selectors until they are defined. There
		is thus no ordering on the undefined tokenised member selectors of
		a compound type. If a compound type has only undefined token
		selectors, it cannot be initialised with an initialiser-list. There
		will be an ordering on the defined members of a compound type and
		in this case, the compound type can be initialised
		automatically.</para>

	<para>The decision to allow unordered member selectors has been taken
		deliberately in order to separate the decision of which members
		belong to a structure from that of where such member components lie
		within the structure. This makes it possible to represent
		extensions to APIs which require extra member selectors to be added
		to existing compound types.</para>

	<para>As an example of the use of token member selectors, consider the
		structure <code>lconv</code> specified in the ISO C Standard library (section
		7.4.3.1). The standard does not specify all the members of <code>struct
		lconv</code> or the order in which they appear. This type cannot be
		represented naturally by existing C types, but can be described by
		the token syntax.</para>

	<para>There are two methods for defining selector tokens, one explicit
		and one implicit. As selector token identifiers do not reside in
		the macro name space they cannot be defined using #define
		statements.</para>

	<para>Suppose <code>A</code> is an undefined compound token type and
		<code>mem</code> is an undefined selector token for <code>A</code>.
		If <code>A</code> is later defined to be the compound type <code>B</code>
		and <code>B</code> has a member selector with identifier
		<code>mem</code> then <code>A.mem</code> is defined to be
		<code>B.mem</code> providing the type of <code>A.mem</code> can
		be resolved to the type of <code>B.mem</code>. This is known as
		implicit selector token definition.</para>

	<para>In the program shown below the redefinition of the compound type
		<code>s_t</code> causes the token for the selector <code>mem_x</code> to be
		implicitly defined to be the second member of struct
		<code>s_tag</code>. The consequential type resolution leads to the
		token type <code>t_t</code> being defined to be int.</para>

	<programlisting language="c">#pragma token TYPE t_t#
#pragma token STRUCT s_t#
#pragma token MEMBER t_t : s_t : mem_x#
#pragma token MEMBER t_t : s_t : mem_y#
struct s_tag { int a, mem_x, b; }
typedef struct s_tag s_t;</programlisting>

	<para>Explicit selector token definition takes place using the pragma:</para>

	<programlisting language="bnf">#pragma DEFINE MEMBER<replaceable> type-name</replaceable><replaceable>identifier</replaceable> : <replaceable>member-designator</replaceable>

member-designator:
	<replaceable>identifier</replaceable>
	<replaceable>identifier . member-designator</replaceable></programlisting>

	<para>The <replaceable>type-name</replaceable> specifies the compound type to
		which the selector belongs.</para>

	<para>The <replaceable>identifier</replaceable> provides the identification of the
		member selector within that compound type.</para>

	<para>The <replaceable>member-designator</replaceable> provides the definition of the
		selector token. It must identify a selector of a compound type.</para>

	<para>If the <replaceable>member-designator</replaceable> is an identifier, then the
		identifier must be a member of the compound type specified by the
		<replaceable>type-name</replaceable>. If the <replaceable>member-designator</replaceable> is an
		identifier, <replaceable>id</replaceable> say, followed by a further
		member-designator, M say, then:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>the identifier id must be a member identifying a selector of
				the compound type specified by <replaceable>type-name</replaceable>;</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>the type of the selector identified by id must have compound
				type, C say;</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>the <code>member-designator</code> M must identify a member
				selector of the compound type C.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>As with implicit selector token definitions, the type of the
		selector token must be resolved to the type of the selector
		identified by the <replaceable>member-designator</replaceable>.</para>

	<para>In the example shown below, the selector token mem is defined to
		be the second member of struct <replaceable>s</replaceable> which in turn is the
		second member of struct <replaceable>s_t</replaceable>.</para>

	<programlisting language="c">#pragma token STRUCT s_t#
#pragma token MEMBER int : s_t : mem#
typedef struct {int x; struct {char y; int z;} s; } s_t;
#pragma DEFINE MEMBER s_t : mem s.z</programlisting>
</chapter>

