<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!-- $Id$ -->

<article>

	<articleinfo>
		<title>The TDF Linker - Program Overview</title>
		<productname>tld</productname>

		<authorgroup>
			<othercredit class="copyeditor">
				<firstname>Katherine</firstname>
				<surname>Flavel</surname>
				<affiliation><orgname>The TenDRA Project</orgname></affiliation>
			</othercredit>

			<author>
				<firstname>Steve</firstname>
				<surname>Folkes</surname>
				<affiliation><orgname>DRA</orgname></affiliation>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>

		<pubdate>1995</pubdate>

		<copyright>
			<year>1994</year>
			<year>1995</year>
			<year>1998</year>

			<holder>DERA</holder>
		</copyright>

		<copyright>
			<year>2007</year>

			<holder>The TenDRA Project</holder>
		</copyright>

		<revhistory>
			<revision role="version">
				<date>2010-02-21</date>
				<authorinitials>kate</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Moved out TLD as a standalone tool.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>

			<revision role="docs">
				<date>2007-12-02</date>
				<authorinitials>kate</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Converted to DocBook.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>

			<revision role="docs">
				<date>2007-12-02</date>
				<authorinitials>kate</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Converted to DocBook.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>

			<revision role="version">
				<date>2007-10-02</date>
				<authorinitials>kate</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Moved out TLD to join ANDFutils.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>

			<revision role="version">
				<date>1998-07-30</date>
				<revnumber>TLD 4.0#7</revnumber>
				<authorinitials>DERA</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>TenDRA 4.1.2 release.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>

	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>

		<para>This document gives an overview of the linker source code.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Hash Tables</title>

		<para>This section describes the four types of hash table that are used by the
			linker.  These data structures are fundamental to the linker, and most of
			the linker's behaviour involves adding things to the hash tables or writing
			out information stored in them.</para>

		<para>The four types of hash table are the unit set table, the shape table, the
			name table, and the mapping table.  Name tables only exist as part of
			entries in a shape table, and mapping tables only exist as part of entries
			in a unit set table.</para>

		<para>When linking, there is one unit set table and one shape table into which the
			information read from capsules is stored.  There is a second shape table
			into which the information from the library index is stored.</para>

		<para>When building libraries, one unit set table and one shape table are used for
			reading capsules in the same way as for linking, but one shape table is used
			for each library that is read (they are only used for checking the validity
			of the index, and are discarded immediately after the library has been
			read).</para>

		<para>For showing the library content, and extracting capsules from a library,
			only a single shape table is used to store the library index.</para>

		<section>
			<title>The Unit Set Table</title>

			<para>The first hash table type is the unit set hash table, defined in
				"tdf/unit-table.[ch]".  Each entry in the table (defined in
				"tdf/unit-entry.[ch]") has the following information:</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>next</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is a pointer to the next entry in the hash table.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>key</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is the unit set name.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>order</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is the order number of the unit set.  When reading unit set
							names from a capsule, each unit set must have a higher order number
							than the preceding unit sets.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>head</code></term>
					<term><code>tail</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>These are the start and end pointers of the list of units in the
							unit set that this entry represents.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>

			<para>Each unit in the unit list contains the following information:</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>next</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is a pointer to the next unit in the list.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>map_table</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is the unit mapping table.  It contains the unit scope
							identifier limits (counts) and the unit scope to capsule scope
							identifier mapping tables for each shape in the capsule that the
							unit came from.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>contents</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is the unit's TDF content.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>The Shape Table</title>

			<para>The second main hash table type is the shape table defined in
				"shape-table.[ch]".  Each entry in the table (defined in "shape-entry.[ch]")
				has the following information:</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>next</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is a pointer to the next entry in the hash table.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>key</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is the shape name.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>names</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is a table that contains the external names for the shape.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>id_count</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This stores the next available capsule scope identifier for the
							shape.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>non_empty</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is set to true during the capsule output routines if the shape
							is to be output (if it has either unit scope identifiers or capsule
							scope identifiers).</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>num_lib_names</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is used to cache the number of identifiers of the shape that
							are going to be written out to the library index.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>head</code></term>
					<term><code>tail</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>These store a list of name entries as they are added to the name
							table "names".  As new names are added to the the name table, they
							are also added to this list.  When trying to resolve undefined
							external names, the names are removed from the front of this list,
							and definitions are looked up in the libraries.  When all such lists
							are empty, then all possible name resolution has been done.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Name Tables</title>

			<para>The third hash table type is the name table defined in "name-table.[ch]".
				Each entry in the table (defined in "name-entry.[ch]") has the following
				information:</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>next</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is a pointer to the next entry in the hash table.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>key</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is the name's name.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>type</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is the type of the name.  There are five types: "NT_INDIRECT",
							"NT_INDIRECT_CYCLING", "NT_INDIRECT_DONE", "NT_DIRECT" and
							"NT_PLACEHOLDER".  The first three types are all indirect names
							(used by the renaming); the last type is also used by the renaming.
							The direct name type is the real name type.</para>

						<para>When renaming information is read, it is entered into each name
							table of the appropriate shape.  Initially, a place holder name is
							created for the new name, and an indirect name is created for the
							old name.  The indirect name contains a pointer to the place holder
							name (actually, this may also be an indirect name if it has also
							been renamed).</para>

						<para>Once all of the renamed names have been added to the table, the
							renamings are checked for cycles, and the indirect entries are set
							so that they all point to a place holder entry (so that it will not
							be necessary to follow chains of indirect entries).  The other two
							indirect types are used by this process.  After the process has
							completed, all entries in the table will be of type
							"NT_INDIRECT_DONE" or "NT_PLACEHOLDER".  At this stage, there will
							be no direct entries.</para>

						<para>Direct entries are added when capsules and libraries are read.
							Place holder entries will automatically turn into direct entries
							when a direct entry of the same name is added.  Attempts to add an
							entry with the same name as an indirect entry will result in the
							entry it points to being used instead.</para>

						<para>The name table hides all of the renaming: the functions that get
							entries from the name table follow indirect entries, and ignore
							place holder entries; the iteration function only iterates across
							direct entries.  In this way, nothing outside of the name table
							structure needs to worry about renaming.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>u.indirect</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains a pointer to another entry that is to be used in place
							of this entry.  It is only used if the entry is an indirect entry of
							some form.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>u.direct.id</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains the capsule scope identifier that has been allocated
							for this name.  It is only used if the entry is a direct entry (as
							is the case for all other "u.direct.X" fields).</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>u.direct.use</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains the name's usage information (as read from the linker
							information unit).  In addition, an otherwise unused bit is used to
							indicate that the name is hidden.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>u.direct.definition</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains a pointer to the capsule object that defined the name.
							It is used for reporting the original definition for multiply
							defined names.  It is also used to indicate that the name has a
							definition (it is set to the nil pointer if the name has no
							definition, or if the definition has been suppressed).  It is only
							used for names not in a library index.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>u.direct.lib_definition</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains a pointer to the library capsule object that defined
							the name.  It is only used for names in a library index, to indicate
							which capsule should be loaded to define the name.  It is set to
							the nil pointer if the name has no library definition, or if the
							definition has been suppressed.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>u.direct.list_next</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains a pointer to the next name in the list of names of
							this shape (the list that the "head" and "tail" fields in the shape
							entry structure represent).</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Mapping Tables</title>

			<para>The last hash table type is the mapping table defined in "map-table.[ch]".
				Each entry in the table (defined in "map-entry.[ch]") has the following
				information:</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>next</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is a pointer to the next entry in the hash table.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>key</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This is the shape name.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>count</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains the unit scope identifier limit for the shape in the
							unit that contains the table that the entry is an entry in.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>num_links</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains the number of unit scope to capsule scope identifier
							mappings for the shape in the unit that contains the table that the
							entry is an entry in.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>links</code></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>This contains the unit scope to capsule scope identifier mappings
							for the shape in the unit that contains the table that the entry is
							an entry in.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>

