<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
	$Id$
-->
		
<chapter id="Objects">
	<title>Specifying Objects</title>

	<para>The main body of any <code>tspec</code> description of an API
		consists of a list of object specifications. Most of this section
		is concerned with the various <code>tspec</code> constructs for
		specifying objects of various kinds, however we start with a few
		remarks on object names.</para>
	
	<section id="S41">
		<title>Object Names</title>
	
		<section id="Names">
			<title>Internal and External Names</title>
	
			<para>All objects specified using <code>tspec</code> actually have
				two names. The first is the internal name by which it is
				identified within the program, the second is the external name by
				which the TDF construct (actually a token) representing this
				object is referred to for the purposes of TDF linking. The
				internal names are normal C identifiers and obey the normal C
				namespace rules (indeed one of the roles of <code>tspec</code> is
				to keep track of these namespaces). The external token name is
				constructed by <code>tspec</code> from the internal name.</para>
		
			<para><code>tspec</code> has two strategies for making up these
				token names. The first, which is default, is to use the internal
				name as the external name (there is an exception to this simple
				rule, namely field selectors - see
				<link linkend="Field">section 4.9</link>). The second, which is preferred
				for standard APIs, is to construct a "unique name" from the API
				name, the header and the internal name. For example, under the
				first strategy, the external name of the type <code>FILE</code>
				specified in <code>c/c89:stdio.h</code> would be <code>FILE</code>,
				whereas under the second it would be <code>c_c89.stdio.FILE</code>.
				The unique name strategy may be specified by passing the
				<option>-u</option> command-line option to <code>tspec</code> (see
				<link linkend="Options">section 2.5</link>) or by setting the
				<code>UNIQUE</code> property to 1 (see
				<link linkend="Properties">section 5.4</link>).</para>
			
			<para>Both strategies involve flattening the several C namespaces
				into the single TDF token namespace, which can lead to clashes.
				For example, in <code>posix:sys/stat.h</code> both a structure,
				<code>struct stat</code>, and a procedure, <code>stat</code>, are
				specified. In C the two uses of <code>stat</code> are in different
				namespaces and so present no difficulty, however they are mapped
				onto the same name in the TDF token namespace. To work round such
				difficulties, <code>tspec</code> allows an alternative external
				form to be specified. When the object is specified the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="bnf">iname | ename</programlisting>

			<para>may be used to specify the internal name <code>iname</code> and
				the external name <code>ename</code>.</para>

			<para>For example, in the <code>stat</code> case above we could
				distinguish between the two uses as follows:</para>

			<programlisting language="tspec">+TYPE struct stat | struct_stat ;
+FUNC int stat ( const char *, struct stat * ) ;</programlisting>

			<para>With simple token names the token corresponding to the
				structure would be called <code>struct_stat</code>, whereas that
				corresponding to the procedure would still be <code>stat</code>.
				With unique token names the names would be
				<code>posix.stat.struct_stat</code> and
				<code>posix.stat.stat</code> respectively.</para>

			<para>Very occasionally it may be necessary to precisely specify an
				external token name. This can be done using the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="bnf">iname | "ename"</programlisting>

			<para>which makes the object <code>iname</code> have external name
				<code>ename</code> regardless of the naming strategy used.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="Identifiers">
			<title>More on Object Names</title>

			<para>Basically the legal identifiers in <code>tspec</code> (for
				both internal and external names) are the same as those in C -
				strings of upper and lower case letters, decimal digits or
				underscores, which do not begin with a decimal digit. However
				there is a second class of local identifiers - those consisting of
				a tilde followed by any number of letters, digits or underscores -
				which are intended to indicate objects which are local to the API
				description and should not be visible to any application using the
				API. For example, to express the specification that <code>t</code>
				is a pointer type, we could say that there is a locally named type
				to which <code>t</code> is a pointer:</para>

				<programlisting language="tspec">+TYPE ~t ;
+TYPEDEF ~t *t ;</programlisting>

			<para>Finally it is possible to cheat the <code>tspec</code>
				namespaces. It may actually be legal to have two objects of the
				same name in an API - they may lie in different branches of a
				conditional compilation, or not be allowed to coexist. To allow
				for this, <code>tspec</code> allows version numbers, consisting of
				a decimal pointer plus a number of digits, to be appended to an
				identifier name when it is first introduced. These version numbers
				are purely to tell <code>tspec</code> that this version of the
				object is different from a previous version with a different
				version number (or indeed without any version number).	If more
				than one version of an object is specified then which version is
				retrieved by <code>tspec</code> in any look-up operation is
				undefined.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="Func">
		<title>+FUNC</title>

		<para>The simplest form of object to specify is a procedure. This is
			done by means of:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FUNC prototype ;</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>prototype</code> is the full C prototype of the
			procedure being declared. For example, <code>c/c89:string.h</code>
			contains:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FUNC char *strcpy ( char *, const char * ) ;
+FUNC int strcmp ( const char *, const char * ) ;
+FUNC size_t strlen ( const char * ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>Strictly speaking, <code>+FUNC</code> means that the procedure
			may be implemented by a macro, but that there is an underlying
			library function with the same effect. The exception is for
			procedures which take a variable number of arguments, such as:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FUNC int fprintf ( FILE *, const char *, ... ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>which cannot be implemented by macros. Occasionally it may be
			necessary to specify that a procedure is only a library function,
			and cannot be implemented by a macro. In this case the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FUNC (extern) prototype ;</programlisting>

		<para>should be used. Thus:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FUNC (extern) char *strcpy ( char *, const char * ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>would mean that <code>strcpy</code> was only a library function and
			not a macro.</para>

		<para>Increasingly standard APIs are using prototypes to express their
			procedures. However it still may be necessary on occasion to specify
			procedures declared using old style declarations. In most cases
			these can be easily transcribed into prototype declarations, however
			things are not always that simple. For example,
			<code>xpg3:stdlib.h</code> declares <code>malloc</code> by the old
			style declaration:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">void *malloc ( sz )
size_t sz ;</programlisting>

		<para>which is in general different from the prototype:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">void *malloc ( size_t ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>In the first case the argument is passed as the integral
			promotion of <code>size_t</code>, whereas in the second it is passed
			as a <code>size_t</code> . In general we only know that
			<code>size_t</code> is an unsigned integral type, so we cannot
			assert that it is its own integral promotion. One possible solution
			would be to use the C to TDF producer's weak prototypes (see
			reference 3). The form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FUNC (weak) void *malloc ( size_t ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>means that <code>malloc</code> is a library function returning
			<code>void *</code> which is declared using an old style declaration
			with a single argument of type <code>size_t</code>.	(For an
			alternative approach see
			<link linkend="Typedef">section 4.8</link>.)</para>
	</section>

	<section id="Exp">
		<title>+EXP and +CONST</title>

		<para>Expressions correspond to constants, identities and variables.
			They are specified by:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+EXP type exp1, ..., expn ;</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>type</code> is the base type of the expressions
			<code>expi</code> as in a normal C declaration list. For example, in
			<code>c/c89:stdio.h</code>:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+EXP FILE *stdin, *stdout, *stderr ;</programlisting>

		<para>specifies three expressions of type <code>FILE *</code>.</para>

		<para>By default all expressions are rvalues, that is, values which
			cannot be assigned to. If an lvalue (assignable) expression is
			required its type should be qualified using the keyword
			<code>lvalue</code>. This is an extension to the C type syntax which
			is used in a similar fashion to <code>const</code>. For example,
			<code>c/c89:errno.h</code> says that <code>errno</code> is an
			assignable lvalue of type <code>int</code>. This is expressed as
			follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+EXP lvalue int errno ;</programlisting>

		<para>On the other hand, <code>posix:errno.h</code> states that
			<code>errno</code> is an external value of type <code>int</code>.
			As with procedures the <code>(extern)</code> qualifier may be used
			to express this as:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+EXP (extern) int errno ;</programlisting>

		<para>Note that this automatically means that <code>errno</code> is an
			lvalue, so the <code>lvalue</code> qualifier is optional in this
			case.</para>

		<para>If all the expressions are guaranteed to be literal constants
			then one of the equivalent forms:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+EXP (const) type exp1, ..., expn ;
+CONST type exp1, ..., expn ;</programlisting>

		<para>should be used. For example, in <code>c/c89:errno.h</code> we have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+CONST int EDOM, ERANGE ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="Macro">
		<title>+MACRO</title>

		<para>The <code>+MACRO</code> construct is similar in form to the
			<code>+FUNC</code> construct, except that it means that only a macro
			exists, and no underlying library function. For example, in
			<code>xpg3:ctype.h</code> we have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+MACRO int _toupper ( int ) ;
+MACRO int _tolower ( int ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>since these are explicitly stated to be macros and not functions. Of
			course the <code>(extern)</code> qualifier cannot be used with
			<code>+MACRO</code>.</para>

		<para>One thing which macros can do which functions cannot is to
			return assignable values or to assign to their arguments. Thus it is
			legitimate for <code>+MACRO</code> constructs to have their return
			type or argument types qualified by <code>lvalue</code>, whereas
			this is not allowed for <code>+FUNC</code> constructs.	For example,
			in <code>svid3:curses.h</code>, a macro <code>getyx</code> is
			specified which takes a pointer to a window and two integer
			variables and assigns the cursor position of the window to those
			variables. This may be expressed by:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+MACRO void getyx ( WINDOW *win, lvalue int y, lvalue int x ) ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="Statement">
		<title>+STATEMENT</title>

		<para>The <code>+STATEMENT</code> construct is very similar to the
			<code>+MACRO</code> construct except that, instead of being a C
			expression, it is a C statement (i.e. something ending in a
			semicolon). As such it does not have a return type and so takes one
			of the forms:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+STATEMENT stmt ;
+STATEMENT stmt ( arg1, ..., argn ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>depending on whether or not it takes any arguments. (A <code>
			+MACRO</code> without any arguments is an <code>+EXP</code>, so the
			no argument form does not exist for <code>+MACRO</code>.) As with
			<code>+MACRO</code>, the argument types <code>argi</code> can be
			qualified using <code>lvalue</code>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="Define">
		<title>+DEFINE</title>

		<para>It is possible to insert macro definitions directly into
			<code>tspec</code> using the <code>+DEFINE</code> construct. This
			has two forms depending on whether the macro has arguments:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+DEFINE name %% text %% ;
+DEFINE name ( arg1, ..., argn ) %% text %% ;</programlisting>

		<para>These translate directly into:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#define name text
#define name( arg1, ..., argn ) text</programlisting>

		<para>The macro definition, <code>text</code>, consists of any string
			of characters delimited by double percents. If <code>text</code> is
			a simple number or a single identifier then the double percents may
			be omitted. Thus in <code>c/c89:stddef.h.ts</code> we have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+DEFINE NULL 0 ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="Type">
		<title>+TYPE</title>

		<para>New types may be specified using the <code>+TYPE</code>
			construct. This has the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+TYPE type1, ..., typen ;</programlisting>

		<para>where each <code>typei</code> has one of the forms:</para>

		<table>
			<col align="left"/>
			<col align="left"/>

			<thead>
				<tr>
					<th>Type</th>
					<th>Description</th>
				</tr>
			</thead>

			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td><code>name</code></td>
					<td>A general type (about which we know
						nothing more)</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(struct) <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A structure type</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(union) <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A union type</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>struct <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A structure tag</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>union <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A union tag</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(int) <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>An integral type</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(signed) <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A signed integral type</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(unsigned) <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>An unsigned integral type</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(float) <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A floating type</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(arith)<replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>An arithmetic (integral or floating) type</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(scalar)<replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A scalar (arithmetic or pointer) type</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>

		<para>To make clear the distinction between structure types and
			structure tags, if we have in C:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">typedef struct tag { int x, y ; } type ;</programlisting>

		<para>then <code>type</code> is a structure type and <code>tag</code> is a
			structure tag.</para>

		<para>For example, in <code>c/c89</code> we have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+TYPE FILE ;
+TYPE struct lconv ;
+TYPE (struct) div_t ;
+TYPE (signed) ptrdiff_t ;
+TYPE (unsigned) size_t ;
+TYPE (arith) time_t ;
+TYPE (int) wchar_t ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="Typedef">
		<title>+TYPEDEF</title>

		<para>It is also possible to define new types in terms of existing
			types. This is done using the <code>+TYPEDEF</code> construct, which
			is identical in form to the C <code>typedef</code> construct. This
			construct can be used to define pointer, procedure and array types,
			but not compound structure and union types. For these see
			<link linkend="Field">section 4.9</link> below.</para>

		<para>For example, in <code>xpg3:search.h</code> we have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+TYPE struct entry ;
+TYPEDEF struct entry ENTRY ;</programlisting>

		<para>There are a couple of special forms. To understand the first,
			note that C uses <code>void</code> function returns for two
			purposes.	Firstly to indicate that the function does not return a
			value, and secondly to indicate that the function does not return at
			all (<code>exit</code> is an example of this second usage). In TDF
			terms, in the first case the function returns <code>TOP</code>, in
			the second it returns <code>BOTTOM</code> .	<code>tspec</code>
			allows types to be introduced which have the second meaning. For
			example, we could have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+TYPEDEF ~special ( "bottom" ) ~bottom ;
+FUNC ~bottom exit ( int ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>meaning that the local type <code>~bottom</code> is the
			<code>BOTTOM</code> form of <code>void</code>. The procedure <code>
			exit</code>, which never returns, can then be declared to return
			<code>~bottom</code> rather than <code>void</code>. Other such
			special types may be added in future.</para>

		<para>The second special form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+TYPEDEF ~promote ( x ) y ;</programlisting>

		<para>means that <code>y</code> is an integral type which is the integral
			promotion of <code>x</code>. <code>x</code> must have previously
			been declared as an integral type. This gives an alternative
			approach to the old style procedure declaration problem described in
			<link linkend="Func">section 4.2</link>. Recall that:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">void *malloc ( sz )
size_t sz ;</programlisting>

		<para>means that <code>malloc</code> has one argument which is passed as
			the integral promotion of <code>size_t</code>. This could be
			expressed as follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+TYPEDEF ~promote ( size_t ) ~size_t ;
+FUNC void *malloc ( ~size_t ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>introducing a local type to stand for the integral promotion of
			<code>size_t</code>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="Field">
		<title>+FIELD</title>

		<para>Having specified a structure or union type, or a structure or
			union tag, we may wish to specify certain fields of this structure
			or union. This is done using the <code>+FIELD</code> construct. This
			takes the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FIELD type {
ftype field1, ..., fieldn ;
....
} ;</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>type</code> is the structure or union type and
			<code>field1</code>, ..., <code>fieldn</code> are field selectors
			derived from the base type <code>ftype</code> as in a normal C
			structure definition. <code>type</code> may have one of the forms:</para>

		<table>
			<col align="left"/>
			<col align="left"/>

			<thead>
				<tr>
					<th>Type</th>
					<th>Description</th>
				</tr>
			</thead>

			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td><code>(struct) <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A structure type</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>(union) <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A union type</td>
				</tr>
				
				<tr>
					<td><code>struct <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A structure tag</td>
				</tr>
				
				<tr>
					<td><code>union <replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A union tag</td>
				</tr>
				
				<tr>
					<td><code><replaceable>name</replaceable></code></td>
					<td>A previously declared structure or
						union type</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>

		<para>Except in the final case (where it is not clear if
			<code>type</code> is a structure or a union), it is not necessary to
			have previously introduced <code>type</code> using a
			<code>+TYPE</code> construct - this declaration is implicit in the
			<code>+FIELD</code> construct.</para>

		<para>For example, in <code>c/c89:time.h</code> we have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FIELD struct tm {
int tm_sec ;
int tm_min ;
int tm_hour ;
int tm_mday ;
int tm_mon ;
int tm_year ;
int tm_wday ;
int tm_yday ;
int tm_isdst ;
} ;</programlisting>

		<para>meaning that there exists a structure with tag <code>tm</code> with
			various fields of type <code>int</code>. Any implementation must
			have these corresponding fields, but they need not be in the given
			order, nor do they have to comprise the whole structure.</para>

		<para>As was mentioned above (in <link linkend="Names">4.1.1</link>),
			field selectors form a special case when <code>tspec</code> is
			making up external token names. For example, in the case above, the
			token name for the <code>tm_sec</code> field is either
			<code>tm.tm_sec</code> or <code>c_c89.time.tm.tm_sec</code>,
			depending on whether or not unique token names are used.</para>

		<para>It is possible to have several <code>+FIELD</code> constructs
			referring to the same structure or union. For example,
			<code>posix:dirent.h</code> declares a structure with tag
			<code>dirent</code> and one field, <code>d_name</code>, of this
			structure. <code>xpg3:dirent.h</code> extends this by adding another
			field, <code>d_ino</code>.</para>

		<para>There is a second form of the <code>+FIELD</code> construct
			which has more in common with the <code>+TYPEDEF</code> construct.
			The form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+FIELD type := {
ftype field1, ..., fieldn ;
....
} ;</programlisting>

		<para>means that the type <code>type</code> is defined to be exactly the
			given structure or union type, with precisely the given fields in
			the given order.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="Nat">
		<title>+NAT</title>

		<para>In the example given in
			<link linkend="Field">section 4.9</link>,
			<code>posix:dirent.h</code> specifies that the <code>d_name</code>
			field of <code>struct dirent</code> is a fixed sized array of
			characters, but that the size of this array is implementation
			dependent. We therefore have to introduce a value to stand for the
			size of this array using the <code>+NAT</code> construct. This has
			the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+NAT nat1, ..., natn ;</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>nat1</code>, ..., <code>natn</code> are the array sizes
			to be declared. The example thus becomes:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+NAT ~dirent_d_name_size ;
+FIELD struct dirent {
char d_name [ ~dirent_d_name_size ] ;
} ;</programlisting>

		<para>Note the use of a local variable to stand for a value, namely the
			array size, which is invisible to the user (see
			<link linkend="Identifiers">section 4.1.2</link>).</para>

		<para>As another example, in <code>c/c89:setjmp.h</code> we know that
			<code>jmp_buf</code> is an array type. We therefore introduce
			objects to stand for the type which it is an array of and for the
			size of the array, and define <code>jmp_buf</code> by a
			<code>+TYPEDEF</code> command:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+NAT ~jmp_buf_size ;
+TYPE ~jmp_buf_elt ;
+TYPEDEF ~jmp_buf_elt jmp_buf [ ~jmp_buf_size ] ;</programlisting>

		<para>Again, local variables have been used for the introduced
			objects.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="Enum">
		<title>+ENUM</title>

		<para>Currently <code>tspec</code> only has limited support for
			enumeration types. A <code>+ENUM</code> construct is translated
			directly into a C definition of an enumeration type. The
			<code>+ENUM</code> construct has the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+ENUM etype := {
entry,
....
} ;</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>etype</code> is the enumeration type being defined -
			either a type name or <code>enum etag</code> for some enumeration
			tag <code>etag</code> - and each <code>entry</code> has one of the
			forms:</para>

		<programlisting language="bnf">name
name = number</programlisting>

		<para>as in a C enumeration type. For example, in
			<code>xpg3:search.h</code> we have:</para>

		<programlisting language="tspec">+ENUM ACTION := { FIND, ENTER } ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="Token">
		<title>+TOKEN</title>

		<para>As was mentioned in <link linkend="Intro">section 1</link>, the
			<code>#pragma token</code> syntax is highly complex, and the token
			descriptions output by <code>tspec</code> form only a small subset
			of those possible. It is possible to directly access the full
			<code>#pragma token</code> syntax from <code>tspec</code> using the
			construct:</para>

			<programlisting language="tspec">+TOKEN name %% text %% ;</programlisting>

		<para>where the token <code>name</code> is defined by the sequence of
			characters <code>text</code>, which is delimited by double percents.
			This is turned into the token description:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#pragma token text name #</programlisting>

		<para>No checks are applied to <code>text</code>. A more sophisticated
			mechanism for defining complex tokens may be introduced in a later
			version of <code>tspec</code>.</para>

		<para>For example, in <code>c/c89:stdarg.h</code> a token
			<code>va_arg</code> is defined which takes a variable of type
			<code>va_list</code> and a type <code>t</code> and returns a value
			of type <code>t</code>. This is given by:</para>

			<programlisting language="tspec">+TOKEN va_arg %% PROC ( EXP lvalue : va_list : e, TYPE t ) EXP rvalue : t : %% ;</programlisting>

		<para>See reference 3 for more details on the token syntax.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

