<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
	$Id$
-->
		
<chapter id="overview">
	<title>Overview of tspec</title>

	<section id="levels">
		<title>Specification Levels</title>

		<para>Let us begin by examining the various levels of specification
			with which <command>tspec</command> is concerned. At the
			lowest level it is concerned with objects - the types, expressions,
			constants etc.	which comprise the API - and indeed most of this
			document is concerned with how <command>tspec</command>
			describes these objects. At the highest level,
			<command>tspec</command> is concerned with APIs. We could
			just describe an API as being a set of objects, however this is to
			ignore the internal structure of APIs.</para>
	
		<para>At the most obvious level the objects in an API are spread over
			a number of different system headers. For example, in ANSI, the
			objects concerned with file input and output are grouped in
			<code>stdio.h</code>, whereas those concerned with string
			manipulation are in <code>string.h</code>. But a further level of
			refinement is also required. For example, ANSI specifies that the
			type <code>size_t</code> is defined in both <code>stdio.h</code> and
			<code>string.h</code>. Therefore <code>tspec</code> needs to be able
			to represent subsets of headers in order to express this
			intersection relation.</para>
	
		<para>To conclude, <code>tspec</code> distinguishes four levels of
			specification - APIs (which are sets of headers), headers (which are
			sets of objects), subsets of headers, and objects. It identifies
			APIs by an identifying name chosen by the person performing the API
			description. The (purely arbitrary) convention is for short, lower
			case names, for example:</para>
	
		<table>
			<title>Example API names</title>

			<col align="left"/>
			<col align="left"/>

			<thead>
				<tr>
					<th>Name</th>
					<th>Standard</th>
				</tr>
			</thead>

			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td><code>c/c89</code></td>
					<td>ANSI C (X3.159)</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>posix</code></td>
					<td>POSIX 1003.1</td>
				</tr>
		
				<tr>
					<td><code>xpg3</code></td>
					<td>X/Open Portability Guide 3</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
	
		<para>In this document, headers are identified by the API they belong
			to and the header name. Thus <code>c/c89:stdio.h</code> refers to the
			<code>stdio.h</code> header of the ANSI API.	Finally subsets of
			headers are identified by the header and the subset name. If, for
			example, the <code>stdio.h</code> header of ANSI has a subset named
			<code>file</code>, then this is referred to as
			<code>c/c89:stdio.h:file</code>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="input">
		<title>Input Layout</title>

		<para>The <code>tspec</code> representation of an API is arranged as a
			directory with the same name as the API, containing a number of
			files, one for each API header. For example, the ANSI C89 API is
			represented by a directory <code>c/c89</code> containing files
			<code>c/c89/stdio.h</code>, <code>c/c89/string.h.ts</code> etc. In
			addition each API directory contains a master file (for ANSI C89 it
			would be called <code>c/c89/master.ts</code>) which lists all the
			headers comprising that API.</para>
<!-- TODO: update for .ts files -->
	
		<para>When <code>tspec</code> needs to find an API directory it does
			so by searching along its input directory path. This is a colon
			separated list of directories to be searched. This may be specified
			in a number of ways. A default search list is built into
			<code>tspec</code>, however this may be overridden by the system
			variable <code>TSPEC_INPUT</code>. Directories may be added to the
			start of the path using the
			<option>-I</option><filename>dir</filename> command-line option (see
			<link linkend="options">section 2.5</link> for a complete list of
			options). The current working directory is always added to the start
			of the path.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output">
		<title>Output Layout</title>

		<para><code>tspec</code> actually outputs two sets of output files,
			the include output files, containing the <code>#pragma token</code>
			directives corresponding to the input API, and the source output
			files, which provide a rig for TDF library building (see
			<link linkend="libraries">section 6.4</link>). These output files and
			directories are built up under two standard output directories - the
			include output directory, <filename>incl_dir</filename> say, and the
			source output directory, <filename>src_dir</filename> say.
			<code>tspec</code> has default values for these directories built
			in, but these may be overridden in a number of ways. Firstly, if the
			system variable <code>TSPEC_OUTPUT</code> is defined to be
			<filename>dir</filename>, say, then <filename>incl_dir</filename> is
			<filename>dir/include</filename> and <filename>src_dir</filename> is
			<filename>dir/src</filename>. Secondly,
			<filename>incl_dir</filename> and <filename>src_dir</filename> can
			be set independently using the system variables
			<code>TSPEC_INCL_OUTPUT</code> and <code>TSPEC_SRC_OUTPUT</code>
			respectively. Finally, they may also be set using the
			<option>-O</option><filename>dir</filename> and
			<option>-S</option><filename>dir</filename> command-line options
			respectively.</para>
	
		<para>As an example of the mapping from input files to output files,
			the header <code>c/c89:stdio.h</code> is mapped to the include output
			file <filename>incl_dir/c/c89.api/stdio.h</filename> and the source
			output file <filename>src_dir/c/c89.api/stdio.c</filename>.
			The header subset <code>c/c89:stdio.h:file</code> is mapped to its own
			pair of output files,
			<filename>subset_dir/c/c89.api/file.h</filename> and
			<filename>src_dir/c/c89.api/file.c</filename>.</para>
	
		<para>The default output file names can be overridden by means of the
			<code>INCLNAME</code> and <code>SOURCENAME</code> file properties
			described in <link linkend="properties">section 5.4</link>.</para>
	
		<para>By default, <code>tspec</code> only creates an output file if
			the date stamps on all the input files it depends on indicate that
			it needs updating. In effect, <code>tspec</code> creates an internal
			makefile from the dependencies it deduces. This behaviour can be
			overridden by means of the <option>-f</option> command-line option,
			which forces all output files to be created.</para>
	
		<para>In addition, <code>tspec</code> only creates the source output
			file if it is needed for TDF library building. If the corresponding
			include output file does not contain any token specifications then
			the source output file is suppressed (see
			<link linkend="libraries">section 5.5</link>).</para>

		<para><code>tspec</code> can also generate environment files suitable
			for &tcc; (see <link linkend="environment">section 5.4</link>).</para>
	</section>

	<section id="options">
		<title>Command-line Options</title>

		<para>There are three main forms for invoking <code>tspec</code> on
			the command-line, depending on whether it is desired to process an
			entire API, a single header from that API, or only a subset of that
			header. These are given respectively as:</para>

		<!-- TODO: just use the manpage -->

		<literallayout>tspec [options] api
tspec [options] api header
tspec [options] api header subset</literallayout>

		<para>The valid options include:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The option <option>-I</option><filename>dir</filename>
					adds a directory to the input directory search path (see
					<link linkend="input">section 2.2</link>).</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The option <option>-O</option><filename>dir</filename>
					specifies the include output directory (see
					<link linkend="output">section 2.3</link>).</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The option <option>-S</option><filename>dir</filename>
					specifies the source output directory (see
					<link linkend="output">section 2.3</link>).</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-c</option> option causes <code>tspec</code>
				to only check the input files and not to generate any output
				files.</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-e</option> option causes <code>tspec</code>
					only to run its preprocessor phase, writing the result to the
					standard output.</para>
				</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-f</option> option forces <code>tspec</code>
					to create all output files regardless of date
					stamps.</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-i</option> option causes <code>tspec</code>
				to print an index of all the objects in the input files (see
				<link linkend= "index">section 6.3</link>).</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-p</option> option indicates to
					<code>tspec</code> that its input has already been
					preprocessed (i.e. it is the output of a previous
					<option>-e</option> option).</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-r</option> option causes <code>tspec</code>
				to only produce output for implemented objects, and not used
				objects (see <link linkend="IMPLEMENT-USE">section 3.2</link>).</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-s</option> option causes <code>tspec</code>
				to check all the headers in an API separately rather than, as
				with the <option>-c</option> option, all at once.</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-u</option> option causes <code>tspec</code>
				to generate unique token names for the specified objects (see
				<link linkend="names">section 4.1.1</link>).</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-v</option> option causes <code>tspec</code>
				to enter verbose mode, in which it reports on the output files
				it creates. If two <option>-v</option> options are given then
				<code>tspec</code> enters very verbose mode, in which it gives
				more information on its activities.</para>
			</listitem>
	
			<listitem>
				<para>The <option>-V</option> option causes <code>tspec</code>
				to print its current version number (this document refers to
				version 2.0).</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>In addition <code>tspec</code> has a local input mode for
			translating single headers which are not part of an API into the
			corresponding <code>#pragma token</code> statements.
			The form:</para>

		<literallayout>tspec [options] -l file</literallayout>

		<para>processes the input file <code>file</code>, writing the include
			output file to the standard output.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

