<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
	$Id$
-->
		
<preface id="introduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>As explained in &tdf-portability.doc;, &tdf; may be regarded as an abstract
		target machine which can be used to facilitate the separation of
		target independent and target dependent code which characterises
		portable programs. An important aspect of this separation is the
		Application Programming Interface, or &api;, of the program. Just as,
		for a conventional machine, the &api; needs to be implemented on that
		machine before the program can be ported to it, so for that program to
		be ported to the abstract &tdf; machine, an "abstract implementation" of
		the &api; needs to be provided.</para>

	<para>But of course, an "abstract implementation" is precisely what is
		provided by the &api; specification - it is an abstraction of all the
		possible &api; implementations. Therefore the &tdf; representation of an
		&api; must reflect the &api; specification. As a consequence, compiling a
		program to the abstract &tdf; machine is to check it against the &api;
		specification rather than, as with compiling to a conventional
		machine, against at best a particular implementation of that
		&api;.</para>

	<para>In this document we address the problem of how to translate a
		standard &api; specification into its &tdf; representation, by describing
		a tool, <command>tspec</command>, which has been developed for
		this purpose.</para>

	<para>The low level form which is used to represent &api;s to the C to &tdf;
		producer is the <code>#pragma token</code> syntax described in
		reference 3. However this is not a suitable form in which to describe
		&api; specifications. The <code>#pragma token</code> syntax is
		necessarily complex, and can only be checked through extensive testing
		using the producer. Instead an alternative form, close to C, has been
		developed for this purpose. &api; specifications in this form are
		transformed by <command>tspec</command> into the corresponding
		<code>#pragma token</code> statements, while it applies various
		internal checks to the &api; description.</para>

	<para>Another reason for introducing &tspec; is that the
		<code>#pragma token</code> syntax is currently limited in some areas.
		For example, at present it has very limited support for expressing
		constancy of expressions. By allowing the &tspec; syntax to
		express this information, the &api; description will contain all the
		information which may be needed in future upgrades to the
		<code>#pragma token</code> syntax. Thus describing an &api; using
		&tspec; is hopefully a one off process, whereas describing
		it directly to the <code>#pragma token</code> syntax could require
		periodic reworkings. Improvements in the <code>#pragma token</code>
		syntax will be reflected in the translations produced by future
		versions of <command>tspec</command>.</para>

	<para>The &tspec; syntax is not designed to be a formal
		specification language. Instead it is a pragmatic attempt to capture
		the common specification idioms of standard &api; specifications. A
		glance at these specifications shows that they are predominantly C
		based, but with an added layer of abstraction - instead of saying that
		<code>t</code> is a specific C type, they say, there exists a type
		<code>t</code>, and so on. The &tspec; syntax is designed
		to reflect this.</para>
</preface>

