<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="token-output">
	<title>Output type system specification</title>

	<para>In this section we document the basic output of
		<command>calculus</command>. Two forms of the output can be generated -
		a description of the output specification in terms of the TenDRA
		<code>#pragma token</code> constructs, and the actual C code which
		implements these tokens.</para>

	<para>In this section the description given will be at the level of the
		output specification. The more important details of the
		<link linkend="c-output">C implementation</link> are given in the
		following section.</para>

	<para>The output is split among several header files in the specified
		output directory. The main output is printed into
		<filename>name.h</filename>, where <literal>name</literal> is the
		overall algebra name. Unless otherwise stated, all the objects specified
		below are to be found in <literal>name</literal><code>.h</code>. However
		for each union, <literal>union</literal>, in the algebra certain
		information associated with the union is printed into
		<literal>union</literal><code>_ops.h</code>. If the union has any maps
		associated with it then further output is printed to
		<filename>union_map.h</filename> and <filename>union_hdr.h</filename>.
		</para>

	<section id="output-info">
		<title>Version information</title>

		<para>Certain basic information about the input algebra is included in
			<literal>name</literal><code>.h</code>. <literal>name</literal>
			<code>_NAME</code> is a string literal giving the overall algebra
			name.	<literal>name</literal><code>_VERSION</code> is a string
			literal giving the algebra version number.
			<literal>name</literal><code>_SPECIFICATION</code> and
			<literal>name</literal><code>_IMPLEMENTATION</code> are flags which
			take the values 0 or 1 depending on whether the specification of the
			type system in terms of <code>#pragma token</code> statements or the C
			implementation is included.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-basic">
		<title>Basic types</title>

		<para>Six abstract type operators, each taking a type as argument and
			returning a type, are specified as follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="alg">TYPE PTR(TYPE t);
TYPE LIST(TYPE t);
TYPE STACK(TYPE t);
TYPE VEC(TYPE t);
TYPE VEC_PTR(TYPE t);
TYPE SIZE(TYPE t);</programlisting>

		<para>These represent a pointer to an object of type
			<literal>t</literal>, a list of objects of type <literal>t</literal>,
			a stack of objects of type <literal>t</literal>, a vector of objects
			of type <literal>t</literal>, a pointer into a vector of objects of
			type <literal>t</literal>, and an allocation block size for type
			<literal>t</literal> respectively. (It is possible to suppress all
			constructs involving <code>VEC</code> or <code>VEC_PTR</code> by
			passing the <code>-x</code> command-line option to
			<command>calculus</command>. Similarly <code>STACK</code> constructs
			may be suppressed using <code>-z</code>.)</para>

		<para>These constructors can be applied to any type, although in
			practice they are only applied to the types specified in the algebra
			and those derived from them. For example, we may form the type:</para>

		<programlisting language="alg">LIST(PTR(int))</programlisting>

		<para>representing a list of pointers to <code>int</code>.</para>

		<para>An integral type:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">INT_TYPE name_dim;</programlisting>

		<para>is specified, where <literal>name</literal> is the overall algebra
			name.	This type is used to represent the sizes of vectors.</para>

		<para>A function pointer type:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">typedef void (*DESTROYER)();</programlisting>

		<para>is specified, which represents a destructor function.	Two destructor
			functions are specified:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">void destroy_name();
void dummy_destroy_name();</programlisting>

		<para>where <literal>name</literal> is as above.
			<code>destroy_</code><literal>name</literal> is the default
			destructor, whereas <code>dummy_destroy_</code><literal>name</literal>
			is a dummy destructor which has no effect. The details of the
			arguments passed to the destructors and so on are implementation
			dependent.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-size">
		<title>Operations on sizes</title>

		<para>The <code>SIZE</code> type constructor is used to represent a
			multiple of the size of a type. It is used, for example, in the
			<link linkend="output-ptr">pointer stepping construct</link>
			<code>STEP_ptr</code> to specify the number of units the pointer is to
			be increased by.	Having a separate abstract type for the size of each
			type greatly increases the scope for type checking of memory
			allocation, and other, functions.</para>

		<para>For each basic type in the algebra (a primitive, a structure or a
			union), there is a constant expression:</para>

		<programlisting language="alg">SIZE ( t ) SIZE_type;</programlisting>

		<para>where <literal>t</literal> denotes the type itself, and
			<literal>type</literal> is the associated type name.</para>

		<para>For the five other type constructors
			<link linkend="output-basic">described above</link> there are constant
			expressions:</para>

		<programlisting language="alg">SIZE(PTR(t))			SIZE_ptr(TYPE t);
SIZE(LIST(t))		 SIZE_list(TYPE t);
SIZE(STACK(t))		SIZE_stack(TYPE t);
SIZE(VEC(t))			SIZE_vec(TYPE t);
SIZE(VEC_PTR(t))	SIZE_vec_ptr(TYPE t);</programlisting>

		<para>for any type <literal>t</literal>.</para>

		<para>These constructs allow the size of any type derived from the
			algebra to be built up. There is also a construct which corresponds to
			multiplying the size of a type by a constant. This takes the
			form:</para>

		<programlisting language="alg">SIZE(t) SCALE(SIZE(t), INT_TYPE itype);</programlisting>

		<para>for any type <literal>t</literal> and any integral type
			<literal>itype</literal>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-ptr">
		<title>Operations on pointers</title>

		<para>The <code>PTR</code> type constructor is used to represent a
			pointer to an object of type <literal>t</literal>. It should be
			emphasised that this construct is not in general implemented by means
			of the C pointer construct.</para>

		<section id="simple-pointer-constructs">
			<title>Simple pointer constructs</title>

			<para>There are several simple operations on pointers, given as
				follows:</para>

				<programlisting language="c">PTR(t) NULL_ptr(TYPE t);
int IS_NULL_ptr(PTR (t));
int EQ_ptr(PTR(t), PTR(t));
PTR(t) STEP_ptr(PTR(t), SIZE(t));</programlisting>

			<para>The construct <code>NULL_ptr</code> is used to form the null
				pointer to <literal>t</literal> for a type <literal>t</literal>.
				This is a constant expression.	<code>IS_NULL_ptr</code> can be used
				to test whether a given pointer expression is a null pointer.
				Similarly <code>EQ_ptr</code> checks whether two pointers are equal
				(note that we can only compare pointers to the same type). Finally
				<code>STEP_ptr</code> can be used to add a scalar value to a
				pointer.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="unique-pointers">
			<title>Unique pointers</title>

			<para>There are also constructs for generating and destroying unique
				pointers:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">PTR(t) UNIQ_ptr(TYPE t);
void DESTROY_UNIQ_ptr(PTR(t));</programlisting>

			<para>A unique pointer is guaranteed to be different from all other
				undestroyed pointers. Dereferencing a unique pointer is
				undefined.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="pointer-construction-destruction">
			<title>Pointer construction and destruction</title>

			<para>The constructs:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">PTR(t) MAKE_ptr(SIZE(t));
void DESTROY_ptr(PTR(t), SIZE(t));</programlisting>

			<para>are used to respectively create and destroy a pointer to a given
				type.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="construct-assignment-dereference">
			<title>Assignment and dereference constructs</title>

			<para>The constructs for assigning and dereferencing pointers have one
				of two forms depending on the complexity of the type pointed to. For
				simple types, including primitive, enumeration and union types, they
				have the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">void COPY_type(PTR(t), t);
t DEREF_type(PTR(t));</programlisting>

			<para>where <literal>t</literal> is the type involved and
				<literal>type</literal> is the associated short name.</para>

			<para>For more complex types, including structures, the assignment or
				dereference cannot be done in a single expression, so the constructs
				are specified to be statements as follows:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT COPY_type(PTR(t), t);
STATEMENT DEREF_type(PTR(t), lvalue t);</programlisting>

			<para>Here the <code>lvalue</code> type qualifier is used to indicate
				that the statement argument is an assignable <code>lvalue</code>. In
				this case it should give the location of an object of type
				<literal>t</literal> into which the pointer will be
				dereferenced.</para>

			<para>The appropriate assignment and dereference constructs are
				generated for each of the basic algebra types (primitives,
				enumerations, structures and unions). In addition there are generic
				assignment and dereference constructs for pointer types, list types,
				stack types, vector types and vector pointer types.	The first three
				are of the first form above, whereas the second two have the second
				form, as follows:</para>

				<programlisting language="c">void COPY_ptr(PTR(PTR(t)), PTR(t));
PTR(t) DEREF_ptr(PTR (PTR (t)));
void COPY_list(PTR(LIST(t)), LIST(t));
LIST(t) DEREF_list(PTR(LIST(t)));
void COPY_stack(PTR(STACK(t)), STACK(t));
STACK(t) DEREF_stack(PTR(STACK(t)));
STATEMENT COPY_vec(PTR(VEC(t)), VEC(t));
STATEMENT DEREF_vec(PTR(VEC(t)), lvalue VEC(t));
STATEMENT COPY_vec_ptr(PTR(VEC_PTR(t)), VEC_PTR(t));
STATEMENT DEREF_vec_ptr(PTR(VEC_PTR(t)), lvalue VEC_PTR(t));</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="output-list">
		<title>Operations on lists</title>

		<para>The <code>LIST</code> type constructor is used to represent a list
			of objects of type <literal>t</literal>.</para>

		<section id="simple-list-constructs">
			<title>Simple list constructs</title>

			<para>There are several simple list constructs:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">LIST(t) NULL_list(TYPE t);
int IS_NULL_list(LIST(t));
int EQ_list(LIST(t), LIST(t));
unsigned LENGTH_list(LIST(t));
PTR(t) HEAD_list(LIST(t));
LIST(t) TAIL_list(LIST(t));
PTR(LIST(t)) PTR_TAIL_list(LIST(t));
LIST(t) END_list(LIST(t));
LIST(t) REVERSE_list(LIST(t));
LIST(t) APPEND_list(LST(t), LIST(t));</programlisting>

			<para>Empty lists may be constructed or tested for.
				<code>NULL_list</code> is a constant expression. Two lists may be
				checked for equality (note that this is equality of lists, rather
				than element-wise equality).	The number of elements in a list can
				be found. The head or tail (or <code>car</code> and
				<code>cdr</code>) of a list may be formed. The end element of a list
				may be selected. The order of the elements in a list can be
				reversed. One list can be appended to another.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="unique-lists">
			<title>Unique lists</title>

			<para>There are also constructs for generating and destroying unique
				lists:</para>

				<programlisting language="c">LIST(t) UNIQ_list(TYPE t);
void DESTROY_UNIQ_list(LIST(t));</programlisting>

			<para>A unique lists is guaranteed to be different from all other
				undestroyed lists. Taking the head or tail of a unique list is
				undefined.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="list-construction-destruction">
			<title>List construction and destruction</title>

			<para>For each type <literal>t</literal> there are operations for
				constructing and deconstructing lists. For the basic types
				comprising the algebra these take the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT CONS_type(t, LIST(t), lvalue LIST(t));
STATEMENT UN_CONS_type(lvalue t, lvalue LIST(t), LIST(t)) ;
STATEMENT DESTROY_CONS_type(DESTROYER, lvalue t, lvalue LIST(t), LIST(t));</programlisting>

			<para>where <literal>type</literal> is the short type name.</para>

			<para>The operation <code>CONS_</code><literal>type</literal> is used
				to build a list whose head is the first argument and whose tail is
				the second argument. This is assigned to the third argument.
				<code>UN_CONS_</code><literal>type</literal> reverses this process,
				decomposing a list into its head and its tail.
				<code>DESTROY_CONS_</code><literal>type</literal> is similar, but it
				also applies the given destructor function to the decomposed list
				component.</para>

			<para>There are also generic list construction and deconstruction
				operations which apply to lists of pointers (with a <code>ptr</code>
				suffix), lists of lists (with a <code>list</code> suffix), lists of
				stacks (with a <code>stack</code> suffix), lists of vectors (with a
				<code>vec</code> suffix) and lists of pointers to vectors (with a
				<code>vec_ptr</code> suffix). For example, for lists of pointers
				these have the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT CONS_ptr(PTR(t), LIST(PTR(t)), lvalue LIST(PTR(t))) ;
STATEMENT UN_CONS_ptr(lvalue PTR(t), lvalue LIST(PTR(t)), LIST(PTR(t)));
STATEMENT DESTROY_CONS_ptr(DESTROYER, lvalue PTR(t), lvalue LIST(PTR(t)), LIST(PTR(t)));</programlisting>

			<para>There is also a generic list destruction construct:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT DESTROY_list(LIST(t), SIZE(t));</programlisting>

				<para>which may be used to destroy all the elements in a list.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="output-stack">
		<title>Operations on stacks</title>

		<para>The <code>STACK</code> type constructor is used to represent
			stacks of objects of type <literal>t</literal>. Empty stacks can be
			created and tested for:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">STACK(t) NULL_stack(TYPE t);
int IS_NULL_stack(STACK(t));</programlisting>

		<para>For each type <literal>t</literal> there are operations for
			pushing objects onto a stack and for popping elements off. For the
			basic types comprising the algebra these take the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT PUSH_type(t, lvalue STACK(t));
STATEMENT POP_type(lvalue t, lvalue STACK(t));</programlisting>

		<para>where <literal>type</literal> is the short type name. There are also
			generic constructs, such as <code>PUSH_ptr</code> for pushing any
			pointer type, similar to the
			<link linkend="output-list">generic list constructors</link>
			above.</para>

		<para>Stacks are in fact just modified lists with pushing corresponding
			adding an element to the start of a list, and popping to removing the
			first element. There are constructs:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">LIST(t) LIST_stack(STACK(t));
STACK(t) STACK_list(LIST(t));</programlisting>

		<para>for explicitly converting between lists and stacks.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-vec">
		<title>Operations on vectors</title>

		<para>The <code>VEC</code> type constructor is used to represent vectors
			of objects of type <literal>t</literal>. There are a number of simple
			operations on vectors:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">VEC(t) NULL_vec(TYPE t);
name_dim DIM_vec(VEC(t));
name_dim DIM_ptr_vec(PTR(VEC(t)));
PTR(t) PTR_ptr_vec(PTR(VEC(t)));</programlisting>

		<para>An empty vector can be constructed (note that, unlike null
			pointers and null lists, this is not a constant expression). The
			number of elements in a vector (or in a vector given by a pointer) can
			be determined (note how the type
			<literal>name</literal><code>_dim</code> is used to represent vector
			sizes). A pointer to a vector can be transformed into a pointer to the
			elements of the vector.</para>

		<para>In general a vector may be created or destroyed using the
			operators:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT MAKE_vec(SIZE(t), name_dim, lvalue VEC(t));
STATEMENT DESTROY_vec(VEC(t), SIZE(t));</programlisting>

		<para>Finally a vector can be trimmed using:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT TRIM_vec(VEC(t), SIZE(t), int, int, lvalue VEC(t));</programlisting>

		<para>the two integral arguments giving the lower and upper bounds for the
			trimming operation.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-vec-ptr">
		<title>Operations on vector pointers</title>

		<para>The <code>VEC_PTR</code> type constructor is used to represent a
			pointer to an element of a vector of objects of type
			<literal>t</literal>.	Apart from the basic constructors already
			mentioned, there are only two operations on vector pointers:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">VEC_PTR(t) VEC_PTR_vec(VEC(t));
PTR(t) PTR_vec_ptr(VEC_PTR(t));</programlisting>

		<para>The first transforms a vector into a vector pointer (pointing to
			its first argument). The second transforms a vector pointer into a
			normal pointer.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-primitives">
		<title>Operations on primitives</title>

		<para>Each primitive specified within the algebra maps onto a
			<code>typedef</code> defining the type in terms of its given
			definition.	The only operations on primitives are those listed above
			- the size constructs, the pointer assignment and dereference
			operations, the list construction and deconstruction operations and
			the stack push and pop operations.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-ident">
		<title>Operations on identities</title>

		<para>Each identity specified within the algebra maps onto a
			<code>typedef</code> in the output file. There are no operations on
			identities.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-enum">
		<title>Operations on enumerations</title>

		<para>Each enumeration specified within the algebra maps onto an
			unsigned integral type in the output file. The
			<link linkend="output-primitives">basic operations</link>
			listed above are always generated unless it has been indicated that
			<link linkend="input-enum">no lists of this type will be formed</link>,
			when <code>CONS_</code><literal>type</literal> and the other list and
			stack operators are suppressed. In addition each enumerator which is a
			member of this enumeration maps onto a constant expression:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">t enum_member;</programlisting>

		<para>where <literal>t</literal> is the enumeration type,
			<literal>enum</literal> is the short type name, and
			<literal>member</literal> is the enumerator name. It is guaranteed
			that the first enumerator will have value 0, the second 1, and so on,
			unless the value of the enumerator is explicitly given (as in C).
			There is also a constant expression:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">unsigned long ORDER_enum;</programlisting>

		<para>giving one more than the maximum enumerator in the enumeration.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-struct">
		<title>Operations on structures</title>

		<para>Each structure specified within the algebra maps onto a
			<code>typedef</code> defining the type to be the C structure with the
			given components. In addition to the
			<link linkend="output-primitives">basic operations</link>
			listed above there are also field selectors defined.</para>

		<para>Suppose that <literal>t</literal> is a structure type with short
			name <literal>struct</literal>, and that <literal>comp</literal> is a
			component of <literal>t</literal> of type <literal>ctype</literal>.
			Then there is an operation:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">PTR(ctype) struct_comp(PTR(t));</programlisting>

		<para>which transforms a pointer to the structure into a pointer to the
			component. There is also an operation:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT MAKE_struct(ctype, ...., PTR(t));</programlisting>

		<para>where <literal>ctype</literal> ranges over all the component types
			which do not have a component initialiser string in the structure
			definition. This is used to assign values to all the components of a
			structure. If a component has an initialiser string then this is used
			as an expression giving the initial value, otherwise the given
			operation argument is used. The initialiser strings are evaluated in
			the context of the <code>MAKE_</code><literal>struct</literal>
			statement.	The parameters to the operation may be referred to by the
			corresponding component name followed by <code>_</code>. The partially
			initialised object may be referred to by the special character
			sequence <code>%0</code>. Any remainder operations should be written
			as <code>%%</code> rather than <code>%</code>.</para>

		<para>Inheritance in structures is handled as follows: if
			<literal>t</literal> is a derived structure with base structure
			<literal>btype</literal> then there is an operation:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">PTR(btype) CONVERT_struct_base(PTR(t));</programlisting>

		<para>where <literal>struct</literal> and <literal>base</literal> are the
			short names of <literal>t</literal> and <literal>btype</literal>
			respectively.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="output-union">
		<title>Operations on unions</title>

		<para>Each union specified within the algebra maps onto an opaque type
			in the output file. In addition to the
			<link linkend="output-primitives">basic operations</link> listed above there
			are a number of other constructs output into
			<literal>name</literal><code>.h</code>, namely:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">unsigned int ORDER_union;
t NULL_union;
int IS_NULL_union(t);
int EQ_union(t, t);</programlisting>

		<para>where <literal>t</literal> denotes the union type, and
			<literal>union</literal> is the short type name.
			<code>ORDER_</code><literal>union</literal> is a constant value giving
			the number of union fields.
			<code>NULL_</code><literal>union</literal> is a distinguished constant
			value of type <literal>t</literal>. Values of type
			<literal>t</literal> may be compared against this distinguished value,
			or against each other.</para>

		<section id="union-construction-operations">
			<title>Union construction operations</title>

			<para>Most of the output for the union type <literal>t</literal> is
				output into the file <filename>union_ops.h</filename>. This contains
				a construct:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">unsigned int TAG_union(t);</programlisting>

			<para>for extracting the discriminant tag from a union.</para>

			<para>For each shared component, <literal>comp</literal>, of
				<literal>t</literal> of type <literal>ctype</literal>, say, there is
				an operator:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">PTR(ctype) union_comp(t);</programlisting>

			<para>which extracts this component from the union.</para>

			<para>For each field, <literal>field</literal>, of the union there are
				constructs:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">unsigned int union_field_tag;
int IS_union_field(t);</programlisting>

			<para>giving the (constant) discriminant tag associated with this field,
				and a test for whether an object of type <literal>t</literal> has
				this discriminant.</para>

			<para>In addition, for each unshared component,
				<literal>comp</literal>, of <literal>field</literal> of type
				<literal>ctype</literal>, say, there is an operator:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">PTR(ctype) union_field_comp(t);</programlisting>

			<para>which extracts this component from the union.</para>

			<para>There are also operations for constructing and deconstructing
				objects of type <literal>t</literal> for field
				<literal>field</literal> given as follows:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">STATEMENT MAKE_union_field(ctype, ...., lvalue t);
STATEMENT DECONS_union_field(lvalue ctype, ...., t);
STATEMENT DESTROY_union_field(DESTROYER, lvalue ctype, ...., t);</programlisting>

			<para>The operation <code>MAKE_</code><literal>union_field</literal>
				constructs a value of type <literal>t</literal> from the various
				components and assigns it into the last argument. The
				<literal>ctype</literal> arguments range over all the components of
				<literal>field</literal>, both the shared components and the
				unshared components, which do not have a component initialiser
				string in the definition. The union component are initialised either
				using the <link linkend="output-struct">initialiser string</link> or
				the given operation argument.</para>

			<para><code>DECONS_</code><literal>union_field</literal> performs the
				opposite operation, deconstructing an object of type
				<literal>t</literal> into its components for this field.
				<code>DESTROY_</code><literal>union_field</literal> is similar,
				except that it also applies the given destructor function to the
				original value. For these two operations <literal>ctype</literal>
				ranges over all the components, including those with
				initialiser strings.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="union-field-sets">
			<title>Union field sets</title>

			<para>Recall that
				<link linkend="input-union">a number of union field identifiers</link>
				may be associated with the same set of components.	In this case
				these fields form a union field set named after the first element of
				the set. There are operations:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">int IS_union_field_etc(t);
PTR(ctype) union_field_etc_comp(t);
STATEMENT MAKE_union_field_etc(unsigned int, ctype, ...., lvalue t);
STATEMENT MODIFY_union_field_etc(unsigned int, t);
STATEMENT DECONS_union_field_etc(lvalue ctype, ...., t);
STATEMENT DESTROY_union_field_etc(DESTROYER, lvalue ctype, ...., t);</programlisting>

			<para>defined on these sets. These are exactly analogous to the single
				field operations except that they work for any field in the set.
				Note that
				<code>MAKE_</code><literal>union_field</literal><code>_etc</code>
				takes an extra argument, giving the tag associated with the
				particular element of the set being constructed. Also the construct
				<code>MODIFY_</code><literal>union_field</literal><code>_etc</code>
				is introduced to allow the tag of an existing object to be modified
				to another value within the same set.</para>

			<para>The valid range of union tags for this set can be given by the
				two constants:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">unsigned int union_field_tag;
unsigned int union_field_etc_tag;</programlisting>

			<para>A union is a member of this set if its tag is greater than or
				equal to <literal>union_field</literal><code>_tag</code> and
				strictly less than
				<literal>union_field</literal><code>_etc_tag</code>.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="inheritance-in-unions">
			<title>Inheritance in unions</title>

			<para>Inheritance in unions is handled as follows: if
				<literal>t</literal> is a derived union with base union
				<literal>btype</literal> then there is an operation:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">btype CONVERT_union_base(t);</programlisting>

			<para>where <literal>union</literal> and <literal>base</literal> are the
				short names of <literal>t</literal> and <literal>btype</literal>
				respectively.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="output-union-maps">
			<title>Union maps</title>

			<para>For each map, <literal>map</literal>, on the union
				<literal>t</literal>, we have declared in
				<literal>union</literal><code>_ops.h</code> an operator:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">map_ret map_union(t, map_par, ....);</programlisting>

			<para>where <literal>map_ret</literal> is the map return type and
				<literal>map_par</literal> ranges over the map parameter types. This
				is except for maps with destructors (i.e. those qualified by a
				<link linkend="input-union">hash symbol</link>) which have the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">map_ret map_union(t, DESTROYER, map_par, ....);</programlisting>

			<para>These maps are implemented by having one function per field for
				each map. The output file
				<literal>union</literal><code>_map.h</code> contains tables of these
				functions. These have the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">map_ret(*map_union_table[ORDER_union])(t, map_par, ....) = {
	....
	map_union_field,
	....
} ;</programlisting>

			<para>where there is one entry per union field.</para>

			<para>In order to aid the construction of these functions a set of
				function headers is provided in
				<literal>union</literal><code>_hdr.h</code>.	These take the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#define HDR_map_union_field                               \
map_ret map_union_field(name_union, destroyer, par, ....) \
    t name_union;                                         \
    DESTROYER destroyer; /* if required */                \
    map_par par;                                          \
    ....                                                  \
    {                                                     \
        ctype comp;                                       \
        ....                                              \
        DECONS_union_field(comp, ...., name_union);</programlisting>
			<!-- TODO: missing } ? -->

			<para>There is also an alternative function header,
				<code>HDR_</code><literal>map</literal>_d_<literal>union_field</literal>,
				which calls <code>DESTROY_</code><literal>union_field</literal>
				rather than <code>DECONS_</code><literal>union_field</literal>. The
				destructor function used is <literal>destroyer</literal>, if this
				parameter is present, or the default destructor,
				<code>destroy_</code><literal>name</literal>, otherwise.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>

