<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
	$Id$
-->

<chapter id="namingscheme">
	<title>Naming scheme</title>

	<para>A flat name space will suffice for &tdf; token names if producer writers
		adopt the simple constraints described here. &tdf; has separate provision
		for a hierarchic unique naming scheme, but that was intended for a
		specific purpose that has not yet been realised.</para>

	<para>External names for program or application specific tokens should be
		confined to &ldquo;simple names&rdquo;, which we define to mean that they consist
		only of letters, digits and underscore, the characters allowed in
		C identifiers. Normally there will be very few such external names,
		as tokens internal to a single capsule do not require to be named.
		All other token names will consist of some controlled prefix followed
		by a simple name, with the prefix identifying the control authority.</para>

	<para>For &api; tokens, the prefix will consist of a sequence of simple names,
		each followed by a dot, where the first simple name is the name of
		the &api; as listed or referred to in <xref linkend="apis"/>.</para>

	<para>The prefix for producer specific and target dependency tokens will
		begin and end with characters that distinguish them from the above
		cases. However, common tools such as <!-- TODO application tags -->DISP, TNC and PL-&tdf; assume that
		token names contain only letters, digits, underscore, dot, and/or
		twiddle<!-- TODO tilde? -->.</para>

	<para>The following prefixes are currently reserved:</para>

	<table>
		<col align="center"/>
		<col align="left"/>

		<thead>
			<tr>
				<th>Prefix</th>
				<th>Reservation</th>
			</tr>
		</thead>

		<tbody>
			<tr>
				<td><code>~</code></td>
				<td>&tdf; interface tokens as specified in
					<xref linkend="tdfinterfacetoks"/> below, and also &lpi; tokens
					specific to <acronym>DRA</acronym>'s C producer.</td>
				<!-- TODO split into ~ and ~c. respectively? - kate -->
			</tr>

			<tr>
				<td><code>.~</code></td>
				<td>Registered target dependency tokens as specified
					in <xref linkend="targetdep"/> below, and basic mapping tokens specified
					in section <xref linkend="basicmappingtoks"/>.</td>
			</tr>

			<tr>
				<td><code>~c.</code></td>
				<td>&lpi; tokens specific to <acronym>DRA</acronym>'s C++ producer,
					other than those it shares with the C producer.</td>
			</tr>

			<tr>
				<td><code>.Et~</code></td>
				<td>&lpi; tokens specific to Etnoteam's Fortran77 producer.</td>
			</tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
</chapter>

