<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter>
	<title>Classes</title>

	<section id="class">
		<title>Class layout</title>

		<para>Consider a class with no base classes:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">class A {
    // A's members
} ;</programlisting>

		<para>Each object of class <emphasis>A</emphasis> needs its own copy of the non-static
			data members of <emphasis>A</emphasis> and, for polymorphic types, a means of referencing
			the virtual function table and run-time type information for <emphasis>A</emphasis>.
			This is accomplished using a layout of the form:</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Class A</title>

			<graphic fileref="images/class.svg"/>
		</figure>

		<para>where the <emphasis>A</emphasis> component consists of the non-static data members and
			<emphasis>vptr A</emphasis> is a pointer to the virtual function table for <emphasis>A</emphasis>.
			For non-polymorphic classes the <emphasis>vptr A</emphasis> field is omitted; otherwise
			space for <emphasis>vptr A</emphasis> needs to be allocated within the class and
			the pointer needs to be initialised in each constructor for <emphasis>A</emphasis>.
			The precise layout of the <link linkend="vtable">virtual function table</link>
			and the <link linkend="rtti">run-time type information</link> is given below.</para>

		<para>Two alternative ways of laying out the non-static data members within
			the class are implemented.  The first, which is default, gives them
			in the order in which they are declared in the class definition.
			The second lays out the <code>public</code>, the <code>protected</code>,
			and the <code>private</code> members in three distinct sections, the
			members within each section being given in the order in which they
			are declared. The latter can be enabled using the <code>-jo</code>
			command-line option.</para>

		<para>The offset of each member within the class (including <emphasis>vptr A</emphasis>)
			can be calculated in terms of the offset of the previous member.
			The first member has offset zero.  The offset of any other member
			is given by the offset of the previous member plus the size of the
			previous member, rounded up to the alignment of the current member.
			The overall size of the class is given by the offset of the last member
			plus the size of the last member, rounded up using the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~comp_off : ( EXP OFFSET ) -&gt; EXP OFFSET</programlisting>

		<para>which allows for any target dependent padding at the end of the class.
			The shape of the class is then a <code>compound</code> shape with
			this offset.</para>

		<para>Classes with no members need to be treated slightly differently.
			The shape of such a class is given by the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.empty.shape : () -&gt; SHAPE</programlisting>

		<para>(recall that an empty class still has a nonzero size).  The token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.empty.offset : () -&gt; EXP OFFSET</programlisting>

		<para>is used to represent the offset required for an empty class when it
			is used as a base class.  This may be a zero offset.</para>

		<para>Bitfield members provide a slight complication to the picture above.
			The offset of a bitfield is additionally padded using the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~pad : ( EXP OFFSET, SHAPE, SHAPE ) -&gt; EXP OFFSET</programlisting>

		<para>where the two shapes give the type underlying the bitfield and the
			bitfield itself.</para>

		<para>The layout of unions is similar to that of classes except that all
			members have zero offset, and the size of the union is the maximum
			of the sizes of its members, suitably padded.  Of course unions cannot
			be polymorphic and cannot have base classes.</para>

		<para>Pointers to incomplete classes are represented by means of the alignment:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.empty.align : () -&gt; ALIGNMENT</programlisting>

		<para>This token is also used for the alignment of a complete class if that
			class is never used in the generated TDF in a manner which requires
			it to be complete.  This can lead to savings on the size of the generated
			code by preventing the need to define all the member offset tokens
			in order to find the shape of the class.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="derive">
		<title>Derived class layout</title>

		<para>The description of the implementation of derived classes will be given
			in terms of the example class hierarchy given by:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">class A {
    // A's members
} ;

class B : public A {
    // B's members
} ;

class C : public A {
    // C's members
} ;

class D : public B, public C {
    // D's members
} ;</programlisting>

		<para>or, as a directed acyclic graph:</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Class D</title>

			<graphic fileref="images/graph.svg"/>
		</figure>


		<section id="primary">
			<title>Single inheritance</title>

			<para>The layout of class <emphasis>A</emphasis> is given by:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class A</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/classA.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>as above.  Class <emphasis>B</emphasis> inherits all the members of class <emphasis>A</emphasis>
				plus those members explicitly declared within class <emphasis>B</emphasis>.  In
				addition, class <emphasis>B</emphasis> inherits all the virtual member functions
				of <emphasis>A</emphasis>, some of which may be overridden in <emphasis>B</emphasis>, extended
				by any additional virtual functions declared in <emphasis>B</emphasis>.  This may
				be represented as follows:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class B</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/classB.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>where <emphasis>A</emphasis> denotes those members inherited
				from the base class and
				<emphasis>B</emphasis> denotes those members added in the derived class.  Note that
				an object of class <emphasis>B</emphasis> contains a sub-object of class <emphasis>A</emphasis>.
				The fact that this sub-object is located at the start of <emphasis>B</emphasis>
				means that the base class conversion from <emphasis>B</emphasis> to <emphasis>A</emphasis> is
				trivial.  Any base class with this property is called a
				primary base class.</para>

			<para>Note that in theory two virtual function tables are required, the
				normal virtual function table for <emphasis>B</emphasis>, denoted by <emphasis>vtbl B</emphasis>,
				and a modified virtual function table for <emphasis>A</emphasis>, denoted by <emphasis>vtbl
				B::A</emphasis>, taking into account any overriding virtual functions within
				<emphasis>B</emphasis>, and pointing to <emphasis>B</emphasis>'s run-time type information.  This
				latter means that the dynamic type information for the <emphasis>A</emphasis> sub-object
				relates to
				<emphasis>B</emphasis> rather than <emphasis>A</emphasis>.  However these two tables can usually
				be combined - if the virtual functions added in <emphasis>B</emphasis> are listed
				in the virtual function table after those inherited from <emphasis>A</emphasis>
				and the form of the overriding is <link linkend="vtable">suitably well
				behaved</link>
				(in the sense defined below) then <emphasis>vptr B::A</emphasis> is an initial segment
				of <emphasis>vptr B</emphasis>.  It is also possible to remove the <emphasis>vptr B</emphasis>
				field and use <emphasis>vptr B::A</emphasis> in its place in this case (it has to
				be this way round to preserve the <emphasis>A</emphasis> sub-object).  Thus the
				items shaded in the diagram can be removed.</para>

			<para>The class <emphasis>C</emphasis> is similarly given by:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class C</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/classC.svg"/>
			</figure>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Multiple inheritance</title>

			<para>Class <emphasis>D</emphasis> is more complex because of the presence of multiple
				inheritance.  <emphasis>D</emphasis> inherits all the members of <emphasis>B</emphasis>,
				including those which <emphasis>B</emphasis> inherits from <emphasis>A</emphasis>, plus all the members
				of <emphasis>C</emphasis>, including those which <emphasis>C</emphasis> inherits from
				<emphasis>A</emphasis>.
				It also inherits all of the virtual member functions from <emphasis>B</emphasis>
				and <emphasis>C</emphasis>, some of which may be overridden in <emphasis>D</emphasis>, extended by
				any additional virtual functions declared in <emphasis>D</emphasis>.  This may be
				represented as follows:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class D</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/classD.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>Note that there are two copies of <emphasis>A</emphasis> in <emphasis>D</emphasis> because virtual
				inheritance has not been used.</para>

			<para>The <emphasis>B</emphasis> base class of <emphasis>D</emphasis> is essentially similar to the
				single inheritance case already discussed; the <emphasis>C</emphasis> base class
				is different however.  Note firstly that the <emphasis>C</emphasis> sub-object of
				<emphasis>D</emphasis> is located at a non-zero offset, <emphasis>delta D::C</emphasis>, from
				the start of the object. This means that the base class conversion
				from <emphasis>D</emphasis> to <emphasis>C</emphasis>
				consists of adding this offset (for pointer conversions things are
				further complicated by the need to allow for null pointers).  Also
				<emphasis>vtbl D::C</emphasis> is not an initial segment of <emphasis>vtbl D</emphasis> because
				this contains the virtual functions inherited from <emphasis>B</emphasis> first,
				followed by those inherited from <emphasis>C</emphasis>, followed by those first
				declared in <emphasis>D</emphasis> (there are <link linkend="vtable">other reasons</link>
				as well).  Thus <emphasis>vtbl D::C</emphasis> cannot be eliminated.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="diamond">
			<title>Virtual inheritance</title>

			<para>Virtual inheritance introduces a further complication.  Now consider
				the class hierarchy given by:</para>

			<programlisting language="cpp">class A {
// A's members
} ;

class B : virtual public A {
// B's members
} ;

class C : virtual public A {
// C's members
} ;

class D : public B, public C {
// D's members
} ;</programlisting>

			<para>or, as a directed acyclic graph:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class D</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/diamond.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>As before <emphasis>A</emphasis> is given by:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class A</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/classA.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>but now <emphasis>B</emphasis> is given by:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class B</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/virtualB.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>Rather than having the sub-object of class <emphasis>A</emphasis> directly as part
				of <emphasis>B</emphasis>, the class now contains a pointer, <emphasis>ptr A</emphasis>, to this
				sub-object.  The virtual sub-objects are always located at the end
				of a class layout; their offset may therefore vary for different objects,
				however the offset for <emphasis>ptr A</emphasis> is always fixed.  The <emphasis>ptr A</emphasis>
				field is initialised in each constructor for <emphasis>B</emphasis>.  In order to
				perform the base class conversion from <emphasis>B</emphasis> to <emphasis>A</emphasis>, the contents
				of <emphasis>ptr A</emphasis> are taken (again provision needs to be made for null
				pointers in pointer conversions).  In cases when the dynamic type
				of the <emphasis>B</emphasis> object can be determined statically it is possible
				to access the <emphasis>A</emphasis> sub-object directly by adding a suitable offset.
				Because this conversion is non-trivial (see <link linkend="vtable">below</link>)
				the virtual function table <emphasis>vtbl B::A</emphasis> is not an initial segment
				of <emphasis>vtbl B</emphasis> and cannot be eliminated.</para>

			<para>The class <emphasis>C</emphasis> is similarly given by:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class C</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/virtualC.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>Now the class <emphasis>D</emphasis> is given by:</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Class D</title>

				<graphic fileref="images/virtualD.svg"/>
			</figure>

			<para>Note that there is a single <emphasis>A</emphasis> sub-object of <emphasis>D</emphasis> referenced
				by the <emphasis>ptr A</emphasis> fields in both the
				<emphasis>B</emphasis> and <emphasis>C</emphasis> sub-objects.
				The elimination of <emphasis>vtbl D::B</emphasis> is as above.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="constr">
		<title>Constructors and destructors</title>

		<para>The implementation of constructors and destructors, whether explicitly
			or implicitly defined, is slightly more complex than that of other
			member functions.  For example, the constructors need to set up the
			internal <emphasis>vptr</emphasis> and <emphasis>ptr</emphasis> fields mentioned above.</para>

		<para>The order of initialisation in a constructor is as follows:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The internal <emphasis>ptr</emphasis> fields giving the locations of the virtual
					base classes are initialised.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The constructors for the virtual base classes are called.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The constructors for the non-virtual direct base classes are called.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The internal <emphasis>vptr</emphasis> fields giving the locations of the virtual
					function tables are initialised.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The constructors for the members of the class are called.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The main constructor body is executed.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>To ensure that each virtual base is only initialised once, if a class
			has a virtual base class then all its constructors have an implicit
			extra parameter of type <code>int</code>.  The first two steps above
			are then only applied if this flag is nonzero.  In normal applications
			of the constructor this argument will be 1, however in base class
			initialisations such as those in the third and fourth steps above,
			it will be 0.</para>

		<para>Note that similar steps to protect virtual base classes are not taken
			in an implicitly declared <code>operator=</code> function.  The order
			of assignment in this case is as follows:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The assignment operators for the direct base classes (both virtual
					and non-virtual) are called.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The assignment operators for the members of the class are called.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>A reference to the object assigned to (i.e. <code>*this</code>)
					is returned.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>The order of destruction in a destructor is essentially the reverse
			of the order of construction:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The main destructor body is executed.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The destructor for the members of the class are called.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The internal <emphasis>vptr</emphasis> fields giving the locations of the virtual
					function tables are re-initialised.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The destructors for the non-virtual direct base classes are called.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The destructors for the virtual base classes are called.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>If necessary the space occupied by the object is deallocated.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>All destructors have an extra parameter of type <code>int</code>.
			The virtual base classes are only destroyed if this flag is nonzero
			when and-ed with 2.  The space occupied by the object is only deallocated
			if this flag is nonzero when and-ed with 1.  This deallocation is
			equivalent to inserting:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">delete this ;</programlisting>

		<para>in the destructor.  The <code>operator delete</code> function is called
			via the destructor in this way in order to implement the pseudo-virtual
			nature of these deallocation functions.  Thus for normal destructor
			calls the extra argument is 2, for base class destructor calls it
			is 0, and for calls arising from a <code>delete</code> expression
			it is 3.</para>

		<para>The point at which the virtual function tables are initialised in
			the constructor, and the fact that they are re-initialised in the
			destructor, is to ensure that virtual functions called from base class
			initialisers are handled correctly (see ISO C++ 12.7).</para>

		<para>A further complication arises from the need to destroy
			partially constructed objects if an exception
			is thrown in a constructor.  A count is maintained of the number of
			base classes and members constructed within a constructor.  If an
			exception is thrown then it is caught in the constructor, the constructed
			base classes and members are destroyed, and the exception is re-thrown.
			The count variable is used to determine which bases and members need
			to be destroyed.</para>

		<warning>
			<para>These partial destructors
				currently do not interact correctly with any exception specification
				on the constructor.  Exceptions thrown within destructors are not
				correctly handled either.</para>
		</warning>
	</section>

	<section id="vtable">
		<title>Virtual function tables</title>

		<para>The virtual functions in a polymorphic class are given in its virtual
			function table in the following order: firstly those virtual functions
			inherited from its direct base classes (which may be overridden in
			the derived class) followed by those first declared in the derived
			class in the order in which they are declared.  Note that this can
			result in virtual functions inherited from virtual base classes appearing
			more than once.  The virtual functions are numbered from 1 (this is
			slightly more convenient than numbering from 0 in the default implementation).</para>

		<para>The virtual function table for this class has shape:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.vtab.type : ( NAT ) -&gt; SHAPE</programlisting>

		<para>the argument being <emphasis>n + 1</emphasis> where <emphasis>n</emphasis> is the number of virtual
			functions in the class (there is also a token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.vtab.diag : () -&gt; SHAPE</programlisting>

		<para>which is used in the diagnostic output for a generic virtual function
			table).  The table is created using the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.vtab.make : ( EXP pti, EXP OFFSET, NAT, EXP NOF ) -&gt; EXP vt</programlisting>

		<para>where the first expression gives the address of the <link linkend="rtti">run-time
			type information structure</link> for the class, the second expression
			gives the offset of the <emphasis>vptr</emphasis> field within the class
			(i.e. <emphasis>voff</emphasis>),
			the integer constant is <emphasis>n + 1</emphasis>, and the final expression is
			a <code>make_nof</code> construct giving information on each of the
			<emphasis>n</emphasis> virtual functions.</para>

		<para>The information given on each virtual function in this table has the
			form of a <link linkend="ptr_mem_func">pointer to function member</link> formed
			using the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.pmf.make : ( EXP PROC, EXP OFFSET, EXP OFFSET ) -&gt; EXP pmf</programlisting>

		<para>as above, except that the third argument gives the offset of the base
			class in virtual function tables such as <emphasis>vtbl B::A</emphasis>.  For pure
			virtual functions the function pointer in this token is given by:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.vtab.pure : () -&gt; EXP PROC</programlisting>

		<para>In the default implementation this gives a function
			<code>__TCPPLUS_pure</code> which just calls <code>abort</code>.</para>

		<para>To avoid duplicate copies of virtual function tables and run-time
			type information structures being created, the ARM algorithm is used.
			The virtual function table and run-time type information structure
			for a class are defined in the module containing the definition of
			the first non-inline, non-pure virtual function declared in that class.
			If such a function does not exist then duplicate copies are created
			in every module which requires them.  In the former case the virtual
			function table will have an <link linkend="other">external tag name</link>;
			in the latter case it will be an internal tag.  This scheme can be
			overridden using the <code>-jv</code> command-line option, which causes
			local virtual function tables to be output for all classes.</para>

		<para>Note that the discussion above applies to both simple virtual function
			tables, such as <emphasis>vtbl B</emphasis> above, and to those arising from base
			classes, such as <emphasis>vtbl B::A</emphasis>.  We are now
			in a position to precisely determine when <emphasis>vtbl B::A</emphasis> is an initial
			segment of <emphasis>vtbl B</emphasis> and hence can be eliminated.  Firstly,
			<emphasis>A</emphasis> must be the first direct base class of <emphasis>B</emphasis> and cannot
			be virtual.  This is to ensure both that there are no virtual functions
			in <emphasis>vtbl B</emphasis> before those inherited from <emphasis>A</emphasis>, and that the
			corresponding base class conversion is trivial so that the pointers
			to function members of <emphasis>B</emphasis> comprising the virtual function table
			can be equally regarded as pointers to function members of <emphasis>A</emphasis>.
			The second requirement is that if a virtual function for <emphasis>A</emphasis>,
			<emphasis>f</emphasis>, is overridden in <emphasis>B</emphasis> then the return type for <emphasis>B::f</emphasis>
			cannot differ from the return type for <emphasis>A::f</emphasis> by a non-trivial
			conversion (recall that ISO C++ allows the return types to differ
			by a base class conversion).  In the non-trivial conversion case the
			function entered in <emphasis>vtbl B::A</emphasis> needs to be, not <emphasis>B::f</emphasis>
			as in <emphasis>vtbl B</emphasis>, but a stub function which calls <emphasis>B::f</emphasis> and
			converts its return value to the return type of <emphasis>A::f</emphasis>.</para>

		<!-- <title>Calling virtual functions</title> -->

		<para>The virtual function call mechanism is implemented using the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.vtab.func : ( EXP ppvt, SIGNED_NAT ) -&gt; EXP ppmf</programlisting>

		<para>which has as its arguments a reference to the <emphasis>vptr</emphasis> field of
			the object the function is to be called for, and the number of the
			virtual function to be called.  It returns a reference to the corresponding
			pointer to function member within the object's virtual function table.
			The function is then called by extracting the base class offset to
			be added, and the function to be called, from this reference using
			the tokens:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.pmf.delta : ( ALIGNMENT a, EXP ppmf ) -&gt; EXP OFFSET ( a, a )
~cpp.pmf.func : ( EXP ppmf ) -&gt; EXP PROC</programlisting>

		<para>described as part of the <link linkend="ptr_mem_func">pointer to function
			member call mechanism</link> above.</para>
	</section>

</chapter>

