<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
	$Id$
-->

<chapter>
    <title>Other implementation details</title>

	<section id="parsing">
		<title>Parsing C++</title>

		<para>The parser used in the C++ producer is generated using the &sid; tool.
			Because of the large size of the generated code (1.3MB), &sid; is
			instructed to split its output into a number of more manageable modules.</para>

		<para>&sid; is designed as a parser for grammars which can be
			transformed into LL(1) grammars.  The distinguishing feature of these
			grammars is that the parser can always decide what to do next based
			on the current terminal.  This is not the case in C++; in some circumstances
			a potentially unlimited look-ahead is required to distinguish, for
			example, declaration statements from expression statements.  In the
			technical phrase, C++ is an LL(k) grammar. Fortunately there are relatively
			few such situations, and &sid; provides a mechanism, predicates,
			for bypassing the normal parsing mechanism in these cases.  Thus it
			is possible, although difficult, to express C++ as a <code>sid</code>
			grammar.</para>

		<para>The <code>sid</code> grammar file, <code>syntax.sid</code>, is closely
			based on the ISO C++ grammar.  In particular, the same production
			names have been used.  The grammar has been extended slightly to allow
			common syntactic errors to be detected elegantly.  Other parsing errors
			are handled by <code>sid</code>'s exception mechanism.  At present
			there is only limited recovery after such errors.</para>

		<para>The lexical analysis routines in the C++ producer are hand-crafted,
			based on an initial version generated by the simple lexical analyser
			generator, &lexi;.  &lexi; has been used more directly
			to generate the lexical analysers for certain of the other automatic
			code generating tools, including &calculus;, used in the
			producer.</para>

		<para>The &sid; grammar contains a number of entry points.  The
			most important is <code>parse_file</code>, which is used to parse
			a complete C++ translation unit.  The syntax for the
			&tdfc2pragma.5; <code>#pragma TenDRA</code> directives is
			included within the same grammar with two entry points,
			<code>parse_tendra</code> in normal use, and <code>parse_preproc</code>
			for use in preprocessing mode.  There are also entry points in the
			grammar for each of the kinds of <link linkend="tok">token argument</link>.
			The parsing routines for token and template arguments are largely
			hand-crafted, based on these primitives.</para>

		<para>Certain parsing operations are performed before control passes to
			the &sid; grammar.  As mentioned above, these include the processing
			of token and template applications.  The other important case concerns
			nested name specifiers.  For example, in:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">class A {
    class B {
    static int c ;
    } ;
} ;

int A::B::c = 0 ;</programlisting>

		<para>the qualified identifier <code>A::B::c</code> is split into two terminals,
			a nested name specifier, <code>A::B::</code>, and an identifier, <code>c</code>,
			which is looked up in the corresponding namespace.  Note that it is
			at this stage that name look-up occurs. An identifier can be mapped
			to one of a number of terminals, including  keywords, type names,
			namespace names and other identifiers, according to the result of
			this look-up.  If the look-up gives a macro then this is expanded
			at this stage.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="undefined-conversions">
		<title>Undefined conversions</title>

		<para>Several conversions in C and C++ can only be represented by undefined
			&tdf;.  For example, converting a pointer to an integer can only be
			represented in &tdf; by forming a union of the pointer and integer shapes,
			putting the pointer into the union and pulling the integer out.  Such
			conversions are tokenised.  Undefined conversions not mentioned below
			may be performed by combining those given with the standard, well-defined,
			conversions.</para>

		<para>The token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~ptr_to_ptr : ( ALIGNMENT a, ALIGNMENT b, EXP POINTER a ) -&gt; EXP POINTER b</programlisting>

		<para>is used to convert between two incompatible pointer types.  The first
			alignment describes the source pointer shape while the second describes
			the destination pointer shape.  Note that if the destination alignment
			is greater than the source alignment then the source pointer can be
			used in most &tdf; constructs in place of the destination pointer, so
			the use of <code>~ptr_to_ptr</code> can be omitted (the exception
			is <code>pointer_test</code> which requires equal alignments).  Base
			class pointer conversions are examples of these well-behaved, alignment
			preserving conversions.</para>

		<para>The tokens:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~f_to_pv : ( EXP PROC ) -&gt; EXP pv
~pv_to_f : ( EXP pv ) -&gt; EXP PROC</programlisting>

		<para>are used to convert pointers to functions to and from <code>void *</code>
			(these conversions are not allowed in ISO C/C++ but are in older dialects).</para>

		<para>The tokens:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~i_to_p : ( VARIETY v, ALIGNMENT a, EXP INTEGER v ) -&gt; EXP POINTER a
~p_to_i : ( ALIGNMENT a, VARIETY v, EXP POINTER a ) -&gt; EXP INTEGER v
~i_to_pv : ( VARIETY v, EXP INTEGER v ) -&gt; EXP pv
~pv_to_i : ( VARIETY v, EXP pv ) -&gt; EXP INTEGER v</programlisting>

		<para>are used to convert integers to and from <code>void *</code> and other
			pointers.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="div">
		<title>Integer division</title>

		<para>The precise form of the integer division and remainder operations
			in C and C++ is left unspecified with respect to the sign of the result
			if either operand is negative.  The tokens:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~div : ( EXP INTEGER v, EXP INTEGER v ) -&gt; EXP INTEGER v
~rem : ( EXP INTEGER v, EXP INTEGER v ) -&gt; EXP INTEGER v</programlisting>

		<para>are used to represent integer division and remainder.  They will map
			onto one of the pairs of &tdf; constructs, <code>div0</code> and <code>rem0</code>,
			<code>div1</code> and <code>rem1</code> or <code>div2</code> and
			<code>rem2</code>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="dynamic-initialisation">
		<title>Dynamic initialisation</title>

		<para>The dynamic initialisation of variables with static storage duration
			in C++ is implemented by means of the &tdf; <code>initial_value</code>
			construct.  However in order for the producer to maintain control
			over the order of initialisation, rather than each variable being
			initialised separately using <code>initial_value</code>, a single
			expression is created which initialises all the variables in a module,
			and this initialiser expression is used to initialise a single dummy
			variable using <code>initial_value</code>.  Note that, while this
			enables the variables within a single module to be initialised in
			the order in which they are defined, the order of initialisation between
			different modules is unspecified.</para>

		<para>The implementation needs to keep a list of those variables with static
			storage duration which have been initialised so that it can call the
			destructors for these objects at the end of the program. This is done
			by declaring a variable of shape:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.destr.type : () -&gt; SHAPE</programlisting>

		<para>for each such object with a non-trivial destructor.  Each element
			of an array is considered a distinct object.  Immediately after the
			variable has been initialised the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.destr.global : ( EXP pd, EXP POINTER c, EXP PROC ) -&gt; EXP TOP</programlisting>

		<para>is called to add the variable to the list of objects to be destroyed.
			The first argument is the address of the dummy variable just declared,
			the second is the address of the object to be destroyed, and the third
			is the destructor to be used.  In this way a list giving the objects
			to be destroyed, and the order in which to destroy them, is built
			up.  Note that partially constructed objects are destroyed within
			their constructors (see <xref linkend="constr"/>) so that only
			completely constructed objects need to be considered.</para>

		<para>The implementation also needs to ensure that it calls the destructors
			in this list at the end of the program, including calls of
			<code>exit</code>.  This is done by calling the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.destr.init : () -&gt; EXP TOP</programlisting>

		<para>at the start of each <code>initial_value</code> construct.  In the
			default implementation this uses <code>atexit</code> to register a
			function, <code>__TCPPLUS_term</code>, which calls the destructors.
			To aid alternative implementations the token:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~cpp.start : () -&gt; EXP TOP</programlisting>

		<para>is called at the start of the <code>main</code> function, however
			this has no effect in the default implementation.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="std">
		<title>The <code>std</code> namespace</title>

		<para>Several classes declared in the <code>std</code> namespace arise naturally
			as part of the C++ language specification.  These are as follows:</para>

		<table>
			<col align="left"/>
			<col align="left"/>

			<thead>
				<tr>
					<th>Type</th>
					<th>Purpose</th>
				</tr>
			</thead>

			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td><code>std::type_info</code></td>
					<td>type of <code>typeid</code> construct</td>
				</tr>


				<tr>
					<td><code>std::bad_cast</code></td>
					<td>thrown by <code>dynamic_cast</code> construct</td>
				</tr>


				<tr>
					<td><code>std::bad_typeid</code></td>
					<td>thrown by <code>typeid</code> construct</td>
				</tr>


				<tr>
					<td><code>std::bad_alloc</code></td>
					<td>thrown by <code>new</code> construct</td>
				</tr>


				<tr>
					<td><code>std::bad_exception</code></td>
					<td>used in exception specifications</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>

		<para>The definitions of these classes are found, when needed, by looking
			up the appropriate class name in the <code>std</code> namespace.
			Depending on the context, an error may be reported if the class is
			not found. It is possible to modify the namespace which is searched
			for these classes using the directive:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">#pragma TenDRA++ set std namespace : <emphasis>scope-name</emphasis></programlisting>

		<para>where <emphasis>scope-name</emphasis> can be an identifier giving a namespace name
			or <code>::</code>, indicating the global namespace.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="errors">
		<title>Error catalogue</title>

		<para>This section describes the error catalogue which lies at the heart
			of the C++ producer's error reporting routines.  The full
			error catalogue syntax is documented under &make_err.5;
			A typical entry in the catalogue is as follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="make_err">class_union_deriv ( CLASS_TYPE: ct )
{
    USAGE:              serious
    PROPERTIES:         ansi
    KEY (ISO)           &quot;9.5&quot;
    KEY (STANDARD)      &quot;The union '&quot;ct&quot;' can't have base classes&quot;
}</programlisting>

		<para>This defines an error, <code>class_union_deriv</code>, which takes
			a single parameter <code>ct</code> of type <code>CLASS_TYPE</code>.
			The severity of this error is <code>serious</code>; that is to say,
			a constraint error.  The error property <code>ansi</code> indicates
			that the error arises from the ISO C++ standard, the associated
			<code>ISO</code> key indicating section 9.5.  Finally the text to
			be printed for this error, including a reference to <code>ct</code>,
			is given.  Looking up section 9.5 in the ISO C++ standard reveals
			the corresponding constraint in paragraph 1:</para>
			<blockquote>A union shall not have base classes.</blockquote>
			<para>Each constraint within the ISO C++ standard has a corresponding error
			in this way.  The errors are named in a systematic fashion using the
			section names used in the draft standard.  For example, section 9.5
			is called <code>class.union</code>, so all the constraint errors arising
			from this section have names of the form <code>class_union_*</code>.
			These error names can be used in the &tdfc2pragma.5; low
			level directives such as:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">#pragma TenDRA++ error &quot;class_union_deriv&quot; <emphasis>allow</emphasis></programlisting>

		<para>to modify the error severity.  The effect of reducing the severity
			of a constraint error in this way is undefined.</para>

		<para>In addition to the obvious error severity levels, <code>serious</code>,
			<code>warning</code> and <code>none</code>, the error catalogue specifies
			a list of optional severity levels along with their default values.
			For example, the entry:</para>

		<programlisting language="make_err">link_incompat = serious</programlisting>

		<para>sets up an option named <code>link_incompat</code> which is a constraint
			error by default.  Errors with this severity, such as:</para>

		<programlisting language="make_err">dcl_stc_external ( LONG_ID: id, PTR_LOC: loc )
{
    USAGE:              link_incompat
    PROPERTIES:         ansi
    KEY (ISO)           &quot;7.1.1&quot;
    KEY (STANDARD)      &quot;'&quot;id&quot;' previously declared with external
             linkage (at &quot;loc&quot;)&quot;
}</programlisting>

		<para>are therefore constraint errors.  The severity associated with
			<code>link_incompat</code> can be modified either
			directly, using the directive:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">#pragma TenDRA++ option &quot;link_incompat&quot; <emphasis>allow</emphasis></programlisting>

		<para>or indirectly using the directive:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">#pragma TenDRA incompatible linkage <emphasis>allow</emphasis></programlisting>

		<para>the effect being to modify the severity of the associated error messages.</para>

		<para>The error catalogue is processed by a simple tool,
			<code>make_err</code>, which generates C code which is compiled into
			the C++ producer.  Each error in the catalogue is assigned a number
			(there are currently 873 errors in the catalogue) which gives an index
			into an automatically generated table of error information.  It is
			this error number, together with a list of error arguments, which
			forms the associated <link linkend="err"><code>ERROR</code> object</link>.
			<code>make_err</code> generates a macro for each error in the catalogue
			which takes arguments of the appropriate types (which may be statically
			checked) and creates an <code>ERROR</code> object.  For example, for
			the entry above this macro takes the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="cpp">ERROR ERR_class_union_deriv ( CLASS_TYPE ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>These macros hide the error catalogue numbers from the rest of the
			C++ producer.</para>

		<para>It is also possible to join a number of simple <code>ERROR</code>
			objects to form a single composite <code>ERROR</code>.  The severity
			of the composite error is the maximum of the severities of the component
			errors.  To this purpose a dummy error severity level <code>whatever</code>
			is introduced which is less severe than any other level.  This is
			intended for use with error messages which are only ever used to add
			information to existing errors, and which inherit their severity level
			from the main error.</para>

		<para>The text of a simple error message can be found in the table of error
			information.  The text contains certain escape sequences indicating
			where the error arguments are to be printed.  For example,
			<code>%1</code> indicates the second argument.  The error argument
			sorts - what is referred to as the error signature - is also stored
			in the table of error information as an array of characters, each
			corresponding to an <code>ERR_KEY_</code><emphasis>type</emphasis> macro.
			The producer
			defines printing routines for each of the types given by these values,
			and calls the appropriate routine to print the argument.</para>

		<para>There are several command-line options which can be used to modify
			the form in which the error message is printed.  The default format
			is as follows:</para>

		<screen>&quot;file.C&quot;, line 42: Error:
    [ISO 9.5]: The union 'U' can't have base classes.</screen>

	    <para>The ISO section number can be suppressed using <code>-m-s</code>.
	        The <code>-mc</code> option causes the source code line giving rise
	        to the error to be printed as part of the message, with <code>!!!!</code>
	        marking the position of the error within the line.  The <code>-me</code>
	        option causes the error name, <code>class_union_deriv</code>, to be
	        printed as part of the message.  The <code>-ml</code> option causes
	        the full file location, including the list of <code>#include</code>
	        directives used in reaching the file, to be printed.  The <code>-mt</code>
	        option causes <code>typedef</code> names to be used when printing
	        types, rather than expanding to the type definition.</para>
    </section>

</chapter>

