<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<news>
	<entry>
		<date>2007-06-02</date>

		<content>Tagged version 1.10</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>2007-06-01</date>

		<content>Restructured for initial stand-alone release.
			The only user-visible change here is that -? is replaced
			with -h. An example of using sid with lex has been added.
			This is the first release of sid stand-alone under
			tendra.org.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1996-02-29</date>

		<content>Added support for an unreachable code macro
			(instead of a comment) in the C output languages.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-07-22</date>

		<content>Froze version 1.8.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-07-19</date>

		<content>Added assignment as an alternative to identity
			binding.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-07-14</date>

		<content>Added initialisers for non local variables.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-07-01</date>

		<content>Added support for non local variables within
			rules. Froze version 1.7.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-06-22</date>

		<content>Added support for language specific options.
			Added options to control prototyping, use of numeric
			identifiers and casting of substituted parameters for
			C output language.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-06-16</date>

		<content>Added support for call by reference and action
			parameter mutation information.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-05-27</date>

		<content>Changed the format of the C definition file to
			provide a parameter assignment operation (this should
			have been in from the start for consistent semantics).
			Also, the prefix section, maps section and all three
			assignment operation sections are now optional.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-05-26</date>

		<content>Improved error messages.  Made dump file be updated
			with information from the phase that failed in the case
			of an error (this is not always useful though - the
			grammar may be in a useless state after a failed transform;
			left recursion elimination is particularly bad for this).</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-05-17</date>

		<content>Added a stricter ANSI C language that uses numeric
			identifiers to keep the identifier length below 32
			characters. Froze version 1.6.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-05-16</date>

		<content>Changed the syntax of the input files so that the
			grammar looks more like a conventional programming language.
			Removed basics. Added a header file to the C language
			output.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-27</date>

		<content>Added "--show-errors" option to show the error
			table status, and a "--help" option to show the command
			line syntax. Froze version 1.5.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-26</date>

		<content>Changed command line syntax to be compatible with
			the TDF linker.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-25</date>

		<content>Froze version 1.4.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-28</date>

		<content>Added "#line" directives to header and trailer.
			Ensured that there is always a newline at the end of a
			code block.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-11</date>

		<content>Added support for anonymous rules and in alternative
			exception handlers.  Fixed cycle detection routine used
			in needed function computation. Froze version 1.3.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-08</date>

		<content>Changed syntax of code blocks in action file.
			SID now inlines all actions, basics, assignments etc.
			and performs the substitutions. Substitutions allow for
			identifier and label substitution, as well as exception
			raising.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-04</date>

		<content>Put name identifiers in a separate namespace.
			Stopped it being an error if the "-version" switch
			is used with no files specified.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-02</date>

		<content>Added a test mode language.
			Froze version 1.2.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-01</date>

		<content>Added exception handling instead of old error
			reporting mechanism.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-18</date>

		<content>Added option of inlining rules that only contain
			basics.  Changed output routines, so that parameters
			and results of inlined functions are substituted, rather
			than created and assigned to.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-17</date>

		<content>Changed identifier prefixes.  Made grammar printing
			mark inlinable rules with a '+'.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-16</date>

		<content>Added predicate support.  Improved factoring
			to allow alternatives with the same dataflow, but
			different names to be factored.  Allowed types to be
			defined that were only the result types of terminals.
			Stopped rules being declared as entry points to the
			grammar multiple times.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-04</date>

		<content>Fixed the cycle detection routines used in tail
			recursion detection. Froze version 1.1.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1994-01-02</date>

		<content>Fixed the cycle detection routines used in left
			recursion detection.  Fixed bug in outputting code
			for see through alternatives.  Sorted error lists to
			make comparisons easier.  Modified grammar printing
			to mark tail calls.</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<date>1993-12-22</date>

		<content>Initial version of the new sid.  Adds dataflow
			and marginally improved error handling to the original
			version of sid.  Also fixes some bugs in the algorithms
			used in the earlier version of sid. Froze version
			1.0.</content>
	</entry>
</news>

