<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
  $Id$
-->

<chapter>
	<title>Control Flow within procedures</title>

	<section>
		<title>Unconditional flow</title>

		<section id="sequence">
			<title>sequence</title>

			<para>To perform a sequential set of operations in TDF, one uses the
				constructor sequence:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">statements: LIST(EXP)
result:     EXP x
            -&gt; EXP x</programlisting>

			<para>Each of the <code>statements</code> are evaluated in order,
				throwing away their results. Then, <code>result</code> is
				evaluated and its result is the result of the sequence.</para>

			<para>A translator is free to rearrange the order of evaluation if
				there is no observable difference other than in time or space.
				This applies anywhere I say &ldquo;something is evaluated and then ...&rdquo;.
				We find this kind of statement in definitions of local variables
				in <link linkend="defining-and-using-locals">section 5.3</link>,
				and in the controlling parts of the conditional constructions
				below.</para>

			<para>For a more precise discussion of allowable reorderings see
				(<!-- <fix>S7.14</fix> -->) .</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="conditional-flow">
		<title>Conditional flow</title>

		<section id="labelled">
			<title>labelled, make_label</title>

			<para>All simple changes of flow of control within a TDF procedure
				are done by jumps or branches to LABELs, mirroring what actually
				happens in most computers. There are three constructors which
				introduce LABELs; the most general is labelled which allows
				arbitrary jumping between its component EXPs:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">placelabs_intro: LIST(LABEL)
starter:         EXP x
places:          LIST(EXP)
                 -&gt; EXP w</programlisting>

			<para>Each of the EXPs in <code>places</code> is labelled by the
				corresponding LABEL in <code>placelabs_intro</code>; these LABELs
				are constructed by make_label applied to a TDFINT uniquely drawn
				from the LABEL name-space introduced by the enclosing PROPS. The
				evaluation starts by evaluating <code>starter</code>; if this runs
				to completion the result of the labelled is the result of
				<code>starter.</code> If there is some jump to a LABEL in
				<code>placelabs_intro</code> then control passes to the
				corresponding EXP in <code>places</code> and so on.  If any of
				these EXPS runs to completion then its result is the result of the
				labelled; hence the SHAPE of the result, w, is the LUB of the
				SHAPEs of the component EXPs.</para>

			<para>Note that control does not automatically pass from one EXP to
				the next; if this is required the appropriate EXP must end with an
				explicit goto.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="goto">
			<title>goto, make_local_lv, goto_local_lv, long_jump,
				return_to_label</title>

			<para>The unconditional goto is the simplest method of jumping. In
				common with all the methods of jumping using LABELs, its LABEL
				parameter must have been introduced in an enclosing construction,
				like labelled, which scopes it.</para>

			<para>One can also pick up a label value of SHAPE POINTER {code}
				(usually implemented as a program address) using make_local_lv for
				later use by an "indirect jump" such as goto_local_lv . Here the
				same prohibition holds - the construction which introduced the
				LABEL must still be active.</para>

			<para>The construction goto_local_lv only permits one to jump within
				the current procedure; if one wished to do a jump out of a
				procedure into a calling one, one uses long_jump which requires a
				pointer to the destination frame (produced by current_env in the
				destination procedure) as well as the label value. If a long_jump
				is made to a label, only those local TAGs which have been defined
				with a visible ACCESS are guaranteed to have preserved their
				values; the translator could allocate the other TAGs in scope as
				registers whose values are not necessarily preserved.</para>

			<para>A slightly "shorter" long jump is given by return_to_label.
				Here the destination of the jump must a label value in the calling
				procedure. Usually this value would be passed as parameter of the
				call to provide an alternative exit to the procedure.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="integer_test">
			<title>integer_test, NTEST</title>

			<para>Conditional branching is provided by the various _test
				constructors, one for each primitive SHAPE except BITFIELD.  I
				shall use integer_test as the paradigm for them all:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">nt:   NTEST
dest: LABEL
arg1: EXP INTEGER(v)
arg2: EXP INTEGER(v)
      -&gt; EXP TOP</programlisting>

			<para>The NTEST <code>nt</code> chooses a dyadic test (e.g. =, &gt;=,
				&lt;, etc.) that is to be applied to the results of evaluating
				<code>arg1</code> and <code>arg2</code>. If <code>arg1</code>
				<code>nt</code> <code>arg2</code> then the result is TOP;
				otherwise control passes to the LABEL <code>dest</code>.  In other
				words, integer_test acts like an assertion where if the assertion
				is false, control passes to the LABEL instead of continuing in the
				normal fashion.</para>

			<para>Some of the constructors for NTESTs are disallowed for some
				_tests (e.g. proc_test) while others are redundant for some
				_tests; for example, not_greater_than is the same as
				less_than_or_equal for all except possibly floating_test. where
				the use of NaNs (in the IEEE sense) as operands may give different
				results.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="case">
			<title>case</title>

			<para>There are only two other ways of changing flow of control
				using LABELs. One arises in ERROR_TREATMENTs which will be dealt
				with in the arithmetic operations. The other is case:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">exhaustive: BOOL
control:    EXP INTEGER(v)
branches:   LIST(CASELIM)
            -&gt; EXP (exhaustive ? BOTTOM : TOP)</programlisting>

			<para>Each CASELIM is constructed using make_caselim:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">branch: LABEL
lower:  SIGNED_NAT
upper:  SIGNED_NAT
        -&gt; CASELIM</programlisting>

			<para>In the case construction, the <code>control</code> EXP is
				evaluated and tested to see whether its value lies inclusively
				between some <code>lower</code> and <code>upper</code> in the list
				of CASELIMs. If so, control passes to the corresponding
				<code>branch</code>. The order in which these tests are performed
				is undefined, so it is probably best if the tests are exclusive.
				The exhaustive flag being true asserts that one of the branches
				will be taken and so the SHAPE of the result is BOTTOM.
				Otherwise, if none of the branches are taken, its SHAPE is TOP and
				execution carries on normally.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="conditional">
			<title>conditional, repeat</title>

			<para>Besides labelled, two other constructors, conditional and
				repeat, introduce LABELs which can be used with the various jump
				instructions.  Both can be expressed as labelled, but have extra
				constraints which make assertions about the use of the LABELs
				introduced and could usually be translated more efficiently; hence
				producers are advised to use them where possible. A conditional
				expression or statement would usually be done using conditional:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">alt_label_intro: LABEL
first:           EXP x
alt:             EXP y
                 -&gt; EXP(LUB(x, y))</programlisting>

			<para>Here <code>first</code> is evaluated; if it terminates normally,
				its result is the result of the conditional. If a jump to
				<code>alt_label_intro</code> occurs then <code>alt</code> is
				evaluated and its result is the result of the conditional.
				Clearly, this, so far, is just the same as
				labelled((<code>alt_label_intro</code>), <code>first</code>,
				(<code>alt</code>)). However, conditional imposes the constraint
				that <code>alt</code> cannot use <code>alt_label_intro</code>. All
				jumps to <code>alt_label_intro</code> are "forward jumps" - a
				useful property to know in a translator.</para>

			<para>Obviously, this kind of conditional is rather different to
				those found in traditional high-level languages which usually have
				three components, a boolean expression, a then-part and an
				else-part. Here, the <code>first</code> component includes both
				the boolean expression and the then-part; usually we find that it
				is a sequence of the tests (branching to
				<code>alt_label_intro</code>) forming the boolean expression
				followed by the else-part. This formulation means that HLL
				constructions like "andif" and "orelse" do not require special
				constructions in TDF.</para>

			<para>A simple loop can be expressed using repeat:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">repeat_label_intro: LABEL
start:              EXP TOP
body:               EXP y
                    -&gt; EXP y</programlisting>

			<para>The EXP <code>start</code> is evaluated, followed by
				<code>body</code> which is labelled by
				<code>repeat_label_intro</code>. If a jump to
				<code>repeat_label_intro</code> occurs in <code>body</code>, then
				<code>body</code> is re-evaluated. If <code>body</code> terminates
				normally then its result is the result of the repeat. This is just
				the same as:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">labelled((repeat_label_intro), sequence((start), goto(repeat_label_intro)), (body))</programlisting>

			<para>except that no jumps to <code>repeat_label_intro</code> are
				allowed in <code>start</code> - a useful place to do
				initialisations for the loop.</para>

			<para>Just as with conditionals, the tests for the continuing or
				breaking the loop are included in <code>body</code> and require no
				special constructions.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="exceptional-flow">
		<title>Exceptional flow</title>

		<para>A further way of changing the flow of control in a TDF program
			is by means of exceptions. TDF exceptions currently arise from three
			sources - overflow in arithmetic operations with trap
			ERROR_TREATMENT(see
			<link linkend="error_treatment">section 8.1.1</link>), an attempt to
			access a value via a nil pointer using assign_with_mode,
			contents_with_mode or move_some(see
			<link linkend="transfer_mode-operations">section 7.3</link>) or a
			stack overflow on procedure entry with PROCPROPS check_stack(see
			<link linkend="procprops">section 5.2.2</link>) or a
			local_alloc_check.</para>

		<para>Each of these exceptions have an ERROR_CODE ascribed to them,
			namely overflow, nil_access and stack_overflow. Each ERROR_CODE can
			be made into a distinct NAT by means of the constructor error_val;
			these NATs could be used, for example, to discriminate the different
			kinds of errors using a case construction.</para>

		<para>When one of these exceptions is raised, the translator will
			arrange that a TOKEN, ~Throw, is called with the appropriate
			ERROR_CODE as its (sole) parameter. Given that every language has a
			different way of both characterising and handling exceptions, the
			exact expansion of ~Throw must be given by the producer for that
			language - usually it will involve doing a long_jump to some label
			specifying a signal handler and translating the ERROR_CODE into its
			language-specific representation.</para>

		<para>The expansion of ~Throw forms part of the language specific
			environment required for the translation of TDF derived from the
			language, just as the exact shape of FILE must be given for the
			translation of C.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

