<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter id="tdf-expansions-of-offsets">
	<title>&tdf; expansions of offsets</title>

	<section id="compound-offsets">
		<title>Offsets within compound types</title>

		<para>Consider the C structure defined by:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">typedef struct{ int i; double d; char c;} mystruct;</programlisting>

		<para>Given that sh_int, sh_char and sh_double are the SHAPEs for int, char
			and double, the SHAPE of <code>mystruct</code> is constructed by:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">SH_mystruct = compound(S_c)</programlisting>

		<para>where:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">S_c = offset_add(O_c, shape_offset(sh_char))</programlisting>

		<para>where:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">O_c = offset_pad(alignment(sh_char), S_d)</programlisting>

		<para>where:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">S_d = offset_add(O_d, shape_offset(sh_double))</programlisting>

		<para>where:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">O_d = offset_pad(alignment(sh_double), S_i)</programlisting>

		<para>where: <footnote>
			<para>I could equally have given simply shape_offset(sh_int) for
				S_i, but the above formulation is more uniform with respect to
				selection OFFSETs.</para>
			</footnote></para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">S_i = offset_add(O_i, shape_offset(sh_int))</programlisting>

		<para>and:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">O_i = offset_zero(alignment(sh_int))</programlisting>

		<para>Each of S_c, S_d and S_i gives the minimum "size" of the space
			required to upto and including the field c, d and i respectively. Each
			of O_c, O_d and O_i gives the OFFSET "displacement" from a pointer to
			a <code>mystruct</code> required to select the fields c, d and i
			respectively. The C program fragment:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">mystruct s;
.... s.d = 1.0; ...</programlisting>
        
		<para>would translate to something like:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">variable(empty, tag_s, make_value(compound(S_c)),
         sequence(...,
         assign(add_to_ptr(obtain_tag(tag_s), O_d), 1.0),
         ...
         )
        )</programlisting>
        
		<para>Each of the OFFSET expressions above are ideal candidates for
			tokenisation; a producer would probably define tokens for each of them
			and use exp_apply_token to expand them at each of their uses.</para>

		<para>From the definition, we find that:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">S_c = shape_offset(SH_mystruct)
			i.e. an OFFSET(alignment(sh_int) xc8  alignment(sh_char) xc8  alignment(sh_double), {})</programlisting>

		<para>This would not be the OFFSET required to describe
			<code>sizeof(mystruct)</code> in C, since this is defined to be the
			difference between successive elements an array of
			<code>mystruct</code>s. The <code>sizeof</code> OFFSET would have to
			pad S_c to the alignment of SH_mystruct:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">offset_pad(alignment(SH_mystruct), S_c)</programlisting>

		<para>This is the OFFSET that one would use to compute the displacement of
			an element of an array of <code>mystruct</code>s using offset_mult
			with the index.</para>

		<para>The most common use of OFFSETs is in add_to_ptr to compute the
			address of a structure or array element. Looking again at its
			signature in a slightly different form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">arg1: EXP POINTER(y xc8 A)
arg2: EXP OFFSET(y, z)
      -&gt; EXP POINTER(z)
      ... for any ALIGNMENT A</programlisting>

		<para>one sees that <code>arg2</code> can measure an OFFSET from a value of
			a "smaller" alignment than the value pointed at by <code>arg1</code>.
			If <code>arg2</code> were O_d, for example, then <code>arg1</code>
			could be a pointer to any structure of the form struct {int i, double
			d,...} not just <code>mystruct</code>. The general principle is that
			an OFFSET to a field constructed in this manner is independent of any
			fields after it, corresponding to normal usage in both languages and
			machines. A producer for a language which conflicts with this would
			have to produce less obvious &tdf;, perhaps by re-ordering the fields,
			padding the offsets by later alignments or taking maxima of the sizes
			of the fields.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="bitfield-offsets">
		<title>Bitfield offsets</title>

		<para>Bitfield offsets are governed by rather stricter rules. In order
			to extract or assign a bitfield, we have to find an integer variety
			which entirely contains the bitfield. Suppose that we wished to
			extract a bitfield by:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">bitfield_contents(v, p:POINTER(X), b:OFFSET(Y, B))</programlisting>

		<para>Y must be an alignment(I) where I is some integer SHAPE, contained
			in X. Further, this has to be equivalent to:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">bitfield_contents(v, add_ptr(p, d:OFFSET(Y,Y)), b':OFFSET(Y, B))</programlisting>

		<para>for some d and b' such that:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">offset_pad(v, shape_offset(I)) &gt;= b'</programlisting>
				  
		<para>and</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">offset_add(offset_pad(v, offset_mult(d, sizeof(I)), b') = b</programlisting>

		<para>Clearly, we have a limitation on the length of bitfields to the
			maximum integer variety available; in addition, we cannot have a
			bitfield which overlaps two such varieties.</para>

		<para>The difficulties inherent in this may be illustrated by
			attempting to construct an array of bitfields using the nof
			constructor. Assuming a standard architecture, we find that we
			cannot usefully define an object of SHAPE nof(N,
			bitfield(bfvar_bits(b, M))) without padding this shape out to some
			integer variety which can contain M bits. In addition, they can only
			be usefully indexed (using bitfield_contents)either if M is some
			power of 2 or M*N is less than the length of the maximum integer
			variety. Thus a producer must be sure that these conditions hold if
			he is to generate and index this object simply. Even here he is in
			some dificulty, since he does not know the representational
			varieties of the integers available to him; also it is difficult for
			him to ensure that the alignment of the entire array is in some
			sense minimal. Similar difficulties occur with bitfields in
			structures - they are not restricted to arrays.</para>

		<para>The solution to this conundrum in its full generality requires
			knowledge of the available representational varieties. Particular
			languages have restrictions which means that sub-optimal solutions
			will satisfy its specification on the use of bitfields.  For
			example, C is satisfied with bitfields of maximum length 32 and
			simple alignment constraints. However, for the general optimal
			solution, I can see no reasonable alternative to the installer
			defining some tokens to produce bitfield offsets which are
			guaranteed to obey the alignment rules and also give optimal packing
			of fields and alignments of the total object for the platform in
			question. I believe that three tokens are sufficient to do this;
			these are analogous to the constructors offset_zero, offset_pad and
			offset_mult with ordinary alignments and their signatures could be:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~Bitfield_offset_zero:
n:        NAT
issigned: BOOL
          -&gt; EXP OFFSET(A, bfvar_bits(issigned, n))</programlisting>
          
		<para>Here the result is a zero offset to the bitfield with &ldquo;minimum&rdquo;
			integer variety alignment A.</para>
  
		<programlisting language="tdf">~Bitfield_offset_pad:
n:        NAT
issigned: BOOL
sh:       SHAPE
          -&gt; EXP OFFSET(alignment(sh) xc8  A, bfvar_bits(issigned, n))</programlisting>
          
		<para>Here the result is the shape_offset of <code>sh</code> padded with
			the `minimum' alignment A so that it can accomodate the bitfield.
			Note that this may involve padding <code>sh</code> with the
			alignment of the maximum integer variety if there are not enough
			bits left at the end of <code>sh.</code></para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">~Bitfield_offset_mult:
n:        NAT
issigned: BOOL
ind:      EXP INTEGER(v)
          -&gt; EXP OFFSET(A, bfvar_bits(issigned, n))</programlisting>
          
		<para>Here the result is an offset which gives the displacement of
			<code>ind</code>th element of an array of <code>n</code>-bit
			bitfields with `minimum' alignment A. Note that this will correspond
			to a normal multiplication only if <code>n</code> is a power of 2 or
			<code>ind</code> * <code>n</code> &lt;= length of the maximum
			integer variety.</para>

		<para>These tokens can be expressed in &tdf; if the lengths of the
			available varieties are known, i.e., they are installer defined.<footnote>
				<para>For most architectures, these definition are dependent only
					on a few constants such as the maximum length of bitfield.,
					expessed as tokens for the target. The precise specification of
					such target dependent tokens is of current interest outside the
					scope of this document.</para>
			</footnote>
			They ought to be used in place of offset_zero, offset_pad and
			offset_mult whereever the alignment or shape (required to construct
			a SHAPE or an argument to the bitfield constructs) is a pure
			bitfield.  The constructor nof should never be used on a pure
			bitfield; instead it should be replaced by:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">S = compound(~Bitfield_offset_mult(M, b, N))</programlisting>
		  
		<para>to give a shape, S, representing an array of N M-bit bitfields. This
			may not be just N*M bits; for example ~Bitfield_offset_mult may be
			implemented to pack an array of 3-bit bitfields as 10 fields to a
			32-bit word. In any case, one would expect that normal rules for
			offset arithmetic are preserved, e.g.</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">offset_add(~Bitfield_offset_pad(M, b, S), size(bitfield(bfvar_bits(b, N)))) =
    ~Bitfield_offset_mult(M, b, N + 1)

where size(X) = offset_pad(alignment(X), shape_offset(X))</programlisting>
	</section>
</chapter>

