<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
  $Id$
-->

<chapter>
	<title>Operations</title>

	<para>Most of the arithmetic operations of &tdf; have familiar analogues
		in standard languages and processors.  They differ principally in how
		error conditions (e.g. numeric overflow) are handled. There is a wide
		diversity in error handling in both languages and processors, so &tdf;
		tries to reduce it to the simplest primitive level compatible with
		their desired operation in languages and their implementation on
		processors.  Before delving into the details of error handling, it is
		worthwhile revisiting the SHAPEs and ranges in arithmetic
		VARIETYs.</para>

		<section id="S67">
			<title>VARIETY and overflow</title>

			<para>An INTEGER VARIETY, for example, is defined by some range of
				signed natural numbers. A translator will fit this range into some
				possibly larger range which is convenient for the processor in
				question. For example, the integers with variety(1,10) would
				probably be represented as unsigned characters with range (0..255),
				a convenient representation for both storage and arithmetic.</para>

			<para>The question then arises of what is meant by overflow in an
				operation which is meant to deliver an integer of this VARIETY - is
				it when the integer result is outside the range (1..10) or outside
				the range (0..255)? For purely pragmatic reasons, &tdf; chooses the
				latter - the result is overflowed when it is outside its
				representational range (0..255). If the program insists that it must
				be within (1..10), then it can always test for it. If the program
				uses the error handling mechanism and the result is outside (1..10)
				but still within the representational limits, then, in order for the
				program to be portable, then the error handling actions must in some
				sense be "continuous" with the normal action. This would not be the
				case if, for example, the value was used to index an array with
				bounds (1..10), but will usually be the case where the value is used
				in further arithmetic operations which have similar error handling.
				The arithmetic will continue to give the mathematically correct
				result provided the representational bounds are not exceeded.</para>

			<para>The limits in a VARIETY are there to provide a guide to its
				representation, and not to give hard limits to its possible values.
				This choice is consistent with the general &tdf; philosophy of how
				exceptions are to be treated. If, for example, one wishes to do
				array-bound checking, then it must be done by explicit tests on the
				indices and jumping to some exception action if they fail.
				Similarly, explicit tests can be made on an integer value, provided
				its representational limits are not exceeded. It is unlikely that a
				translator could produce any more efficient code, in general, if the
				tests were implicit. The representational limits can be exceeded in
				arithmetic operations, so facilities are provided to either to
				ignore it, to allow one to jump to a label, or to obey a &tdf;
				exception handler if it happens.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="error_treatment">
			<title>ERROR_TREATMENT</title>

			<para>Taking integer addition as an example, plus has signature:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">ov_err: ERROR_TREATMENT
arg1:   EXP INTEGER(v)
arg2:   EXP INTEGER(v)
        -&gt; EXP INTEGER(v)</programlisting>

		<para>The result of the addition has the same integer VARIETY as its
			parameters.  If the representational bounds of
			<code>v</code> are exceeded, then the action taken
			depends on the ERROR_TREATMENT <code>ov_err</code>.</para>

		<para>The ERROR_TREATMENT, impossible, is an assertion by the
			producer that overflow will not occur; on its head be it if it
			does.</para>

		<para>The ERROR_TREATMENTS continue and wrap give "fixup" values for
			the result. For continue the fixup value is undefined. For wrap,
			the the answer will be modulo 2 to the power of the number of bits
			in the representational variety.Thus, integer arithmetic with byte
			representational variety is done modulo 256. This just corresponds
			to what happens in most processors and, incidentally, the
			definition of C.</para>

		<para>The ERROR_TREATMENT that one would use if one wished to jump
			to a label is error_jump:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">lab: LABEL
     -&gt; ERROR_TREATMENT</programlisting>

		<para>A branch to <code>lab</code> will occur if the result
			overflows.</para>

		<para>The ERROR_TREATMENT, trap(overflow) will raise a &tdf;
			exception(see <link linkend="exceptional-flow">section 6.3</link>)
			with ERROR_CODE overflow if overflow occurs.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S69">
		<title>Division and remainder</title>

		<para>The various constructors in involving integer division (e.g.
			div1, rem1) have two ERROR_TREATMENT parameters, one for overflow
			and one for divide-by-zero e.g. div1 is:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">div_by_zero_error: ERROR_TREATMENT
ov_err:            ERROR_TREATMENT
arg1:              EXP INTEGER(v)
arg2:              EXP INTEGER(v)
                   -&gt; EXP INTEGER(v)</programlisting>

		<para>There are two different kinds of division operators (with
			corresponding remainder operators) defined. The operators div2 and
			rem2 are those generally implemented directly by processor
			instructions giving the sign of the remainder the same as the sign
			of the quotient. The other pair, div1 and rem1, is less commonly
			implemented in hardware, but have rather more consistent
			mathematical properties; here the sign of remainder is the same as
			the sign of divisor. Thus, div1(x, 2) is the same as shift_right(x,
			1) which is only true for div2 if x is positive. The two pairs of
			operations give the same results if both operands have the same
			sign. The constructors div0 and rem0 allow the translator to choose
			whichever of the two forms of division is convenient - the producer
			is saying that he does not care which is used, as long as they are
			pairwise consistent. The precise definition of the divide operations
			is given in (<!-- <fix>S7.4</fix> -->).</para>
	</section>

	<section id="change_variety">
		<title>change_variety</title>

		<para>Conversions between the various INTEGER varieties are provided
			for by change_variety:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">ov_err: ERROR_TREATMENT
r:      VARIETY
arg1:   EXP INTEGER(v)
        -&gt; EXP INTEGER(r)</programlisting>

		<para>If the value <code>arg1</code> is outside the limits of the
			representational variety of <code>r</code>, then the ERROR_TREATMENT
			<code>ov_err</code> will be invoked.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S71">
		<title>and, or, not, xor</title>

		<para>The standard logical operations, and, not, or and xor are
			provided for all integer varieties.  Since integer varieties are
			defined to be represented in twos-complement the result of these
			operations are well defined.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S72">
		<title>Floating-point operations, ROUNDING_MODE</title>

		<para>All of the floating-point (including complex) operations include
			ERROR-TREATMENTs. If the result of a floating-point operation cannot
			be represented in the desired FLOATING_VARIETY, the error treatment
			is invoked. If the ERROR_TREATMENT is wrap or impossible, the result
			is undefined; otherwise the jump operates in the same way as for
			integer operations. Both floating_plus and floating_mult are defined
			as n-ary operations. In general, floating addition and
			multiplication are not associative, but a producer may not care
			about the order in which they are to be performed. Making them
			appear as though they were associative allows the translator to
			choose an order which is convenient to the hardware.</para>

		<para>Conversions from integer to floating are done by float_int and
			from floating to integers by round_with_mode . This latter
			constructor has a parameter of SORT ROUNDING_MODE which effectively
			gives the IEEE rounding mode to be applied to the float to produce
			its integer result.</para>

		<para>One can extract the real and imaginary parts of a complex
			FLOATING using real_part and imaginary_part. A complex FLOATING can
			be constructed using make_complex. Normal complex arithmetic applies
			to all the other FLOATING constructors except for those explicitly
			excluded (eg floating_abs, floating_max etc.)</para>
	</section>

	<section id="change_bitfield_to_int">
		<title>change_bitfield_to_int, change_int_to_bitfield</title>

		<para>There are two bit-field operation, change_bitfield_to_int and
			change_int_to_bitfield to transform between bit-fields and integers.
			If the varieties do not fit the result is undefined; the producer
			can always get it right.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="make_compound">
		<title>make_compound, make_nof, n_copies</title>

		<para>There is one operation to make values of COMPOUND SHAPE,
			make_compound:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">arg1: EXP OFFSET(base, y)
arg2: LIST(EXP)
      -&gt; EXP COMPOUND(sz)</programlisting>

		<para>The OFFSET <code>arg1</code> is evaluated as a translate-time
			constant to give <code>sz</code>, the size of the compound
			object.  The EXPs of arg2 are alternately OFFSETs (also
			translate-time constants) and values which will be placed at those
			offsets. This constructor is used to construct values given by
			structure displays; in C, these only occur with constant
			<constant>val[i]</constant> in global definitions. It is also used
			to provide union injectors; here <code>sz</code> would be
			the size of the union and the list would probably two elements with
			the first being an offset_zero.</para>

		<para>Constant sized array values may be constructed using make_nof,
			make_nof_int, and n_copies. Again, they only occur in C as constants
			in global definitions.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

