<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter>
	<title>Procedures and Locals</title>

	<para>All procedures in &tdf; are essentially global; the only values
		which are accessible from the body of a procedure are those which are
		derived from global TAGs (introduced by TAGDEFs or TAGDECs), local
		TAGs defined within the procedure and parameter TAGs of the
		procedure.</para>

	<para>All executable code in &tdf; will arise from an EXP PROC made by
		either make_proc or make_general_proc. They differ in their treatment
		of how space for the actual parameters of a call is managed; in
		particular, is it the caller or the callee which deallocates the
		parameter space?</para>

	<para>With make_proc, this management is conceptually done by the caller
		at an apply_proc; i.e. the normal C situation. This suffers from the
		limitation that tail-calls of procedures are then only possible in
		restricted circumstances (e.g. the space for the parameters of the
		tail-call must be capable of being included in caller's parameters)
		and could only be implemented as an optimisation within a translator.
		A producer could not predict these circumstances in a machine
		independent manner, whether or not it knew that a tail-call was
		valid.</para>

	<para>An alternative would be to make the management of parameter space
		the responsibility of the called procedure. Rather than do this,
		make_general_proc (and apply_general_proc) splits the parameters into
		two sets, one whose allocation is the responsibility of the caller and
		the other whose allocation is dealt with by the callee. This allows an
		explicit tail_call to be made to a procedure with new callee
		parameters; the caller parameters for the tail_call will be the same
		as (or some initial subset of) the caller parameters of the procedure
		containing the tail_call .</para>

	<para>A further refinement of make_general_proc is to allow access to
		the caller parameter space in a postlude at the call of the procedure
		using an apply_general_proc. This allows simple implementations of Ada
		out_parameters, or more generally, multiple results of
		procedures.</para>

	<section>
		<title>make_proc and apply_proc</title>

		<para>The make_proc constructor has signature:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">result_shape: SHAPE
params_intro: LIST(TAGSHACC)
var_intro:    OPTION(TAGACC)
body:         EXP BOTTOM
              -&gt; EXP PROC</programlisting>
  
		<para>The <code>params_intro</code> and <code>var_intro</code> parameters
			introduce the formal parameters of the procedure which may be used
			in <code>body</code>. The procedure result will have SHAPE
			<code>result_shape</code> and will be usually given by some return
			construction within <code>body</code>. The basic model is that space
			will be provided to copy actual parameters (into space supplied by
			some apply_proc) by value into these formals and the body will treat
			this space effectively as local variables.</para>

		<para>Each straightforward formal parameter is introduced by an
			auxiliary SORT TAGSHACC using make_tagshacc:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">sha:        SHAPE
opt_access: OPTION(LIST(ACCESS))
tg_intro:   TAG POINTER(alignment(sha))
            -&gt; TAGSHACC</programlisting>

		<para>Within <code>body</code>, the formal will be accessed using
			<code>tg_intro</code>; it is always considered to be a pointer to
			the space of SHAPE <code>sha</code> allocated by apply_proc, hence
			the pointer SHAPE.</para>

		<para>For example, if we had a simple procedure with one integer
			parameter, <code>var_intro</code> would be empty and
			<varname>params_intro</varname> might be:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">params_intro = make_tagshacc(integer(v), empty, make_tag(13))</programlisting>

		<para>Then, TAG 13 from the enclosing UNIT's name-space is identified with
			the formal parameter with SHAPE POINTER(INTEGER(v)). Any use of
			obtain_tag(make_tag(13)) in <code>body</code> will deliver a pointer
			to the integer parameter. I shall return to the meaning of
			<code>opt_access</code> and the ramifications of the scope and extent
			of TAGs involved in conjunction with local declarations in
			<link linkend="identify-variable">section 5.3.1</link>.</para>

		<para>Procedures, whether defined by make_proc or make_general_proc,
			will usually terminate and deliver its result with a return:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">arg1: EXP x
		-&gt; EXP BOTTOM</programlisting>

		<para>Here <varname>x</varname> must be identical to the
			<code>result_shape</code> of the call of the procedure There may be
			several returns in body; and the SHAPE <varname>x</varname> in each
			will be the same. Some languages allow different types to be returned
			depending on the particular call.  The producer must resolve this
			issue. For example, C allows one to deliver void if the resulting
			value is not used.  In &tdf; a dummy value must be provided at the
			return; for example make_value(<code>result_shape</code>).</para>

		<para>Note that the <code>body</code> has SHAPE bottom since all
			possible terminations to a procedure have SHAPE BOTTOM..</para>

		<para>Procedures defined by make_proc are called using
			apply_proc:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">result_shape: SHAPE
arg1:         EXP PROC
arg2:         LIST(EXP)
varparam:     OPTION(EXP)
              -&gt; EXP result_shape</programlisting>

		<para>Here <code>arg1</code> is the procedure to be called and
			<code>arg2</code> gives the actual parameters. There must be at least
			as many actual parameters as given (with the same SHAPE) in the
			<code>params_intro</code> of the corresponding make_proc for arg1.
			<footnote>
				<para>The vararg construction in C are implemented by giving more
					actuals than formals; the extra parameters are accessed by offset
					arithmetic with a pointer to a formal, using parameter_alignment
					to pad the offsets.</para>
			</footnote>
			The values of <code>arg2</code> will be copied into space managed by
			caller.</para>

		<para>The SHAPE of the result of the call is given by
			<code>result_shape</code> which must be identical to the
			<code>result_shape</code> of the make_proc.</para>

		<section id="vartag-varparam">
			<title>vartag, varparam</title>

			<para>Use of the <code>var_intro</code> OPTION in make_proc and the
				corresponding <code>varparam</code> in apply_proc allows one to
				have a parameter of any SHAPE, possibly differing from call to
				call where the actual SHAPE can be deduced in some way by the
				<code>body</code> of the make_proc . One supplies an extra actual
				parameter, <code>varparam</code>, which usually would be a
				structure grouping some set of values. The body of the procedure
				can then access these values using the pointer given by the TAG
				<code>var_intro</code>, using add_to_ptr with some computed
				offsets to pick out the individual fields.</para>

			<para>This is a slightly different method of giving a variable
				number of parameters to a procedure, rather than simply giving
				more actuals than formals. The principle difference is in the
				alignment of the components of <code>varparam</code>; these will
				be laid out according to the default padding defined by the
				component shapes. In most ABIs, this padding is usually different
				to the way parameters are laid out; for example, character
				parameters are generally padded out to a full word.  Thus a
				sequence of parameters of given shape has a different layout in
				store to the same sequence of shapes in a structure. If one wished
				to pass an arbitrary structure to a procedure, one would use the
				<code>varparam</code> option rather passing the fields
				individually as extra actual parameters.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>make_general_proc and apply_general_proc</title>

		<para>A make_general_proc has signature:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">result_shape: SHAPE
prcprops:     OPTION(PROCPROPS)
caller_intro: LIST(TAGSHACC)
callee_intro: LIST(TAGSHACC)
body:         EXP BOTTOM
              -&gt; EXP PROC</programlisting>
      
		<para>Here the formal parameters are split into two sets,
			<code>caller_intro</code> and <code>callee_intro</code>, each given
			by a list of TAGSHACCs just as in make_proc. The distinction between
			the two sets is that the make_general_proc is responsible for
			de_allocating any space required for the callee parameter set; this
			really only becomes obvious at uses of tail_call within
			<code>body</code>.</para>

		<para>The <code>result_shape</code> and <code>body</code> have the
			same general properties as in make_proc. In addition
			<code>prcprops</code> gives other information both about
			<code>body</code> and the way that that the procedure is called.
			PROCPROPS are a set drawn from check_stack, inline,
			no_long_jump_dest, untidy, var_callees and var_callers. The set is
			composed using add_procprops. The PROCPROPS no_long_jump_dest is a
			property of <code>body</code> only; it indicates that none of the
			labels within <code>body</code> will be the target of a long_jump
			construct. The other properties should also be given consistently at
			all calls of the procedure; theu are discussed in
			<link linkend="procprops">section 5.2.2</link>.</para>

		<para>A procedure, <code>p</code>, constructed by make_general_proc is
			called using apply_general_proc:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">result_shape:  SHAPE
prcprops:      OPTION(PROCPROPS)
p:             EXP PROC
caller_params: LIST(OTAGEXP)
callee_params: CALLEES
postlude:      EXP TOP
               -&gt; EXP result_shape</programlisting>

		<para>The actual caller parameters are given by
			<code>caller_params</code> as a list of OTAGEXPs constructed using
			make_otagexp:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">tgopt: OPTION(TAG x / i>)
e:     EXP x / i>
       -&gt; OTAGEXP</programlisting>
  
		<para>Here, <code>e</code> is the value of the parameter and
			<code>tgopt</code>, if present, is a TAG which will bound to the
			final value of the parameter (after <code>body</code> is evaluated)
			in the <code>postlude</code> expression of the apply_general_proc.
			<footnote>
				<para>If a formal parameter is to be used in this way, it should
					be marked as having out_par ACCESS in its corresponding TAGSHACC
					in <code>callers_intro</code>.</para>
			</footnote>
			Clearly, this allows one to use a caller parameter as an extra
			result of the procedure; for example, as in Ada
			out-parameters.</para>

		<para>The actual <code>callee_params</code> may be constructed in
			three different ways. The usual method is to use make_callee_list,
			giving a list of actual EXP parameters, corresponding to the
			<code>caller_intro</code> list in the obvious way.The constructor,
			same_callees allows one to use the callees of the current procedure
			as the callees of the call; this, of course, assumes that the
			formals of the current procedure are compatible with the formals
			required for the call The final method allows one to construct a
			dynamically sized set of CALLEES; make_dynamic_callees takes a
			pointer and a size (expressed as an OFFSET) to make the CALLEES;
			this will be used in conjunction with a var_callees PROCPROPS (see
			<link linkend="procprops">section 5.2.2</link>).</para>

		<para>Some procedures can be expressed using either make_proc or
			make_general_proc. For example:</para>

		<para>make_proc(S, L, empty, B) = make_general_proc(S, var_callers, L,
			empty, B)</para>

		<section id="tail_call">
			<title>tail_call</title>

			<para>Often the result of a procedure, <function>f</function>, is
				simply given by the call of another (or the same) procedure,
				<function>g</function>. In appropriate circumstances, the same
				stack space can be used for the call of <function>g</function> as
				the call of <function>f</function>. This can be particularly
				important where heavily recursive routines are involved; some
				languages even use tail recursion as the preferred method of
				looping.</para>

			<para>One condition for such a tail call to be applicable is knowing
				that <function>g</function> does not require any pointers to
				locals of <function>f</function>; this is often implicit in the
				language involved.  Equally important is that the action on the
				return from <function>f</function> is indistiguishable from the
				return from <function>g</function>. For example, if it were the
				callers responsibility to pop the the space for the parameters on
				return from a call, then the tail call of <function>g</function>
				would only work if <function>g</function> had the same parameter
				space as <function>f</function>.</para>

			<para>This is the justification for splitting the parameter set of a
				general proc; it is (at least conceptually) the caller's
				responsibility for popping the caller-parameters only - the
				callee-parameters are dealt with by the procedure itself. Hence we
				can define tail_call which uses the same caller-parameters, but a
				different set of callee-parameters:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">prcprops:      OPTION(PROCPROPS)
p:             EXP PROC
callee_params: CALLEES
               -&gt; EXP BOTTOM</programlisting>

			<para>The procedure p will be called with the same caller parameters as
				the current procedure and the new <code>callee_params</code> and
				return to the call site of the current procedure. Semantically, if
				S is the return SHAPE of the current procedure, and L is its
				caller-parameters:</para>

			<para>tail_call(P, p, C) = return(apply_general_proc(S, P, p, L, C,
				make_top()))</para>

			<para>However an implementation is expected to conserve stack by
				using the same space for the call of p as the current
				procedure.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="procprops">
			<title>PROCPROPS</title>

			<para>The presence of var_callees (or var_callers) means that the
				procedure can be called with more actual callee (or caller)
				parameters than are indicated in <code>callee_intro</code> (or
				<code>caller_intro</code>). These extra parameters would be
				accessed within body using offset calculations with respect to the
				named parameters. The offsets should be calculated using
				parameter_alignment to give the packing of the parameter
				packs.</para>

			<para>The presence of untidy means that <code>body</code> may be
				terminated by an untidy_return. This returns the result of the
				procedure as in return, but the lifetime of the local space of the
				procedure is extended (in practice this is performed by not
				returning the stack to its original value at the call). A
				procedure containing an untidy_return is a generalisation of a
				local_alloc(see <link linkend="local_alloc">section 5.3.4</link>).
				For example the procedure could do some complicated local
				allocation (a triangular array, say) and untidily return a pointer
				to it so that the space is still valid in the calling procedure.
				The space will remain valid for the lifetime of the calling
				procedure unless some local_free is called within it, just as if
				the space had been generated by a local_alloc in the calling
				procedure.</para>

			<para>The presence of inline is just a hint to the translator that
				the procedure body is a good candidate for inlining at the
				call.</para>

			<para>The presence of check_stack means that the static stack
				requirements of the procedure will be checked on entry to see that
				they do not exceed the limits imposed by set_stack_limit; if they
				are exceeded a &tdf; exception with ERROR_CODE stack_overflow (see
				<link linkend="exceptional-flow">section 6.3</link>) will be
				raised.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="defining-and-using-locals">
		<title>Defining and using locals</title>

		<section id="identify-variable">
			<title>identify, variable</title>

			<para>Local definitions within the <code>body</code> of a procedure
				are given by two EXP constructors which permit one to give names
				to values over a scope given by the definition. Note that this is
				somewhat different to declarations in standard languages where the
				declaration is usually embedded in a larger construct which
				defines the scope of the name; here the scope is explicit in the
				definition. The reason for this will become more obvious in the
				discussion of &tdf; transformations. The simpler constructor is
				identify:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">opt_access: OPTION(ACCESS)
name_intro: TAG x
definition: EXP x
body:       EXP y
            -&gt; EXP y</programlisting>
            
			<para>The <code>definition</code> is evaluated and its result is
				identified with the TAG given by <code>name_intro</code> within
				its scope <code>body</code>.  Hence the use of any
				obtain_tag(<code>name_intro</code>) within <code>body</code> is
				equivalent to using this result. Anywhere else,
				obtain_tag(<code>name_intro</code>) is meaningless, including in
				other procedures.</para>

			<para>The other kind of local definition is variable:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">opt_access: OPTION(ACCESS)
name_intro: TAG x
init:       EXP x
body:       EXP y
            -&gt; EXP y</programlisting>
            
			<para>Here the <code>init</code> EXP is evaluated and its result serves
				as an initialisation of space of SHAPE <varname>x</varname> local
				to the procedure.  The TAG name_intro is then identified with a
				pointer to that SPACE within body. A use of
				obtain_tag(<code>name_intro</code>) within <code>body</code> is
				equivalent to using this pointer and is meaningless outside
				<code>body</code> or in other procedures. Many variable
				declarations in programs are uninitialised; in this case, the
				<code>init</code> argument could be provided by make_value which
				will produce some value with SHAPE given by its parameter.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="sort-access">
			<title>ACCESS</title>

			<para>The ACCESS SORT given in tag declarations is a way of
				describing a list of properties to be associated with the tag.
				They are basically divided into two classes, one which describes
				global properties of the tag with respect to the model for locals
				and the other which gives "hints" on how the value will be used.
				Any of these can be combined using add_access.</para>

			<section id="locals-model">
				<title>Locals model</title>

				<para>At the moment there are just three possibilities in the
					first class of ACCESS constructors. They are standard_access
					(the default), visible, out_par and long_jump_access.</para>

				<para>The basic model used for the locals and parameters of a
					procedure is a frame within a stack of nested procedure calls.
					One could implement a procedure by allocating space according to
					SHAPEs of all of the parameter and local TAGs so that the
					corresponding values are at fixed offsets either from the start
					of the frame or some pointer within it.</para>

				<para>Indeed, if the ACCESS <code>opt_access</code> parameter in a
					TAG definition is produced by visible, then a translator is
					almost bound to do just that for that TAG. This is because it
					allows for the possibility of the value to be accessed in some
					way other than by using obtain_tag which is the standard way of
					recovering the value bound to the TAG. The principal way that
					this could happen within &tdf; is by the combined use of
					env_offset to give the offset and current_env to give a pointer
					to the current frame (see
					<link linkend="current_env">section 5.3.3</link>).</para>

				<para>The out_par ACCESS is only applicable to caller parameters
					of procedures; it indicates that the value of the TAG concerned
					will accessed by the postlude part of an apply_general_proc.
					Hence, the value of the parameter must be accessible after the
					call; usually this will be on the stack in the callers
					frame.</para>

				<para>The long_jump_access flag is used to indicate that the tag
					must be available after a long_jump. In practice, if either
					visible or long_jump_access is set, most translators would
					allocate the space for the declaration on the main-store stack
					rather than in an available register. If it is not set, then a
					translator is free to use its own criteria for whether space
					which can fit into a register is allocated on the stack or in a
					register, provided there is no observable difference (other than
					time or program size) between the two possibilities.</para>

				<para>Some of these criteria are rather obvious; for example, if a
					pointer to local variable is passed outside the procedure in an
					opaque manner, then it is highly unlikely that one can allocate
					the variable in a register. Some might be less obvious. If the
					only uses of a TAG t was in obtain_tag(t)s which are operands of
					contents or the left-hand operands of assigns, most ABIs would
					allow the tag to be placed in a register. We do not necessarily
					have to generate a pointer value if it can be subsumed by the
					operations available.</para>
			</section>

			<section id="access-hints">
				<title>Access "hints"</title>

				<para>A variable tag with ACCESS constant is a write-once value;
					once it is initialised the variable will always contain the
					initialisation. In other words the tag is a pointer to a
					constant value; translators can use this information to apply
					various optimisations.</para>

				<para>A POINTER tag with ACCESS no_other_read or no_other_write is
					asserting that there are no "aliassed" accesses to the contents
					of the pointer. For example, when applied to a parameter of a
					procedure, it is saying that the original pointer of the tag is
					distinct from any other tags used (reading/writing) in the
					lifetime of the tag. These other tags could either be further
					parameters of the procedure or globals. Clearly, this is useful
					for describing the limitations imposed by Fortran parameters,
					for example.</para>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="current_env">
			<title>current_env, env_offset</title>

			<para>The constructor current_env gives a pointer to the current
				procedure frame of SHAPE POINTER(<code>fa</code>) where
				<code>fa</code> is depends on how the procedure was defined and
				will be some set of the special frame ALIGNMENTs. This set will
				always include locals_alignment - the alignment of any locals
				defined within the procedure. If the procedure has any caller-
				parameters, the set will also include callers_alignment(b) where b
				indicates whether there can be a variable number of them;
				similarly for callee-parameters.</para>

			<para>Offsets from the current_env of a procedure to a tag declared
				in the procedure are constructed by env_offset:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">
fa: ALIGNMENT
y:  ALIGNMENT
t:  TAG x
    -&gt; EXP OFFSET(fa, y)</programlisting>
            
			<para>The frame ALIGNMENT <code>fa</code> will be the appropriate one
				for the TAG <code>t</code>; i.e. if <code>t</code> is a local then
				the <code>fa</code> will be locals_alignment; if <code>t</code> is
				a caller parameter, <code>fa</code> will be callers_alignment(b);
				if <code>t</code> is a callee_parameter, <code>fa</code> will be
				callees_alignment(b). The alignment <code>y</code> will be the
				alignment of the initialisation of <code>t</code>.</para>

			<para>The offset arithmetic operations allow one to access the
				values of tags non-locally using values derived from current_env
				and env_offset. They are effectively defined by the following
				identities:</para>

		<!-- TODO this is not one <programlisting language="tdf"> -->
          <programlisting language="tdf">If TAG t is derived from a variable definition
            add_to_ptr(current_env(), env_offset(locals_alignment, A, t)) = obtain_tag(t)
    if TAG t is derived from an identify definition:
            contents(S, add_to_ptr(current_env(), env_offset(locals_alignment, A, t))) = obtain_tag(t)
    if TAG t is derived from a caller parameter:
            add_to_ptr(current_env(), env_offset(callers_alignment(b), A, t)) = obtain_tag(t)
    if TAG t is derived from a callee parameter:
            add_to_ptr(current_env(), env_offset(callees_alignment(b), A, t)) = obtain_tag(t)</programlisting>
            
			<para>These identities are valid throughout the extent of t, including
				in inner procedure calls. In other words, one can dynamically
				create a pointer to the value by composing current_env and
				env_offset.</para>

			<para>The importance of this is that env_offset(t) is a constant
				OFFSET and can be used anywhere within the enclosing UNIT, in
				other procedures or as part of constant TAGDEF; remember that the
				TDFINT underlying t is unique within the UNIT. The result of a
				current_env could be passed to another procedure (as a parameter,
				say) and this new procedure could then access a local of the
				original by using its env_offset. This would be the method one
				would use to access non-local, non-global identifiers in a
				language which allowed one to define procedures within procedures
				such as Pascal or Algol. Of course, given the stack-based model,
				the value given by current_env becomes meaningless once the
				procedure in which it is invoked is exited.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="local_alloc">
			<title>local_alloc, local_free_all, last_local</title>

			<para>The size of stack frame produced by variable and identify
				definitions is a translate-time constant since the frame is
				composed of values whose SHAPEs are known. &tdf; also allows one to
				produce dynamically sized local objects which are conceptually
				part of the frame. These are produced by local_alloc:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">arg1: EXP OFFSET(x, y)
      -&gt; EXP POINTER(alloca_alignment)</programlisting>

			<para>The operand <code>arg1</code> gives the size of the new object
				required and the result is a pointer to the space for this object
				"on top of the stack" as part of the frame. The quotation marks
				indicate that a translator writer might prefer to maintain a
				dynamic stack as well as static one. There are some disadvantages
				in putting everything into one stack which may well out-weigh the
				trouble of maintaining another stack which is relatively
				infrequently used. If a frame has a known size, then all
				addressing of locals can be done using a stack-front register; if
				it is dynamically sized, then another frame-pointer register must
				be used - some ABIs make this easy but not all. The majority of
				procedures contain no local_allocs, so their addressing of locals
				can always be done relative to a stack-front; only the others have
				to use another register for a frame pointer.</para>

			<para>The alignment of pointer result is alloca_alignment which must
				include all SHAPE alignments.</para>

			<para>There are two constructors for releasing space generated by
				local_alloc. To release all such space generated in the current
				procedure one does local_free_all(); this reduces the size of the
				current frame to its static size.</para>

			<para>The other constructor is local_free whch is effectively a
				"pop" to local_alloc's "push":</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">a: EXP OFFSET(x, y)
p: EXP POINTER(alloca_alignment)
   -&gt; EXP TOP</programlisting>

			<para>Here <code>p</code> must evaluate to a pointer generated either by
				local_alloc or last_local . The effect is to free all of the space
				locally allocated after p. The usual implementation (with a
				downward growing stack) of this is that p becomes the "top of
				stack" pointer.</para>

			<para>The use of a procedure with an untidy_return is just a
				generalisation of the idea of local_alloc and the space made
				available by its use can be freed in the same way as normal local
				allocations. Of course, given that it could be the result of the
				procedure it can be structured in an arbitrarily complicated
				way.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="heap-storage">
		<title>Heap storage</title>

		<para>At the moment, there are no explicit constructors of creating
			dynamic off-stack storage in &tdf;. Any off-stack storage requirements
			must be met by the &api; in which the system is embedded, using the
			standard procedural interface.  For example, the ANSI C &api; allows
			the creation of heap space using standard library procedures like
			malloc.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

