<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
  $Id$
-->

<chapter>
	<title>SHAPEs, ALIGNMENTs and OFFSETs.</title>

	<para>In most languages there is some notion of the type of a value.
		This is often an uncomfortable mix of a definition of a representation
		for the value and a means of choosing which operators are applicable
		to the value. The &tdf; analogue of the type of value is its SHAPE
		(S3.20). A SHAPE is only concerned with the representation of a value,
		being an abstraction of its size and alignment properties.  Clearly an
		architecture-independent representation of a program cannot say, for
		example, that a pointer is 32 bits long; the size of pointers has to
		be abstracted so that translations to particular architectures can
		choose the size that is apposite for the platform.</para>

	<section>
		<title>Shapes</title>

		<para>There are ten different basic constructors for the SORT SHAPE
			from bitfield to top as shown in table 3.	<!-- TODO: link -->
			SHAPEs arising from those
			constructors are used as qualifiers (just using an upper case
			version of the constructor name) to various SORTs in the definition;
			for example, EXP TOP is an expression with top SHAPE. This is just
			used for definitional purposes only; there is no SORT SHAPENAME as
			one has SORTNAME.</para>

		<!--
			I am not sure that this is the right place for this table;
			a reference to the original table (which was a .gif file)
			was missing from the 4.1.2 HTML documents.
		-->
		<table>
			<col align="left"/>
			<col align="left"/>
			<col align="left"/>
			<col align="left"/>

			<thead>
				<tr>
					<th><code>SHAPE</code></th>
					<th>Qualifier <code>SORT</code></th>
					<th>Usage</th>
					<th><code>ALIGNMENT</code></th>
				</tr>
			</thead>

			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td><code>BITFIELD(<replaceable>v</replaceable>)</code></td>
					<td><code>BITFIELD_VARIETY</code></td>
					<td>As in C bitfields, e.g. <code>int x:5</code></td>
					<td><code>{<replaceable>v</replaceable>}</code></td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>BOTTOM</code></td>
					<td role="na" align="center">&ndash;</td>
					<td>It never gets here, e.g. <code>goto</code></td>
					<td role="na">(none)</td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>COMPOUND(<replaceable>sz</replaceable>)</code></td>
					<td><code>OFFSET(<replaceable>x</replaceable>,&nbsp;<replaceable>y</replaceable>)</code></td>
					<td>Structs or unions; <code>OFFSET</code> <replaceable>sz</replaceable> is size</td>
					<td><replaceable>x</replaceable> &#8839; set-union of field alignments</td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>FLOATING(<replaceable>fv</replaceable>)</code></td>
					<td><code>FLOATING_VARIETY</code></td>
					<td>Floating point numbers</td>
					<td><code>{<replaceable>fv</replaceable>}</code></td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>INTEGER(<replaceable>v</replaceable>)</code></td>
					<td><code>VARIETY</code></td>
					<td>Integers, including chars</td>
					<td><code>{<replaceable>v</replaceable>}</code></td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>NOF(<replaceable>n</replaceable>,&nbsp;<replaceable>s</replaceable>)</code></td>
					<td><code>(NAT,&nbsp;SHAPE)</code></td>
					<td>Tuple of <replaceable>n</replaceable> values of <code>SHAPE</code> <replaceable>s</replaceable></td>
					<td><code>{alignment(<replaceable>s</replaceable>)}</code></td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>OFFSET(<replaceable>a1</replaceable>,&nbsp;<replaceable>a2</replaceable>)</code></td>
					<td><code>(ALIGNMENT,&nbsp;ALIGNMENT)</code></td>
					<td>Offsets in memory; <replaceable>a1</replaceable> &#8839; <replaceable>a2</replaceable></td>
					<td><code>{offset}</code></td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>POINTER(<replaceable>a</replaceable>)</code></td>
					<td><code>ALIGNMENT</code></td>
					<td>Pointers in memory</td>
					<td><code>{pointer}</code></td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>PROC</code></td>
					<td role="na" align="center">&ndash;</td>
					<td>Procedure values</td>
					<td><code>{proc}</code></td>
				</tr>

				<tr>
					<td><code>TOP</code></td>
					<td role="na" align="center">&ndash;</td>
					<td>No value; e.g. the result of assign</td>
					<td><code>{ }</code></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>

		<para>In the &tdf; specification of EXPs, you will observe that all EXPs
			in constructor signatures are all qualified by the SHAPE name; for
			example, a parameter might be EXP INTEGER(v). This merely means that
			for the construct to be meaningful the parameter must be derived
			from a constructor defined to be an EXP INTEGER(v). You might be
			forgiven for assuming that &tdf; is hence strongly-typed by its
			SHAPEs. This is not true; the producer must get it right. There are
			some checks in translators, but these are not exhaustive and are
			more for the benefit of translator writers than for the user. A tool
			for testing the SHAPE correctness of a &tdf; program would be useful
			but has yet to be written.</para>

		<section>
			<title>TOP, BOTTOM, LUB</title>

			<para>Two of the SHAPE constructions are rather specialised; these
				are TOP and BOTTOM. The result of any expression with a TOP shape
				will always be discarded; examples are those produced by assign
				and integer_test . A BOTTOM SHAPE is produced by an expression
				which will leave the current flow of control e.g. goto . The
				significance of these SHAPEs only really impinges on the
				computation of the shapes of constructs which have alternative
				expressions as results. For example, the result of conditional is
				the result of one of its component expressions. In this case, the
				SHAPE of the result is described as the LUB of the SHAPEs of the
				components. This simply means that if one of the component SHAPEs
				is TOP then the resulting SHAPE is TOP; if one is BOTTOM then the
				resulting SHAPE is the SHAPE of the other; otherwise both
				component SHAPEs must be equal and is the resulting SHAPE. Since
				this operation is associative, commutative and idempotent, we can
				speak quite unambiguously of the LUB of several SHAPEs.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>INTEGER</title>

			<para>Integer values in &tdf; have shape INTEGER(v) where v is of SORT
				VARIETY. The constructor for this SHAPE is integer with a VARIETY
				parameter.  The basic constructor for VARIETY is var_limits which
				has a pair of signed natural numbers as parameters giving the
				limits of possible values that the integer can attain. The SHAPE
				required for a 32 bit signed integer would be:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">integer(var_limits(-2<superscript>31</superscript>, 2<superscript>31</superscript> - 1))</programlisting>

			<para>while an unsigned char is:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">integer(var_limits(0, 255))</programlisting>

			<para>A translator should represent each integer variety by an object
				big enough (or bigger) to contain all the possible values with
				limits of the VARIETY. That being said, I must confess that most
				current translators do not handle integers of more than the
				maximum given naturally by the target architecture, but this will
				be rectified in due course.</para>

			<para>The other way of constructing a VARIETY is to specify the
				number of bits required for its 2s-complemennt representation
				using var_width:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">signed_width: BOOL
width:        NAT
-&gt; VARIETY</programlisting>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>FLOATING and complex</title>

			<para>Similarly, floating point and complex numbers have shape
				FLOATING qualified by a FLOATING_VARIETY.</para>

			<para>A FLOATING_VARIETY for a real number is constructed using
				fvar_parms:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">
base:              NAT
mantissa_digits:   NAT
minimum_exponent:  NAT
maximum_exponent:: NAT
   -&gt; FLOATING_VARIETY</programlisting>

			<para>A FLOATING_VARIETY specifies the base, number of mantissa
				digits, and maximum and minimum exponent. Once again, it is
				intended that the translator will choose a representation which
				will contain all possible values, but in practice only those which
				are included in IEEE float, double and extended are actually
				implemented.</para>

			<para>Complex numbers have a floating variety constructed by
				complex_parms which has the the same signature as fvar_parms. The
				representation of these numbers is likely to be a pair of real
				numbers each defined as if by fvar_parms with the same arguments.
				The real and imaginary parts of of a complex number can be
				extracted using real_part and imaginary_part; these could have
				been injected ito the complex number using make_complex or any of
				the complex operations. Many translators will simply transform
				complex numbers into COMPOUNDs consisting of two floating point
				numbers, transforming the complex operations into floating point
				operations on the fields.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>BITFIELD</title>

			<para>A number of contiguous bits have shape BITFIELD, qualified by
				a BITFIELD_VARIETY (S3.4) which gives the number of bits involved
				and whether these bits are to be treated as signed or unsigned
				integers. Current translators put a maximum of 32 or 64 on the
				number of bits.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>PROC</title>

			<para>The representational SHAPEs of procedure values is given by
				PROC with constructor proc . I shall return to this in the
				description of the operations which use it.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Non-primitive SHAPEs</title>

			<para>The construction of the other four SHAPEs involves either
				existing SHAPEs or the alignments of existing SHAPEs.  These are
				constructed by compound, nof, offset and pointer.  Before
				describing these, we require a digression into what is meant by
				alignments and offsets.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Alignments</title>

		<para>In most processor architectures there are limitations on how one
			can address particular kinds of objects in convenient ways. These
			limitations are usually defined as part of the ABI for the
			processor. For example, in the MIPs processor the fastest way to
			access a 32-bit integer is to ensure that the address of the integer
			is aligned on a 4-byte boundary in the address space; obviously one
			can extract a mis-aligned integer but not in one machine
			instruction. Similarly, 16-bit integers should be aligned on a
			2-byte boundary. In principle, each primitive object could have
			similar restrictions for efficient access and these restrictions
			could vary from platform to platform. Hence, the notion of alignment
			has to be abstracted to form part of the architecture independent
			&tdf; - we cannot assume that any particular alignment regime will
			hold universally.</para>

		<para>The abstraction of alignments clearly has to cover compound
			objects as well as primitive ones like integers. For example, if a
			field of structure in C is to be accessed efficiently, then the
			alignment of the field will influence the alignment of the structure
			as whole; the structure itself could be a component of a larger
			object whose alignment must then depend on the alignment of the
			structure and so on. In general, we find that a compound alignment
			is given by the maximum alignment of its components, regardless of
			the form of the compound object e.g. whether it is a structure,
			union, array or whatever.</para>

		<para>This gives an immediate handle on the abstraction of the
			alignment of a compound object - it is just the set of abstractions
			of the alignments of its components. Since "maximum" is associative,
			commutative and idempotent, the component sets can be combined using
			normal set-union rules. In other words, a compound alignment is
			abstracted as the set of alignments of the primitive objects which
			make up the compound object. Thus the alignment abstraction of a C
			structure with only float fields is the singleton set containing the
			alignment of a float while that of a C union of an int and this
			structure is a pair of the alignments of an int and a float.</para>

		<section id="alignement-constructors">
			<title>ALIGNMENT constructors</title>

			<para>The &tdf; abstraction of an alignment has SORT ALIGNMENT. The
				constructor, unite_alignments, gives the set-union of its
				ALIGNMENT parameters; this would correspond to taking a maximum of
				two real alignments in the translator.</para>

			<para>The constructor, alignment, gives the ALIGNMENT of a given
				SHAPE according to the rules given in the definition. These rules
				effectively <code>define</code> the primitive ALIGNMENTs as in the
				ALIGNMENT column of table 3. Those for PROC, all OFFSETs and all
				POINTERs are constants regardless of any SHAPE qualifiers. Each of
				the INTERGER VARIETYs, each of the FLOATING VARIETYs and each of
				the BITFIELD VARIETYs have their own ALIGNMENTs. These ALIGNMENTs
				will be bound to values apposite to the particular platform at
				translate-time. The ALIGNMENT of TOP is conventionally taken to be
				the empty set of ALIGNMENTs (corresponding to the minimum
				alignment on the platform).</para>

			<para>The alignment of a procedure parameter clearly has to include
				the alignment of its SHAPE; however, most ABIs will mandate a
				greater alignment for some SHAPEs e.g. the alignment of a byte
				parameter is usually defined to be on a 32-bit rather than an
				8-bit boundary. The constructor, parameter_alignment, gives the
				ALIGNMENT of a parameter of given SHAPE.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Special alignments</title>

			<para>There are several other special ALIGNMENTs.</para>

			<para>The alignment of a code address is {<code>code</code>} given
				by code_alignment; this will be the alignment of a pointer given
				by make_local_lv giving the value of a label.</para>

			<para>The other special ALIGNMENTs are considered to include all of
				the others, but remain distinct. They are all concerned with
				offsets and pointers relevant to procedure frames, procedure
				parameters and local allocations and are collectively known as
				frame alignments. These frame alignments differ from the normal
				alignments in that their mapping to a given architecture is rather
				more than just saying that it describes some n-bit boundary. For
				example, alloca_alignment describes the alignment of dynamic space
				produced by local_alloc (roughly the C alloca).  Now, an ABI could
				specify that the alloca space is a stack disjoint from the normal
				procedure stack; thus manipulations of space at alloca_alignment
				may involve different code to space generated in other
				ways.</para>

			<para>Similar considerations apply to the other special alignments,
				callees_alignment(b), callers_alignment(b) and locals_alignment.
				The first two give the alignments of the bases of the two
				different parameter spaces in procedures (q.v.) and
				locals_alignment gives the alignment of the base of locally
				declared tags within a procedure. The exact interpretation of
				these depends on how the frame stack is defined in the target ABI,
				e.g. does the stack grow downwards or upwards?</para>

			<para>The final special alignment is var_param_alignment. This
				describes the alignment of a special kind of parameter to a
				procedure which can be of arbitrary length (see
				<link linkend="vartag-varparam">section 5.1.1</link>).</para>
		</section>

		<section id="al_tag-make_al_tagdef">
			<title>AL_TAG, make_al_tagdef</title>

			<para>Alignments can also be named as AL_TAGs using make_al_tagdef.
				There is no corresponding make_al_tagdec since AL_TAGs are
				implicitly declared by their constructor, make_al_tag. The main
				reason for having names for alignments is to allow one to resolve
				the ALIGNMENTs of recursive data structures. If, for example, we
				have mutually recursive structures, their ALIGNMENTs are best
				named and given as a set of equations formed by AL_TAGDEFs. A
				translator can then solve these equations trivially by
				substitution; this is easy because the only significant operation
				is set-union.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="pointer-and-offset-shapes">
		<title>Pointer and offset SHAPEs</title>

		<para>A pointer value must have a form which reflects the alignment of
			the object that it points to; for example, in the MIPs processor,
			the bottom two bits of a pointer to an integer must be zero. The &tdf;
			SHAPE for a pointer is POINTER qualified by the ALIGNMENT of the
			object pointed to.  The constructor pointer uses this alignment to
			make a POINTER SHAPE.</para>

		<section id="offset">
			<title>OFFSET</title>

			<para>Expressions which give sizes or offsets in &tdf; have an OFFSET
				SHAPE. These are always described as the difference between two
				pointers.  Since the alignments of the objects pointed to could be
				different, an OFFSET is qualified by these two ALIGNMENTs. Thus an
				EXP OFFSET(X,Y) is the difference between an EXP POINTER(X) and an
				EXP POINTER(Y). In order for the alignment rules to apply, the set
				X of alignments must include Y. The constructor offset uses two
				such alignments to make an OFFSET SHAPE. However, many instances
				of offsets will be produced implicitly by the offset arithmetic,
				e.g., offset_pad:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">a:    ALIGNMENT
arg1: EXP OFFSET(z, t)
-&gt; EXP OFFSET(z xc8 a, a)</programlisting>

			<para>This gives the next OFFSET greater or equal to <code>arg1</code>
				at which an object of ALIGNMENT <code>a</code> can be
				placed. It should be noted that the calculation of shapes and
				alignments are all translate-time activities; only EXPs should
				produce runnable code.  This code, of course, may depend on the
				shapes and alignments involved; for example, offset_pad might
				round up <code>arg1</code> to be a multiple of four bytes if
				<code>a</code> was an integer ALIGNMENT and
				<code>z</code> was a character ALIGNMENT. Translators
				also do extensive constant analysis, so if <code>arg1</code> was a
				constant offset, then the round-off would be done at
				translate-time to produce another constant.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Compound SHAPEs</title>

		<para>The alignments of compound SHAPEs (i.e. those arising from the
			constructors compound and nof) are derived from the constructions
			which produced the SHAPE. To take the easy one first, the
			constructor nof has signature:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">n: NAT
s: SHAPE
-&gt; SHAPE</programlisting>

		<para>This SHAPE describes an array of <code>n</code> values all of SHAPE
			<code>s</code>; note that <code>n</code> is a natural number and
			hence is a constant known to the producer. Throughout the definition
			this is referred to as the SHAPE NOF(n, s). The ALIGNMENT of such a
			value is alignment(s); i.e. the alignment of an array is just the
			alignment of its elements.</para>

		<para>The other compound SHAPEs are produced using compound:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">sz: EXP OFFSET(x, y)
-&gt; SHAPE</programlisting>

		<para>The <code>sz</code> parameter gives the minimum size which can
			accommodate the SHAPE.</para>

		<section id="offset-arithmetic">
			<title>Offset arithmetic with compound shapes</title>

			<para>The constructors offset_add, offset_zero and shape_offset are
				used together with offset_pad to implement (<emphasis>inter
				alia</emphasis>) selection from structures represented by
				COMPOUND SHAPEs. Starting from the zero OFFSET given by
				offset_zero, one can construct an EXP which is the offset of a
				field by padding and adding offsets until the required field is
				reached. The value of the field required could then be extracted
				using component or add_to_ptr. Most producers would define a TOKEN
				for the EXP OFFSET of each field of a structure or union used in
				the program simply to reduce the size of the &tdf;.</para>

			<para>The SHAPE of a C structure consisting of an char followed by
				an int would require <varname>x</varname> to be the set consisting
				of two INTEGER VARIETYs, one for int and one for char, and
				<code>sz</code> would probably have been constructed like:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">sz = offset_add(offset_pad(int_al, shape_offset(char)), shape_offset(int))</programlisting>

			<para>The various rules for the ALIGNMENT qualifiers of the OFFSETs
				give the required SHAPE; these rules also ensure that offset
				arithmetic can be implemented simply using integer arithmetic for
				standard architectures (see
				<link linkend="model-for-32bit-architecture">section 13.1</link>).
				Note that the OFFSET computed here is the minimum size for the
				SHAPE. This would not in general be the same as the difference
				between successive elements of an array of these structures which
				would have SHAPE OFFSET(<code>x</code>,
				<code>x</code>) as produced by
				offset_pad(<code>x</code>, <code>sz</code>).
				For examples of the use of OFFSETs to access and create
				structures, see
				<link linkend="tdf-expansions-of-offsets">section 12</link>.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>offset_mult</title>

			<para>In C, all structures have size known at translate-time. This
				means that OFFSETs for all field selections of structures and
				unions are translate-time constants; there is never any need to
				produce code to compute these sizes and offsets. Other languages
				(notably Ada) do have variable size structures and so sizes and
				offsets within these structures may have to be computed
				dynamically. Indexing in C will require the computation of dynamic
				OFFSETs; this would usually be done by using offset_mult to
				multiply an offset expression representing the stride by an
				integer expression giving the index:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">arg1: EXP OFFSET(x, x)
arg2: EXP INTEGER(v)
-&gt; EXP OFFSET(x, x)</programlisting>

			<para>and using add_to_ptr with a pointer expression giving the base of
				the array with the resulting OFFSET.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>OFFSET ordering and representation</title>

			<para>There is an ordering defined on OFFSETs with the same
				alignment qualifiers, as given by offset_test and offset_max
				having properties like:</para>

			<programlisting language="tdf">shape_offset(S) xb3  offset_zero(alignment(S))
A xb3  B        iff offset_max(A,B) = A
offset_add(A, B) xb3  A         where B xb3  offset_zero(some compatible alignment)</programlisting>

			<para>In most machines, OFFSETs would be represented as single integer
				values with the OFFSET ordering corresponding to simple integer
				ordering. The offset_add constructor just translates to simple
				addition with offset_zero as 0 with similar correspondences for
				the other offset constructors. You might well ask why &tdf; does not
				simply use integers for offsets, instead of introducing the rather
				complex OFFSET SHAPE. The reasons are two-fold. First, following
				the OFFSET arithmetic rules concerned with the ALIGNMENT
				qualifiers will ensure that one never extracts a value from a
				pointer with the wrong alignment by, for example, applying
				contents to an add_to_pointer. This frees &tdf; from having to
				define the effect of strange operations like forming a float by
				taking the contents of a pointer to a character which may be
				mis-aligned with respect to floats - a heavy operation on most
				processors. The second reason is quite simple; there are machines
				which cannot represent OFFSETs by a single integer value.</para>

			<para>The iAPX-432 is a fairly extreme example of such a machine; it
				is a "capability" machine which must segregate pointer values and
				non-pointer values into different spaces. On this machine a value
				of SHAPE POINTER({<code>pointer</code>, int}) (e.g. a pointer to a
				structure containing both integers and pointers) could have two
				components; one referring to the pointers and another to the
				integers. In general, offsets from this pointer would also have
				two components, one to pick out any pointer values and the other
				the integer values. This would obviously be the case if the
				original POINTER referred to an array of structures containing
				both pointers and integers; an offset to an element of the array
				would have SHAPE OFFSET({<code>pointer</code>, int},
				{<code>pointer</code>, int}); both elements of the offset would
				have to be used as displacements to the corresponding elements of
				the pointer to extract the structure element. The OFFSET ordering
				is now given by the comparison of both displacements. Using this
				method, one finds that pointers in store to non-pointer alignments
				are two words in different blocks and pointers to
				pointer-alignments are four words, two in one block and two in
				another. This sounds a very unwieldy machine compared to normal
				machines with linear addressing. However, who knows what similar
				strange machines will appear in future; the basic conflicts
				between security, integrity and flexibility that the iAPX-432
				sought to resolve are still with us. For more on the modelling of
				pointers and offsets see
				<link linkend="models-of-the-tdf-algebra">section 13</link>.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="bitfield-alignments">
		<title>BITFIELD alignments</title>

		<para>Even in standard machines, one finds that the size of a pointer
			may depend on the alignment of the data pointed at. Most machines do
			not allow one to construct pointers to bits with the same facility
			as other alignments. This usually means that pointers in memory to
			BITFIELD VARIETYs must be implemented as two words with an address
			and bit displacement.  One might imagine that a translator could
			implement BITFIELD alignments so that they are the same as the
			smallest natural alignment of the machine and avoid the bit
			displacement, but this is not the intention of the definition. On
			any machine for which it is meaningful, the alignment of a BITFIELD
			must be one bit; in other words successive BITFIELDs are butted
			together with no padding bits. <footnote>
				<para>Note that is not generally true for C bitfields; most C ABIs
					have (different) rules for putting in padding bits depending on
					the size of the bitfield and its relation with the natural
					alignments. This is a fruitful source of errors in data exchange
					between different C ABIs For more on similar limitations of
					bitfields in &tdf; (see
					<link linkend="assigning-and-extracting-bitfields">Assigning and
					extracting bitfields</link>).</para>
			</footnote>
			Within the limits of what one can extract from BITFIELDs, namely
			INTEGER VARIETYs, this is how one should implement non-standard
			alignments, perhaps in constructing data, such as protocols, for
			exchange between machines. One could implement some Ada
			representational statements in this way; certainly the most commonly
			used ones.</para>

		<para>&tdf; Version 3.0 does not allow one to construct a pointer of
			SHAPE POINTER(b) where b consists entirely of bitfield alignments;
			this relieves the translators of the burden of doing general
			bit-addressing. Of course, this simply shifts the burden to the
			producer. If the high level language requires to construct a pointer
			to an arbitrary bit position, then the producer is required to
			represent such a pointer as a pair consisting of pointer to some
			alignment including the required bitfield and an offset from this
			alignment to the bitfield. For example, Ada may require the
			construction of a pointer to a boolean for use as the parameter to a
			procedure; the SHAPE of the rep resentation of this Ada pointer
			could be a COMPOUND formed from a POINTER({x,b}) and an OFFSET({x,
			b}, b) where b is the alignment given by a 1 bit alignment. To
			access the boolean, the producer would use the elements of this pair
			as arguements to bitfield_assign and bitfield_contents
			(<link linkend="assigning-and-extracting-bitfields">Assigning and
			extracting bitfields</link>.).</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

