<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!--
  $Id$
-->

<chapter id="tokens-and-apis">
	<title>Tokens and APIs</title>

	<para>All of the examples of the use of TOKENs so far given have really
		been as abbreviations for commonly used constructs, e.g. the EXP
		OFFSETS for fields of structures. However, the real justification for
		TOKENs are their use as abstractions for things defined in libraries
		or application program interfaces (APIs).</para>

	<section id="S79">
		<title>Application programming interfaces</title>

		<para>APIs usually do not give complete language definitions of the
			operations and values that they contain; generally, they are defined
			informally in English giving relationships between the entities
			within them.  An API designer should allow implementors the
			opportunity of choosing actual definitions which fit their hardware
			and the possibility of changing them as better algorithms or
			representations become available.</para>

		<para>The most commonly quoted example is the representation of the
			type FILE and its related operations in C. The ANSI C definition
			gives no common representation for FILE; its implementation is
			defined to be platform-dependent. A TDF producer can assume nothing
			about FILE; not even that it is a structure. The only things that
			can alter or create FILEs are also entities in the Ansi-C API and
			they will always refer to FILEs via a C pointer.  Thus TDF abstracts
			FILE as a SHAPE TOKEN with no parameters, make_tok(T_FILE) say. Any
			program that uses FILE would have to include a TOKDEC introducing
			T_FILE:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">make_tokdec(T_FILE, empty, shape())</programlisting>

		<para>and anywhere that it wished to refer to the SHAPE of FILE it would
			do:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">shape_apply_token(make_tok(T_FILE), ())</programlisting>

		<para>Before this program is translated on a given platform, the actual
			SHAPE of FILE must be supplied. This would be done by linking a TDF
			CAPSULE which supplies the TOKDEF for the SHAPE of FILE which is
			particular to the target platform.</para>

		<para>Many of the C operations which use FILEs are explicitly allowed
			to be expanded as either procedure calls or as macros.  For example,
			putc(c,f) may be implemented either as a procedure call or as the
			expansion of macro which uses the fields of f directly. Thus, it is
			quite natural for putc(c, f) to be represented in TDF as an EXP
			TOKEN with two EXP parameters which allows it to be expanded in
			either way. Of course, this would be quite distinct from the use of
			putc as a value (as a proc parameter of a procedure for example)
			which would require some other representation. One such
			representation that comes to mind might be to simply to make a
			TAGDEC for the putc value, supplying its TAGDEF in the Ansi API
			CAPSULE for the platform. This might prove to be rather
			short-sighted, since it denies us the possibility that the putc
			value itself might be expanded from other values and hence it would
			be better as another parameterless TOKEN. I have not come across an
			actual API expansion for the putc value as other than a simple TAG;
			however the FILE* value stdin is sometimes expressed as:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#define stdin &amp;_iob[0]</programlisting>

		<para>which illustrates the point. It is better to have all of the
			interface of an API expressed as TOKENs to give both generality and
			flexibility across different platforms.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S80">
		<title>Linking to APIs</title>

		<para>In general, each API requires platform-dependent definitions to
			be supplied by a combination of TDF linking and system linking for
			that platform. This is illustrated in the following diagram giving
			the various phases involved in producing a runnable program.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>TDF Production, Linking and Translating</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/guide3.svg"/>
		</figure>

		<para>There will be CAPSULEs for each API on each platform giving the
			expansions for the TOKENs involved, usually as uses of identifiers
			which will be supplied by system linking from some libraries. These
			CAPSULEs would be derived from the header files on the platform for
			the API in question, usually using some automatic tools. For
			example, there will be a TDF CAPSULE (derived from &lt;stdio.h&gt;)
			which defines the TOKEN T_FILE as the SHAPE for FILE, together with
			definitions for the TOKENs for putc, stdin, etc., in terms of
			identifiers which will be found in the library libc.a.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S81">
		<title>Target independent headers, unique_extern</title>

		<para>Any producer which uses an API will use system independent
			information to give the common interface TOKENs for this API. In
			the C producer, this is provided by header files using pragmas,
			which tell the producer which TOKENs to use for the particular
			constructs of the API . In any target-independent CAPSULE which
			uses the API, these TOKENs would be introduced as TOKDECs and made
			globally accessible by using make_linkextern. For a world-wide
			standard API, the EXTERNAL "name" for a TOKEN used by
			make_linkextern should be provided by an application of
			unique_extern on a UNIQUE drawn from a central repository of names
			for entities in standard APIs; this repository would form a kind
			of super-standard for naming conventions in all possible APIs. The
			mechanism for controlling this super-standard has yet to be set
			up, so at the moment all EXTERN names are created by
			string_extern.</para>

		<para>An interesting example in the use of TOKENs comes in
			abstracting field names. Often, an API will say something like
			"the type Widget is a structure with fields alpha, beta ..."
			without specifying the order of the fields or whether the list of
			fields is complete. The field selection operations for Widget
			should then be expressed using EXP OFFSET TOKENs; each field would
			have its own TOKEN giving its offset which will be filled in when
			the target is known. This gives implementors on a particular
			platform the opportunity to reorder fields or add to them as they
			like; it also allows for extension of the standard in the same
			way.</para>

		<para>The most common SORTs of TOKENs used for APIs are SHAPEs to
			represent types, and EXPs to represent values, including
			procedures and constants. NATs and VARIETYs are also sometimes
			used where the API does not specify the types of integers
			involved. The other SORTs are rarely used in APIs; indeed it is
			difficult to imagine <emphasis>any</emphasis> realistic use of
			TOKENs of SORT BOOL. However, the criterion for choosing which
			SORTs are available for TOKENisation is not their immediate
			utility, but that the structural integrity and simplicity of TDF
			is maintained. It is fairly obvious that having BOOL TOKENs will
			cause no problems, so we may as well allow them.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S82">
		<title>Language programming interfaces</title>

		<para>So far, I have been speaking as though a TOKENised API could
			only be some library interface, built on top of some language,
			like xpg3, posix, X etc. on top of C. However, it is possible to
			consider the constructions of the language itself as ideal
			candidates for TOKENisation. For example, the C for-statement
			could be expressed as TOKEN with four parameters. This TOKEN could
			be expanded in TDF in several different ways, all giving the
			correct semantics of a for-statement. A translator (or other
			tools) could choose the expansion it wants depending on context
			and the properties of the parameters. The C producer could give a
			default expansion which a lazy translator writer could use, but
			others might use expansions which might be more advantageous. This
			idea could be extended to virtually all the constructions of the
			language, giving what is in effect a C-language API; perhaps this
			might be called more properly a language programming interface
			(LPI). Thus, we would have TOKENs for C for-statements, C
			conditionals, C procedure calls, C procedure definitions etc.
			<footnote>
				<para>Exercise for the reader: what are the SORTs of these
					parameters?</para>
	
				<para>The current C producer does this for some of the
					constructs, but not in any systematic manner; perhaps it will
					change.</para>
			</footnote></para>

		<para>The notion of a producer for any language working to an LPI
			specific to the constructs of the language is very attractive. It
			could use different TOKENs to reflect the subtle differences
			between uses of similar constructs in different languages which
			might be difficult or impossible to detect from their expansions,
			but which could allow better optimisations in the object code.
			For example, Fortran procedures are slightly different from C
			procedures in that they do not allow aliasing between parameters
			and globals. While application of the standard TDF procedure calls
			would be semantically correct, knowledge of that the non-aliasing
			rule applies would allow some procedures to be translated to more
			efficient code. A translator without knowledge of the semantics
			implicit in the TOKENs involved would still produce correct code,
			but one which knew about them could take advantage of that
			knowledge.</para>

		<para>I also think that LPIs would be a very useful tool for
			crystalising ideas on how languages should be translated, allowing
			one to experiment with expansions not thought of by the producer
			writer. This decoupling is also an escape clause allowing the
			producer writer to defer the implementation of a construct
			completely to translate-time or link-time, as is done at the
			moment in C for off-stack allocation. As such it also serves as a
			useful test-bed for TOKEN constructions which may in future become
			new constructors of core TDF.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="namespaces-and-apis">
		<title>Namespaces and &api;s</title>

		<para>Namespace problems are
			amongst the most difficult faced by standard defining bodies (for
			example, the &ansi; and &posix; committees) and they often go to
			great lengths to specify which names should, and should not,
			appear when certain headers are included. (The position is set
			out in D. F. Prosser, <citetitle>Header and name space rules for
			&unix; systems</citetitle> (private communication),
			USL, 1993.)</para>

		<para>For example, the intention, certainly in &ansi;, is that each
			header should operate as an independent sub-&api;. Thus
			<code>va_list</code> is prohibited from appearing in the
			namespace when <code>stdio.h</code> is included (it is defined
			only in <code>stdarg.h</code>) despite the fact that it appears
			in the prototype:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">int vprintf ( char *, va_list ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>This seeming contradiction is worked round on most
			implementations by defining a type <code>__va_list</code> in <code>
			stdio.h</code> which has exactly the same definition as
			<code>va_list</code>, and declaring <code>vprintf</code> as:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">int vprintf ( char *, __va_list ) ;</programlisting>

		<para>This is only legal because <code>__va_list</code> is deemed
			not to corrupt the namespace because of the convention that names
			beginning with <code>__</code> are reserved for implementation use.</para>

		<para>This particular namespace convention is well-known, but there
			are others defined in these standards which are not generally
			known (and since no compiler I know tests them, not widely
			adhered to). For example, the &ansi; header <code>errno.h</code>
			reserves all names given by the regular expression:</para>

		<literallayout>E[0-9A-Z][0-9a-z_A-Z]+</literallayout>

		<para>against macros (i.e. in all namespaces). By prohibiting the
			user from using names of this form, the intention is to protect
			against namespace clashes with extensions of the &ansi; &api; which
			introduce new error numbers. It also protects against a particular
			implementation of these extensions - namely that new error numbers
			will be defined as macros.</para>

		<para>A better example of protecting against particular
			implementations comes from &posix;. If <code>sys/stat.h</code> is
			included names of the form:</para>

		<literallayout>st_[0-9a-z_A-Z]+</literallayout>

		<para>are reserved against macros (as member names). The intention
			here is not only to reserve field selector names for future
			extensions to <code>struct stat</code> (which would only affect &api;
			implementors, not ordinary users), but also to reserve against the
			possibility that these field selectors might be implemented by
			macros. So our <code>st_atime</code> example in section 2.2.3 is
			strictly illegal because the procedure name <code>st_atime</code>
			lies in a restricted namespace. Indeed the namespace is restricted
			precisely to disallow this program.</para>

		<para>As an exercise to the reader, how many of your programs use
			names from the following restricted namespaces (all drawn from
			&ansi;, all applying to all namespaces)?</para>

		<literallayout>is[a-z][0-9a-z_A-Z]+                            (ctype.h)
to[a-z][0-9a-z_A-Z]+                            (ctype.h)
str[a-z][0-9a-z_A-Z]+                           (stdlib.h)</literallayout>

		<para>With the &tdf; approach of describing &api;s in abstract terms
			using the <code>#pragma token</code> syntax most of these namespace
			restrictions are seen to be superfluous. When a target independent
			header is included precisely the objects defined in that header in
			that version of the &api; appear in the namespace. There are no
			worries about what else might happen to be in the header, because
			there is nothing else. Also implementation details are separated
			off to the &tdf; library building, so possible namespace pollution
			through particular implementations does not arise.</para>

		<para>Currently &tdf; does not have a neat way of solving the
			<code>va_list</code> problem. The present target independent
			headers use a similar workaround to that described above
			(exploiting a reserved namespace). (See the footnote in section
			3.4.1.1.<!-- TODO: link -->)</para>

		<para>None of this is intended as criticism of the &ansi; or &posix;
			standards. It merely shows some of the problems that can arise
			from the insufficient separation of code.</para>
	</section>

</chapter>

