<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter id="info-file">
	<title>The C information file</title>

	<para>The grammar specification itself is not sufficient to produce a
		parser. There also needs to be output language specific information to
		allow the parser to interface with the program it is to be part of. In
		the case of the C output routines, &sid; needs to know the
		following information:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>What code should precede and succeed the automatically
				generated code.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>How to map the &sid; identifiers into C
				identifiers.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>How to do assignments for each type.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>How to get the current terminal number.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>How to get the result of the current terminal.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>How to advance the lexical analyser, to get the next
				terminal.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>What the actions are defined as, and how to pass parameters to
				them.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>How to save and restore the current terminal when an error
				occurs.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Eventually almost all of this should be user suppliable. At the
		moment, some of the information is supplied by the user in the C
		information file, some through macros, and some is built in.
		&sid; currently gets the information as follows:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>The C information file has a header and a trailer section,
				which define code that precedes and succeeds the code that
				&sid; generates.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>The C information file has a section that allows the user to
				specify mappings from &sid; identifiers into C
				identifiers. These are only valid for the following types of
				identifiers: types, functions (implementations of rules) and
				terminals. For other identifier types (or when no mapping is
				supplied), &sid; uses some default rules:</para>

			<para>Firstly, &sid; applies a transform to the
				&sid; identifier name, to make it a legal C identifier.
				At present this maps <code>_</code> to <code>__</code>,
				<code>-</code> to <code>_H</code> and <code>:</code> (this occurs
				in scoped names) to <code>_C</code>. All other characters are
				left unmodified. This transform cannot be changed.</para>

			<para>&sid; also puts a prefix before all identifiers, to
				try to prevent clashes (and also to make automatically generated
				- i.e. numeric - identifiers legal). These prefixes can be
				redefined for each class of identifier, in the C information file.
				They should be chosen so as not to clash with any other
				identifiers (i.e. no other identifiers should begin with that
				prefix).</para>

			<para>By default, the following prefixes are used:</para>

			<table>
				<title>Identifier prefixes</title>

				<col align="center"/>
				<col align="left"/>

				<thead>
					<tr>
						<th>Prefix</th>
						<th>Meaning</th>
					</tr>
				</thead>

				<tbody>
					<tr>
						<td><code>ZT</code></td>
						<td>This prefix is used before type identifiers, for
							the type name itself.</td>
					</tr>

					<tr>
						<td><code>ZR</code></td>
						<td>This prefix is used before rule identifiers, for
							the rule's implementation function.</td>
					</tr>

					<tr>
						<td><code>ZL</code></td>
						<td>This prefix is used before rule identifiers, for
							the rule's label when tail recursion is being
							eliminated. In this case, a number is added to the
							suffix before the identifier name, to prevent clashes
							when a rule is inlined twice in the same function.	It
							is also used before other labels that are automatically
							generated and are just numbered.</td>
					</tr>

					<tr>
						<td><code>ZI</code></td>
						<td>This prefix is used before name identifiers used as
							parameters to functions, or in normal usage. It is also
							used by non-local names (which doesn't cause a problem
							as they always occur scoped, and local names never
							do).</td>
					</tr>

					<tr>
						<td><code>ZO</code></td>
						<td>This prefix is used before name identifiers used as
							results of functions. Results are passed as reference
							parameters, and this suffix is used then. Another
							identifier with the <code>ZI</code> prefix is also used
							within the function, and the type reference assignment
							operator is used at the end of the function to assign
							the results to the reference parameters.</td>
					</tr>

					<tr>
						<td><code>ZB</code></td>
						<td>This prefix is used before the terminal symbol
							names in the generated header file.</td>
					</tr>
				</tbody>
			</table>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>Normally, &sid; will do assignments using the C
				assignment operator. Sometimes, this will not do the right thing,
				so the user can define a set of assignment operations for any type
				in the C information file.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>&sid; expects the <code>CURRENT_TERMINAL</code>
				macro to be defined, and its definition should return an integer
				that is the current terminal. The macro should be an expression,
				not a statement.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>It is necessary to define how to extract the results of all
				terminals in the C information file (if a terminal doesn't return
				anything, then it is not necessary to define how to get the
				result).</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>&sid; expects the <code>ADVANCE_LEXER</code> macro
				to be defined, and its definition should cause the lexical
				analyser to read a new token. The new terminal number should be
				accessible through the <code>CURRENT_TERMINAL</code> macro. On
				entry into the parser <code>CURRENT_TERMINAL</code> should give
				the first terminal number.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>All actions, and their parameter and result names are defined
				in the C information file.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>&sid; expects the <code>SAVE_LEXER</code> and
				<code>RESTORE_LEXER</code> macros to be defined. The first is
				called with an argument which is the error terminal value. The
				macro should save the current terminal's value, and set the
				current terminal to be the error terminal value. The second macro
				is called without arguments, and should restore the saved value of
				the current terminal.	<code>SAVE_LEXER</code> will never be
				called more than once without a call to
				<code>RESTORE_LEXER</code>, so the save stack only needs one
				element.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>&sid; expects the <code>ERROR_TERMINAL</code> macro to be
				defined if the <code>-s no-numeric-terminals</code> option is
				given. This is expected to specify a value which is not a valid
				terminal number. This is required as with non-numeric terminals
				(that is, symbolic names) a non-terminal value would not
				otherwise be known.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>The remainder of this section describes the layout of the C
		information file. The lexical conventions are described first, followed
		by a description of the sections in the order in which they should
		appear. Unlike the &sid; grammar file, not all sections are
		mandatory.</para>

	<section id="info-lex">
		<title>Lexical conventions</title>

		<para>The lexical conventions of the C information file are very similar
			to those of the &sid; grammar file. There is a second class
			of identifier: the C identifier, which is a subset of the valid
			&sid; identifiers; there is also the C code block.</para>

		<para>A C code block begins with <code>@{</code> and is terminated by
			<code>@}</code>. The code block consists of all of the characters
			between the start and end of the code block, subject to substitutions.
			All substitutions begin with the <code>@</code> character. The
			following substitutions are recognised:</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@@</code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This substitutes the <code>@</code> character itself.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@:<replaceable>label</replaceable></code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This form marks a label, which will be substituted for in
						the output code. This is necessary, because an action may be
						inlined into the same function more than once. If this happens,
						then without doing label substitution there would be two
						identical labels in the same scope. With label substitution,
						this problem is avoided. In general, all references to a label
						within an action should be prefixed with <code>@:</code>. This
						substitution may not be used in header and trailer code
						blocks.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@<replaceable>identifier</replaceable></code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This form marks a parameter or result identifier
						substitution. If parameter and result identifiers are not
						prefixed with an <code>@</code> character, then they will not be
						substituted. It is an error if the identifier is not a parameter
						or a result. Header and trailer code blocks have no parameters
						or results, so it is always an error to use identifier
						substitution in them. It is an error if any of the result
						identifiers are not substituted at least once.</para>

					<para>Result identifiers may be assigned to using this form of
						identifier substitution, but parameter identifiers may not be
						(nor may their address be taken - they are immutable). To try
						to prevent this, parameters that are substituted may be cast
						to their own type, which makes them unmodifiable in ISO C (see
						the notes on the <code>casts</code>
						language specific option).</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@&amp;<replaceable>identifier</replaceable></code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This form marks a parameter identifier whose address is to
						be substituted, but whose contents will not be modified. The
						effects of modifying the identifier are undefined. It is an
						error to use this in parameter assignment operator
						definitions.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@=<replaceable>identifier</replaceable></code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This form marks a parameter identifier that will be
						modified. For this to be useful, the parameter should be a call
						by reference parameter, so that the effect of the modification
						will be propagated. This substitution is only valid in actions
						(assignment operators are not allowed to modify their
						parameters).</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@!</code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This form marks an exception raise. In the generated code,
						a jump to the current exception handler will be substituted.
						This substitution is only valid in actions
						and terminal extraction rules.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@.</code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This form marks an attempt to access the current terminal.
						This substitution is only valid in actions.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@&gt;</code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This form marks an attempt to advance the lexical analyser.
						This substitution is only valid in actions.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>@$<replaceable>terminal</replaceable></code></term>

				<listitem>
					<para>This form introduces a terminal, as would be referenced by
						the parser itself. This serves two purposes; firstly it acts
						as a convenience for consistency to the grammar (as opposed
						to writing the underlying C symbols), and secondly the
						expansion of <code>@$</code> is subject to the same rules
						as references to terminals elsewhere in the grammar. Most
						notably, this includes <code>-s numeric-terminals</code>
						causing the terminal name to expand numerically.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>All other forms are illegal. Note that in the case of labels and
			identifiers, no white space is allowed between the <code>@:</code>,
			<code>@</code>, <code>@&amp;</code> or <code>@=</code> and the
			identifier name. An example of a code block is:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">@{
	/* A code block */
	{
		int i ;

		if ( @param ) {
			@! ;
		}

		@result = 0 ;
		for ( i = 0 ; i &lt; 100 ; i++ ) {
			printf ( "{%d}\n", i ) ;
			@result += i ;
		}

		@=param += @result ;
		if ( @. == @$SEMI ) {
			@&gt; ;
		}
	}
@}</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="prefixes">
		<title>The prefixes section</title>

		<para>The first section in the C information file is the prefix
			definition section. This section is optional. It begins with the
			section header, followed by a list of prefix definitions. A prefix
			definition begins with the prefix name, followed by a <code>=</code>
			symbol, followed by a C identifier that is the new prefix, and
			terminated by a semicolon. The following example shows all of the
			prefix names, and their default values:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%prefixes%
type      = ZT ;
function  = ZR ;
label     = ZL ;
input     = ZI ;
output    = ZO ;
terminal  = ZB ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="persistents">
		<title>The persistent section</title>

		<para>&sid; supports passing local variables through rules in the
			grammar, which are eventually passed on to actions. This helps keep
			the generated parser thread-safe, since each variable may be passed
			through from the entry point.  However in practise, often grammars
			tend to build up a structure which is conceptually global to all
			rules (commonly some sort of <quote>parse tree</quote> under
			construction). To pass this through each rule in the grammar and on
			to all actions is certainly possible, but a little
			inconvenient:</para>

		<programlisting language="sid">rule: ( l1 : ParsetreeT, ... ) -> ( ... ) = {
	...
}</programlisting>

		<para>However, adding this declaration to each rule and action would be
			tiresome and error-prone. Instead, it reads more naturally to view
			this variable as if it were <quote>global</quote>. This keeps it
			out of the grammar entirely, as it is a concept specific to the
			action file. <firstterm>Persistent variables</firstterm> provide a
			mechanism to automate this process of passing-through as described
			above, whilst leaving the grammar file untouched. (This could be
			done by hand, though it would require passing variables through
			rules in the grammar; hence persistent variables are not
			necessary, but merely nice to have.)</para>

		<para>From a user's perspective, persistent variables act as globals
			specific to each invocation. They are accessible by every rule and
			every parsing instance. Since they originate from an entry point,
			they persist only for each invocation of an entry into the parser.</para>

		<para>Persistent variables are declared in their own section. This
			section is optional.</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%persistents%

	pv1 : Type1T ;
	pv2 : Type2T ;
</programlisting>

		<para>The persistent variables declared may be used in actions in the
			same manner as actions' parameters:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">&lt;append-node&gt; : ( l1 : Type3 ) -&gt; ( ) = @{
	f ( @pv1, @pv1, @l1 ) ;
@} ;
</programlisting>

		<para>These are passed in at the entry point to the parser.</para>
		<!-- TODO an example? what order are they passed in? -->


		<!-- TODO: what did Kevin mean here?
			<kevin2993> The caller can always initialize them then ignore them on return.
		-->

		<para>Since the <code>ADVANCE_LEXER</code> macro is expanded inside
			generated functions that represent rules, it too may access persistent
			variables, as they are in scope in all rules.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="maps">
		<title>The maps section</title>

		<para>The section that follows the prefixes section is the maps section.
			This section is also optional. It begins with its section header,
			followed by a list of identifier mappings. An identifier mapping
			begins with a &sid; identifier (either a type, a rule or a
			terminal), followed by the <code>-&gt;</code> symbol, followed by the
			C identifier it is to be mapped to, and terminated by a semicolon. An
			example follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%maps%
NumberT    -&gt; unsigned ;
calculator -&gt; calculator ;</programlisting>

		<para>Note that it is not possible to map type identifiers to be
			arbitrary C types. It will be necessary to <code>typedef</code> or
			macro define the type name in the C file.</para>

		<para>It is recommended that all types, terminals and entry point rules
			have their names mapped in this section, although this is not
			necessary. If the names are not mapped, they will have funny names in
			the rest of the program.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="header">
		<title>The header section</title>

		<para>After the maps section comes the header section. This begins with
			the section header, followed by a code block, followed by a comma,
			followed by a second code block, and terminated with a semicolon. The
			first code block will be inserted at the beginning of the generated
			parser file; the second code block will be inserted at the start of
			the generated header file. An example is:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%header% @{
	#include "lexer.h"

	LexerT token ;

	#define CURRENT_TERMINAL token.t
	#define ADVANCE_LEXER    next_token ()

	extern void terminal_error () ;
	extern void syntax_error () ;
@}, @{
@} ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="assign">
		<title>The assignments section</title>

		<para>The assignments section follows the header section. This section
			is optional. Normally, assignment between two identifiers will be done
			using the C assignment operator. In some cases this will not do the
			correct thing, and it is necessary to do the assignment differently.
			All types for which this applies should have an entry in the
			assignments section. The section begins with its header, followed by
			definitions for each type that needs its own assignment operator. Each
			definition should have one parameter, and one result. The action's
			name should be the name of the type. An example follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%assignments%

ListT : ( l1 ) -&gt; ( l2 ) = @{
	if ( @l2.head = @l1.head ) {
		@l2.tail = @l1.tail ;
	} else {
		@l2.tail = &amp;( @l2.head ) ;
	}
@} ;</programlisting>

		<para>If a type has an assignment operator defined, it must also have a
			parameter assignment operator type defined and a result assignment
			operator defined (more precisely it must have either no assignment
			operations defined, or all three assignment operations
			defined).</para>
	</section>

	<section id="param-assign">
		<title>The parameter assignments section</title>

		<para>The parameter assignments section is very similar to the
			assignments section (which it follows), and is also optional. If a
			type has an assignment section entry, it must have a parameter
			assignment entry as well.</para>

		<para>The parameter assignment operator is used in function calls to
			ensure that the object is copied correctly: if no parameter assignment
			operator is provided for a type, the standard C call by copy mechanism
			is used; if a parameter assignment operator is provided for a type,
			then the address of the object is passed by the calling function, and
			the called function declares a local of the same type, and uses the
			parameter assignment operator to copy the object (this should be
			remembered when passing parameters to entry points that have arguments
			of a type that has a parameter assignment operator defined).</para>

		<para>The difference between the parameter assignment operator and the
			assignment operator is that the parameter identifier to the parameter
			assignment operator is a pointer to the object being manipulated,
			rather than the object itself. An example reference assignment section
			is:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%parameter-assignments%

ListT : ( l1 ) -&gt; ( l2 ) = @{
	if ( @l2.head = @l1-&gt;head ) {
		@l2.tail = @l1-&gt;tail ;
	} else {
		@l2.tail = &amp;( @l2.head ) ;
	}
@} ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="result-assign">
		<title>The result assignments section</title>

		<para>The result assignments section is very similar to the assignments
			section and the parameter assignments section (which it follows), and
			is also optional. If a type has an assignment section entry, it must
			also have a result assignment entry. The only difference between the
			two is that the result identifier of the result assignment operation
			is a pointer to the object being manipulated, rather than the object
			itself. Result assignments are only used when the results of a rule
			are assigned back through the reference parameters passed into the
			function. An example result assignment section is:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%result-assignments%

ListT : ( l1 ) -&gt; ( l2 ) = @{
	if ( @l2-&gt;head = @l1.head ) {
		@l2-&gt;tail = @l1.tail ;
	} else {
		@l2-&gt;tail = &amp;( @l2-&gt;head ) ;
	}
@} ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="term-result">
		<title>The terminal result extraction section</title>

		<para>The terminal result extraction section follows the reference
			assignment section. It defines how to extract the results from
			terminals. The section begins with its section header, followed by the
			terminal extraction definitions.</para>

		<para>There must be a definition for every terminal in the grammar that
			returns a result. It is an error to include a definition for a
			terminal that doesn't return a result. The result of the definition
			should be the same as the result of the terminal. An example of the
			terminal result extraction section follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%terminals%

number : () -&gt; ( n ) = @{
	@n = token.u.number ;
@} ;

identifier : () -&gt; ( i ) = @{
	@i = token.u.identifier ;
@} ;

string : () -&gt; ( s ) = @{
	@s = token.u.string ;
@} ;</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="action-defn">
		<title>The action definition section</title>

		<para>The action definition section follows the terminal result
			extractor definition section. The format is similar to the previous
			sections: the section header followed by definitions for all of the
			actions. An action definition has the following form:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">&lt;action-name&gt; : ( parameters ) -&gt; ( results ) = code-block ;</programlisting>

		<para>This is similar to the form of all previous definitions, except
			that the name is surrounded in angle brackets. What follows is also
			true of the other definitions as well (unless they state
			otherwise).</para>

		<para>The <code>action-name</code> is a &sid; identifier that
			is the name of the action being defined; <code>parameters</code> is a
			comma separated list of C identifiers that will be the names of the
			parameters passed to the action, and <code>results</code> is a comma
			separated list of C identifiers that will be the names of the result
			parameters passed to the action. The <code>code-block</code> is the C
			code that defines the action. It is expected that this will assign a
			valid result to each of the result identifier names.</para>

		<para>The parameter and result tuples have the same form as in the
			language independent file, except that the types are optional.	Like
			the language independent file, if the type of an action is zero-tuple
			to zero-tuple, then the type can be omitted, e.g.:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">&lt;action&gt; = @{ /* .... */ @} ;</programlisting>

		<para>An example action definition section is:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%actions%

&lt;add&gt; : ( v1, v2 ) -&gt; ( v3 ) = @{
	@v3 = @v1 + @v2 ;
@} ;

&lt;subtract&gt; : ( v1 : NumberT, v2 : NumberT ) -&gt; ( v3 : NumberT ) = @{
	@v3 = @v1 - @v2 ;
@} ;

&lt;multiply&gt; : ( v1 : NumberT, v2 ) -&gt; ( v3 ) = @{
	@v3 = @v1 * @v2 ;
@} ;

&lt;divide&gt; : ( v1, v2 ) -&gt; ( v3 : NumberT ) = @{
	@v3 = @v1 / @v2 ;
@} ;

&lt;print&gt; : ( v ) -&gt; () = @{
	printf ( "%u\n", @v ) ;
@} ;

&lt;error&gt; = @{
	fprintf ( stderr, "ERROR\n" ) ;
	exit ( EXIT_FAILURE ) ;
@} ;</programlisting>

		<para>Do not define static variables in action definitions; if you do,
			you will get unexpected results. If you wish to use static variables
			in actions definitions, then define them in the header block.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="trailer">
		<title>The trailer section</title>

		<para>After the action definition section comes the trailer section.
			This has the same form as the header section. An example is:</para>

		<programlisting language="act">%trailer% @{
	int main ()
	{
		next_token () ;
		calculator ( NULL ) ;
		return 0 ;
	}
@}, @{
@} ;</programlisting>

		<para>The code blocks will be appended to the generated parser, and the
			generated header file respectively.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

