<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter id="token">
	<title>Token syntax</title>

	<para>The C and C++ producers allow place-holders for various categories
		of syntactic classes to be expressed using directives of the form:</para>

	<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA token <replaceable>token-spec</replaceable></programlisting>

	<para>or simply:</para>

	<programlisting language="c">#pragma token <replaceable>token-spec</replaceable></programlisting>

	<para>These place-holders are represented as TDF tokens and hence are called
		tokens.  These tokens stand for a certain type, expression or whatever
		which is to be represented by a certain named TDF token in the producer
		output.  This mechanism is used, for example, to allow C API specifications
		to be represented target independently.  The types, functions and
		expressions comprising the API can be described using <code>#pragma
		token</code> directives and the target dependent definitions of these
		tokens, representing the implementation of the API on a particular
		machine, can be linked in later.  This mechanism is described in detail
		elsewhere.</para>

	<para>A summary of the grammar for the
		<code>#pragma token</code> directives accepted by the C++ producer
		is given in &tdfcpragma.5;.</para>


		<section id="spec">
			<title>Token specifications</title>

			<para>A token specification is divided into two components, a
				<replaceable>token-introduction</replaceable> giving the token sort, and a
				<replaceable>token-identification</replaceable> giving the internal and external token
				names:</para>

			<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>token-spec</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>token-introduction token-identification</replaceable>

<replaceable>token-introduction</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>exp-token</replaceable>
	<replaceable>statement-token</replaceable>
	<replaceable>type-token</replaceable>
	<replaceable>member-token</replaceable>
	<replaceable>procedure-token</replaceable>

<replaceable>token-identification</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>token-namespace&opt.bnf; identifier</replaceable> # <replaceable>external-identifier&opt.bnf;</replaceable>

<replaceable>token-namespace</replaceable> :
	TAG

<replaceable>external-identifier</replaceable> :
	-
	<replaceable>preproc-token-list</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>The <code>TAG</code> qualifier is used to indicate that the internal
				name lies in the C tag namespace.  This only makes sense for structure
				and union types.  The external token name can be given by any sequence
				of preprocessing tokens.  These tokens are not macro expanded.  If
				no external name is given then the internal name is used.  The special
				external name <code>-</code> is used to indicate that the token does
				not have an associated external name, and hence is local to the current
				translation unit.  Such a local token must be defined.  White space
				in the external name (other than at the start or end) is used to indicate
				that a TDF unique name should be used.  The white space serves as
				a separator for the unique name components.</para>

			<section id="expression-tokens">
				<title>Expression tokens</title>

				<para>Expression tokens are specified as follows:</para>

				<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>exp-token</replaceable> :
	EXP <replaceable>exp-storage&opt.bnf;</replaceable> : <replaceable>type-id</replaceable> :
	NAT
	INTEGER</programlisting>

				<para>representing a expression of the given type, a non-negative integer
					constant and general integer constant, respectively.  Each expression
					has an associated storage class:</para>

<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>exp-storage</replaceable> :
	lvalue
	rvalue
	const</programlisting>

				<para>indicating whether it is an lvalue, an rvalue or a compile-time constant
					expression.  An absent <replaceable>exp-storage</replaceable> is equivalent to
					<code>rvalue</code>.  All expression tokens lie in the macro namespace;
					that is, they may potentially be defined as macros.</para>

				<para>For backwards compatibility with the C producer, the directive:</para>

				<programlisting language="cpp">#pragma TenDRA++ rvalue token as const <replaceable>allow</replaceable></programlisting>

				<para>causes <code>rvalue</code> tokens to be treated as <code>const</code> tokens.</para>
			</section>

			<section>
				<title>Statement tokens</title>

				<para>Statement tokens are specified as follows:</para>

				<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>statement-token</replaceable> :
	STATEMENT</programlisting>

				<para>All statement tokens lie in the macro namespace.</para>
			</section>

			<section>
				<title>Type tokens</title>

				<para>Type tokens are specified as follows:</para>

				<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>type-token</replaceable> :
	TYPE
	VARIETY
	VARIETY signed
	VARIETY unsigned
	FLOAT
	ARITHMETIC
	SCALAR
	CLASS
	STRUCT
	UNION</programlisting>

				<para>representing a generic type, an integral type, a signed integral type,
					an unsigned integral type, a floating point type, an arithmetic (integral
					or floating point) type, a scalar (arithmetic or pointer) type, a
					class type, a structure type and a union type respectively.</para>

				<warning>
					<para>Floating-point, arithmetic and scalar token types have not yet been
						implemented correctly in either the C or C++ producers.</para>
				</warning>
			</section>

			<section id="member-tokens">
				<title>Member tokens</title>

				<para>Member tokens are specified as follows:</para>

				<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>member-token</replaceable> :
	MEMBER <replaceable>access-specifier&opt.bnf; member-type-id</replaceable> : <replaceable>type-id</replaceable> :</programlisting>

				<para>where an <replaceable>access-specifier</replaceable> of <code>public</code> is assumed
					if none is given.  The member type is given by:</para>

				<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>member-type-id</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>type-id</replaceable>
	<replaceable>type-id</replaceable> % <replaceable>constant-expression</replaceable></programlisting>

				<para>where <code>%</code> is used to denote bitfield members (since
					<code>:</code> is used as a separator).  The second type denotes the
					structure or union the given member belongs to.  Different types can
					have members with the same internal name, but the external token name
					must be unique.  Note that only non-static data members can be represented
					in this form.</para>

				<para>Two declarations for the same <code>MEMBER</code> token (including token
					definitions) should have the same type, however the directive:</para>

				<programlisting language="cpp">#pragma TenDRA++ incompatible member declaration <replaceable>allow</replaceable></programlisting>

				<para>allows declarations with different types, provided these types have the
					same size and alignment requirements.</para>
			</section>

			<section>
				<title>Procedure tokens</title>

				<para>Procedure, or high-level, tokens are specified in one of three ways:</para>

				<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>procedure-token</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>general-procedure</replaceable>
	<replaceable>simple-procedure</replaceable>
	<replaceable>function-procedure</replaceable></programlisting>

				<para>All procedure tokens (except ellipsis functions - see below) lie in
					the macro namespace.  The most general form of procedure token specifies
					two sets of parameters.  The bound parameters are those which are
					used in encoding the actual TDF output, and the program parameters
					are those which are specified in the program.
					The program parameters are expressed in terms of the bound parameters.
					A program parameter can be an expression token parameter, a statement
					token parameter, a member token parameter, a procedure token parameter
					or any type.  The bound parameters are deduced from the program parameters
					by a similar process to that used in template argument deduction.</para>

				<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>general-procedure</replaceable> :
	PROC { <replaceable>bound-toks&opt.bnf;</replaceable> | <replaceable>prog-pars&opt.bnf;</replaceable> } <replaceable>token-introduction
  </replaceable>

<replaceable>bound-toks</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>bound-token</replaceable>
	<replaceable>bound-token</replaceable> , <replaceable>bound-toks</replaceable>

<replaceable>bound-token</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>token-introduction token-namespace&opt.bnf; identifier</replaceable>

<replaceable>prog-pars</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>program-parameter</replaceable>
	<replaceable>program-parameter</replaceable> , <replaceable>prog-pars</replaceable>

<replaceable>program-parameter</replaceable> :
	EXP <replaceable>identifier</replaceable>
	STATEMENT <replaceable>identifier</replaceable>
	TYPE <replaceable>type-id</replaceable>
	MEMBER <replaceable>type-id</replaceable> : <replaceable>identifier</replaceable>
	PROC <replaceable>identifier</replaceable></programlisting>

				<para>The simplest form of a <replaceable>general-procedure</replaceable>
					is one in which the <replaceable>prog-pars</replaceable>
					correspond precisely to the <replaceable>bound-toks</replaceable>.  In
					this case the syntax:</para>

				<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>simple-procedure</replaceable> :
	PROC ( <replaceable>simple-toks&opt.bnf;</replaceable> ) <replaceable>token-introduction</replaceable>

<replaceable>simple-toks</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>simple-token</replaceable>
	<replaceable>simple-token</replaceable> , <replaceable>simple-toks</replaceable>

<replaceable>simple-token</replaceable> :
	<replaceable>token-introduction token-namespace&opt.bnf; identifier&opt.bnf;</replaceable></programlisting>

				<para>may be used.  Note that the parameter names are optional.</para>

				<para>A function token is specified as follows:</para>

				<programlisting language="tdf"><replaceable>function-procedure</replaceable> :
	FUNC <replaceable>type-id</replaceable> :</programlisting>

				<para>where the given type is a function type.  This has two effects: firstly
					a function with the given type is declared; secondly, if the function
					type has the form:</para>

				<programlisting language="c">r ( p1, ...., pn )</programlisting>
	
				<para>a procedure token with sort:</para>

				<programlisting language="tdf">PROC ( EXP rvalue : p1 :, ...., EXP rvalue : pn : ) EXP rvalue : r :</programlisting>

				<para>is declared.  For ellipsis function types only the function, not the
					token, is declared.  Note that the token behaves like a macro definition
					of the corresponding function.  Unless explicitly enclosed in a linkage
					specification, a function declared using a <code>FUNC</code>
					token has C linkage.  Note that it is possible for two <code>FUNC</code>
					tokens to have the same internal name, because of function overloading,
					however external names must be unique.</para>

				<para>The directive:</para>

				<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA incompatible interface declaration <replaceable>allow</replaceable></programlisting>

				<para>can be used to allow incompatible redeclarations of functions declared
					using <code>FUNC</code> tokens.  The token declaration takes precedence.</para>


				<warning>
					<para>Certain of the more complex examples of <code>PROC</code> tokens such
						as, for example, tokens with <code>PROC</code> parameters, have not
						been implemented in either the C or C++ producers.</para>
				</warning>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="token-arguments">
			<title>Token arguments</title>

			<para>As mentioned above, the program parameters for a <code>PROC</code>
				token are those specified in the program itself.  These arguments
				are expressed as a comma-separated list enclosed in brackets, the
				form of each argument being determined by the corresponding program
				parameter.</para>

			<para>An <code>EXP</code> argument is an assignment expression.  This must
				be an lvalue for <code>lvalue</code> tokens and a constant expression
				for <code>const</code> tokens.  The argument is converted to the token
				type (for <code>lvalue</code> tokens this is essentially a conversion
				between the corresponding reference types).  A <code>NAT</code> or
				<code>INTEGER</code> argument is an integer constant expression.
				In the former case this must be non-negative.</para>

			<para>A <code>STATEMENT</code> argument is a statement.  This statement
				should not contain any labels or any <code>goto</code> or <code>return</code>
				statements.</para>

			<para>A type argument is a type identifier.  This must name a type of the
				correct category for the corresponding token.  For example, a
				<code>VARIETY</code> token requires an integral type.</para>

			<para>A member argument must describe the offset of a member
				or nested member of the given structure or union type.  The type
				of the member should agree with that of the <code>MEMBER</code> token.
				The general form of a member offset can be described in terms of member
				selectors and array indexes as follows:</para>

			<programlisting language="bnf">
<replaceable>member-offset</replaceable> :
	::<replaceable>&opt.bnf; id-expression</replaceable>
	<replaceable>member-offset</replaceable> . ::<replaceable>&opt.bnf; id-expression</replaceable>
	<replaceable>member-offset</replaceable> [ <replaceable>constant-expression</replaceable> ]</programlisting>

			<para>A <code>PROC</code> argument is an identifier.  This identifier must
				name a <code>PROC</code> token of the appropriate sort.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="tokdef">
			<title>Defining tokens</title>

			<para>Given a token specification of a syntactic object and a normal language
				definition of the same object (including macro definitions if the
				token lies in the macro namespace), the producers attempt to unify
				the two by defining the TDF token in terms of the given definition.
				Whether the token specification occurs before or after the language
				definition is immaterial.  Unification also takes place in situations
				where, for example, two types are known to be compatible.  Multiple
				consistent explicit token definitions are allowed by default when
				allowed by the language; this is controlled by the directive:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA compatible token <replaceable>allow</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>The default unification behaviour may be modified using the directives:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA no_def <replaceable>token-list</replaceable>
#pragma TenDRA define <replaceable>token-list</replaceable>
#pragma TenDRA reject <replaceable>token-list</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>or equivalently:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma no_def <replaceable>token-list</replaceable>
#pragma define <replaceable>token-list</replaceable>
#pragma ignore <replaceable>token-list</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>which set the state of the tokens given in <replaceable>token-list</replaceable>.
				A state of <code>no_def</code> means that no unification is attempted and
				that any attempt to explicitly define the token results in an error.
				A state of <code>define</code> means that unification takes place
				and that the token must be defined somewhere in the translation unit.
				A state of <code>reject</code> means that unification takes place as
				normal, but any resulting token definition is discarded and not output
				to the TDF capsule.</para>

			<para>If a token with the state <code>define</code> is not defined, then the
				behaviour depends on the sort of the token.  A <code>FUNC</code> token
				is implicitly defined in terms of its underlying function, such as:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#define f( a1, ...., an )	( f ) ( a1, ...., an )</programlisting>

			<para>Other undefined tokens cause an error.  This behaviour can be modified
				using the directives:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA++ implicit token definition <replaceable>allow</replaceable>
#pragma TenDRA++ no token definition <replaceable>allow</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>respectively.</para>

			<para>The primitive operations, <code>no_def</code>, <code>define</code> and
				<code>reject</code>, can also be expressed using the context sensitive
				directive:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA interface <replaceable>token-list</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>or equivalently:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma interface <replaceable>token-list</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>By default this is equivalent to <code>no_def</code>, but may be modified
				by inclusion using one of the directives:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA extend <replaceable>header-name</replaceable>
#pragma TenDRA implement <replaceable>header-name</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>or equivalently:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma extend interface <replaceable>header-name</replaceable>
#pragma implement interface <replaceable>header-name</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>These are equivalent to:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#include <replaceable>header-name</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>except that the form <code>[....]</code> is allowed as a header name.
				This is equivalent to <code>&lt;....&gt;</code> except that it starts
				the directory search after the point at which the including file was
				found, rather than at the start of the path (i.e. it is equivalent
				to the <code>#include_next</code> directive found in some preprocessors).
				The effect of the <code>extend</code> directive on the state of the
				<code>interface</code> directive is as follows:</para>

			<!-- TODO: informaltable? -->
			<screen>no_def -&gt; no_def
define -&gt; reject
reject -&gt; reject</screen>

			<para>The effect of the <code>implement</code> directive is as follows:</para>

<screen>no_def -&gt; define
define -&gt; define
reject -&gt; reject</screen>

			<para>That is to say, a <code>implement</code> directive will cause all
				the tokens in the given header to be defined and their definitions
				output. Any tokens included in this header by <code>extend</code>
				may be defined, but their definitions will not be output.  This is
				precisely the behaviour which is required to ensure that each token
				is defined exactly once in an API library build.</para>

			<para>The lists of tokens in the directives above are expressed in the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>token-list</replaceable> :
<replaceable>token-id token-list&opt.bnf;</replaceable>
# <replaceable>preproc-token-list</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>where a <replaceable>token-id</replaceable> represents an internal token name:</para>

			<programlisting language="bnf"><replaceable>token-id</replaceable> :
<replaceable>token-namespace&opt.bnf; identifier</replaceable>
<replaceable>type-id</replaceable> . <replaceable>identifier</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>Note that member tokens are specified by means of both the member
				name and its parent type.  In this type specifier, <code>TAG</code>,
				rather than <code>class</code>, <code>struct</code> or <code>union</code>, may
				be used in elaborated type specifiers for structure and union tokens.
				If the <replaceable>token-id</replaceable> names an overloaded function then the directive is
				applied to all <code>FUNC</code> tokens of that name.  It is possible
				to  be more selective using the <code>#</code> form which allows the
				external token name to be specified.  Such an entry must be the last
				in a <replaceable>token-list</replaceable>.</para>

			<para>A related directive has the form:</para>

			<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA++ undef token <replaceable>token-list</replaceable></programlisting>

			<para>which undefines all the given tokens so that they are no longer visible.</para>

			<para>As noted above, a macro is only considered as a token definition if
				the token lies in the macro namespace.  Tokens which are not in the
				macro namespace, such as types and members, cannot be defined using
				macros. Occasionally API implementations do define member selector
				as macros in terms of other member selectors.  Such a token needs
				to be explicitly defined using a directive of the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA member definition <replaceable>type-id</replaceable> : <replaceable>identifier member-offset</replaceable></programlisting>

		<para>where <replaceable>member-offset</replaceable> is <link linkend="token-arguments">as above</link>.</para>
	</section>

</chapter>

