<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter id="introduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>TDF is a porting technology and, as a result, it is a central part of a
		shrink-wrapping, distribution and installation technology. TDF has been
		chosen by the Open Software Foundation as the basis of its Architecture
		Neutral Distribution Format. It was developed by the United Kingdom's
		Defence Research Agency (DRA). TDF is not UNIX specific, although most of
		the implementation has been done on UNIX.</para>

	<para>Software vendors, when they port their programs to several platforms,
		usually wish to take advantage of the particular features of each platform.
		That is, they wish the versions of their programs on each platform to be
		functionally equivalent, but not necessarily algorithmically identical. TDF
		is intended for porting in this sense. It is designed so that a program in
		its TDF form can be systematically modified when it arrives at the target
		platform to achieve the intended functionality and to use the algorithms and
		data structures which are appropriate and efficient for the target machine.
		A fully efficient program, specialised to each target, is a necessity if
		independent software vendors are to take-up a porting technology.</para>

	<para>These modifications are systematic because, on the source machine,
		programmers work with generalised declarations of the APIs they are using.
		The declarations express the requirements of the APIs without giving their
		implementation. The declarations are specified in terms of TDF's
		&ldquo;tokens&rdquo;, and the TDF which is produced contains uses of these
		tokens. On each target machine the tokens are used as the basis for suitable
		substitutions and alterations.</para>

	<para>Using TDF for porting places extra requirements on software vendors and API
		designers. Software vendors must write their programs scrupulously in terms
		of APIs and nothing more. API designers need to produce an interface which
		can be specialised to efficient data structures and constructions on all
		relevant machines.</para>

	<para>TDF is neutral with respect to the set of languages which has been
		considered. The design of C, C++, Fortran and Pascal is quite conventional,
		in the sense that they are sufficiently similar for TDF constructions to be
		devised to represent them all. These TDF constructions can be chosen so that
		they are, in most cases, close to the language constructions. Other
		languages, such as Lisp, are likely to need a few extensions. To express
		novel language features TDF will probably have to be more seriously
		extended. But the time to do so is when the feature in question has achieved
		sufficient stability. Tokens can be used to express the constructs until the
		time is right. For example, there is a lack of consensus about the best
		constructions for parallel languages, so that at present TDF would either
		have to use low level constructions for parallelism or back what might turn
		out to be the wrong system. In other words it is not yet the time to make
		generalisations for parallelism as an intrinsic part of TDF.</para>

	<para>TDF is neutral with respect to machine architectures. In designing TDF, the
		aim has been to retain the information which is needed to produce and
		optimise the machine code, while discarding identifier and syntactic
		information. So TDF has constructions which are closely related to typical
		language features and it has an abstract model of memory. We expect that
		programs expressed in the considered languages can be translated into code
		which is as efficient as that produced by native compilers for those
		languages.</para>

	<para>Because of these porting features TDF supports shrink-wrapping, distribution
		and installation. Installation does not have to be left to the end-user; the
		production of executables can be done anywhere in the chain from software
		vendor, through dealer and network manager to the end-user.</para>

	<para>This document provides English language specifications for each construct in
		the TDF format and some general notes on various aspects of TDF. It is
		intended for readers who are aware of the general background to TDF but
		require more detailed information.</para>
</chapter>
