<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<preface>
	<title>Preface</title>

	<para>This is Issue 4.0 of the TDF Specification. TDF version 4.0 is not bitwise
		compatible with earlier versions.</para>

	<section id="major-changes-from-issue-3.1">
		<title>Major changes from issue 3.1</title>

		<para>A new <code>SORT</code> for <code>STRING</code> is introduced having the
			same relationship to <code>TDFSTRING</code> as <code>BOOL</code> has to
			<code>TDFBOOL</code>. This is used in place of <code>TDFSTRING</code> in
			various 3.1 constructions.</para>

		<para>They are also used in modified tag and token definitions and declarations
			to provide extra consistency checks in the use of these tags or tokens,
			and also may be used as names external to the TDF system. For example, the
			signature of <replaceable>make_id_tagdec</replaceable> is now:</para>

		<programlisting language="tdf">t_intro:   TDFINT
acc:       OPTION(ACCESS)
signature: OPTION(STRING)
x:         SHAPE
 -&gt; TAGDEC</programlisting>

		<para>A new <code>EXP</code> constructor, <replaceable>initial_value</replaceable>, is
			introduced to allow dynamic initialisation of global tags.</para>

		<para>These changes arise mainly from requirements of C++, but are clearly
			applicable elsewhere.</para>

		<para>Magic numbers are introduced at the start of files containing TDF
			bitstream information.</para>

		<para>The version 3.1 constructor <replaceable>set_stack_limit</replaceable> has had
			to be modified in the light of experience with platforms with ABIs which
			require upward-growing stacks or use disjoint frame stacks and alloca
			stacks.</para>

		<para>Various other minor changes have been made to elucidate some rather
			pathological cases, e.g. <replaceable>make_nof</replaceable> must have at least
			one element. Also there are some cosmetic changes to improve consistency,
			e.g. the order of the arguments of <replaceable>token</replaceable> are now
			consistent with <replaceable>token_definition</replaceable>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="notes-on-revision-1">
		<title>Notes on revision 1</title>

		<para>This Revision 1 of Issue 4.0 incorporates a number of corrections which
			have arisen where inconsistency or impracticability became evident when
			validating the OSF Research Institute's AVS (ANDF Validation Suite). Apart
			from minor textual corrections, the changes are:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use of installer-defined <code>TOKEN</code>s for accessing variable
					parameter lists - see the companion document <ulink url="reference/xhtml/register/">TDF Token Register (Revision
					1)</ulink>.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Tolerance of overflow necessary to allow simple implementation of
					complex multiply and divide.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Modified constraints on the arguments of
					<replaceable>shift_left</replaceable>, <replaceable>shift_right</replaceable>,
					<replaceable>rotate_left</replaceable>, <replaceable>rotate_right</replaceable>,
					<replaceable>make_dynamic_callees</replaceable>,
					<replaceable>make_var_tagdec</replaceable>,
					<replaceable>make_tokdec</replaceable>, <replaceable>make_tokdef</replaceable>,
					and <replaceable>user_info</replaceable>.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Modified constant evaluation constraints with respect to
					<replaceable>env_size</replaceable> and <replaceable>env_offset</replaceable>.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para><replaceable>chain_extern</replaceable> no longer supported.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Changes under consideration but not included in Issue 4.0:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Tokenisation of the various LIST constructs.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Inclusion of the specification of run-time diagnostic information in
					the main specification. This is currently given as an appendix, as
					it it is less mature than the main specification.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</preface>
