<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<preface id="intro">

    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document is designed as a technical overview to usage of
		the TenDRA C++ to TDF/ANDF producer.
		It also describes the <link linkend="interface">public interfaces</link>
		to the producer.</para>

    <para>Whereas the interface description contains most of the information
		which would be required in a users' guide, it is not necessarily in a
		readily digestible form.  The C++ producer is designed to complement the
		existing TenDRA C to TDF producer; although they are completely distinct
		programs, the same design philosophy underlies both and they share a
		number of common interfaces.  There are no radical differences between
		the two producers, besides the fact that the C++ producer covers a
		vastly larger and more complex language.  This means that much of the
		documentation on the C producer can be
		taken as also applying to the C++ producer.  This document tries to make
		clear where the C++ producer extends the C producer's interfaces, and
		those portions of these interfaces which are not directly applicable to
		C++.</para>

    <para>A familiarity with both C++ and TDF is assumed. The version of C++
		implemented is that given by the <link linkend="CPP96">draft ISO C++
		standard</link>.  All references to &quot;ISO C++&quot; within the document
		should strictly be qualified using the word &quot;draft&quot;, but
		for convenience this has been left implicit.  The C++ producer has
		a number of switches which allow it to be configured for older dialects
		of C++.  In particular, the version of C++ described in the
		<link linkend="CPP-ARM">ARM (Annotated Reference Manual)</link>
		is fully supported.</para>

    <para>The &tdf-spec.doc; (version 4.0) may be consulted for a description
		of the compiler intermediate language used.
		The paper &tdf-portability.doc; provides a useful (if slightly old)
		introduction to some of the ideas relating to static
		program analysis and interface checking which underlie the whole TenDRA
		compilation system.</para>

	<para>Since this document was originally written, the old C producer,
		<emphasis>tdfc</emphasis>, has been replaced by a new C producer, <emphasis>tdfc2</emphasis>,
		which is just a modified version of the C++ producer, <emphasis>tcpplus</emphasis>.
		All C producer documentation continues to apply to the new C producer,
		but the new C producer also has many of the features described in this
		document as only applying to the C++ producer.</para>

	<section id="interface">
		<title>Interface descriptions</title>

		<para>The most important public interfaces of the C++ producer are the ISO
			C++ standard and the TDF 4.0 specification; however there are other
			interfaces, mostly common to both the C and C++ producers, which are
			described in this section.</para>

		<para>An important design criterion of the C++ producer was that it should
			be strictly ISO conformant by default, but have a method whereby dialect
			features and extra static program analysis can be enabled. This compiler
			configuration is controlled by the
			<code>#pragma TenDRA</code> directives
			described in the first section.</para>

		<para>The requirement that the C and C++ producers should be able to translate
			portable C or C++ programs into target independent TDF requires a
			mechanism whereby the target dependent implementations of APIs can
			be represented.  This mechanism, the <code>#pragma token</code> syntax,
			is described in &pragmatoken.doc;.  Note
			that at present this mechanism only contains support for C APIs; it
			is considered that the C++ language itself contains sufficient interface
			mechanisms for C++ APIs to be described.</para>

		<para>The C and C++ producers provide two mechanisms whereby type and declaration
			information derived from a translation unit can be stored to a file
			for post-processing by other tools.
			The first is the symbol table dump, which is a public interface
			designed for use by third party tools.
			The second is the C/C++ spec file, which is designed for ease
			of reading and writing by the producers themselves, and is used for
			intermodule analysis.</para>

		<para>The mapping from C++ to TDF implemented by the C++ producer is largely
			straightforward.  There are however target dependencies arising within
			the language itself which require special handling.  These are represented
			by certain standard tokens which the producer requires to be defined on
			the target machine.
			These tokens are also used to describe the interface between the producer
			and the run-time system.
			Note that the C++ producer is primarily concerned with the
			C++ language, not with the standard C++ library. An example implementation
			of those library components which are required as an integral part
			of the language (memory allocation, exception handling, run-time type
			information etc.) is provided. Otherwise, libraries should be obtained
			from third parties.
			A number of hints on <link linkend="stdlib">integrating
			such libraries</link> with the C++ producer are given.</para>
	</section>

</preface>

