<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY tdf "<acronym>TDF</acronym>">
]>

<chapter id="S2">
	<title>Input classes</title>

	<para>The rest of this paper is concerned with the form required of the
		input text file. The input can be divided into eight classes.</para>

	<!-- XXX variablelist instead -->
	<section id="S21">
		<title>Delimiters</title>

		<para>The characters <code>(</code> and <code>)</code> are used as delimiters
			to impose a syntactic structure on the input.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S22">
		<title>White space</title>

		<para>White space comprises sequences of space, tab and newline characters,
			together with comments (see below). It is not significant to the output
			(&tdf; notation is completely free-form), and serves only to separate
			syntactic units. Every identifier, number etc. must be terminated
			by a white space or a delimiter.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S23">
		<title>Comments</title>

		<para>Comments may be inserted in the input at any point. They begin with
			a <code>#</code> character and run to the end of the line.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S24">
		<title>Identifiers</title>

		<para>An identifier consists of any sequence of characters drawn from the
			following set: upper case letters, lower case letters, decimal digits,
			underscore (<code>_</code>), dot (<code>.</code>), and tilde (<code>~</code>),
			which does not begin with a decimal digit. <code>tnc</code> generates
			names beginning with double tilde (<code>~~</code>) for unnamed objects
			when in <emphasis>decode</emphasis> mode, so the use of such identifiers is not
			recommended.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S25">
		<title>Numbers</title>

		<para>Numbers can be given in octal (prefixed by <code>0</code>), decimal,
			or hexadecimal (prefixed by <code>0x</code> or <code>0X</code>). Both
			upper and lower case letters can be used for hex digits. A number
			can be preceded by any number of <code>+</code> or <code>-</code>
			signs.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S26">
		<title>Strings</title>

		<para>A string consists of a sequence of characters enclosed in double quotes
			(<code>&quot;</code>). The following escape sequences are recognised:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><code>\n</code> represents a newline character,</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para><code>\t</code> represents a tab character,</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para><code>\xxx</code>, where <code>xxx</code> consists of three octal
				digits, represents the character with ASCII code <code>xxx</code>.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

		<para>Newlines are not allowed in strings unless they are escaped. For all
			other escaped characters, <code>\x</code> represents <code>x</code>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S27">
		<title>Blanks</title>

		<para>A single minus character (<code>-</code>) has a special meaning. It
			may be used to indicate the absence of an optional argument or optional
			group of arguments.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="S28">
		<title>Bars</title>

		<para>A single vertical bar (<code>|</code>) has a special meaning. It may
			be used to indicate the end of a sequence of repeated arguments.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

