<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter>
	<title>Input syntax</title>

	<section>
		<title>Basic syntax</title>

		<para>The basic input syntax is very simple. A construct consists of an
			identifier followed by a list of arguments, all enclosed in brackets
			in a Lisp-like fashion. Each argument can be an identifier, a number,
			a string, a blank, a bar, or another construct. There are further
			restrictions on this basic syntax, described below.</para>

<programlisting language="bnf">construct	: ( identifier arglist )

argument	: construct
		| identifier
		| number
		| string
		| blank
		| bar

arglist		: (empty)
		| argument arglist</programlisting>

		<para>The construct <code>( identifier )</code>, with an empty argument
			list, is equivalent to the identifier argument <code>identifier</code>.
			The two may be used interchangeably.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Sorts</title>

		<para>Except at the outermost level, which forms a special case discussed
			below, every construct and argument has an associated sort. This is
			one of the basic &tdf; sorts: <code>access</code>, <code>al_tag</code>,
			<code>alignment</code>, <code>bitfield_variety</code>, <code>bool</code>,
			<code>callees</code>, <code>error_code</code>, <code>error_treatment</code>,
			<code>exp</code>, <code>floating_variety</code>, <code>label</code>,
			<code>nat</code>, <code>ntest</code>, <code>procprops</code>, <code>rounding_mode</code>,
			<code>shape</code>, <code>signed_nat</code>, <code>string</code>,
			<code>tag</code>, <code>transfer_mode</code>, <code>variety</code>,
			<code>tdfint</code> or <code>tdfstring</code>.</para>

		<para>Ignoring for the moment the shorthands discussed below, the ways of
			creating constructs of sort <code>exp</code> say, correspond to the
			&tdf; constructs delivering an <code>exp</code>. For example, <code>contents
			</code> takes a <code>shape</code> and an <code>exp</code> and delivers
			an <code>exp</code>. Thus:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( contents arg1 arg2 )</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>arg1</code> is an argument of sort <code>shape</code>
			and <code>arg2</code> is an argument of sort <code>exp</code>, is
			a sort-correct construct. Only constructs which are sort correct in
			this sense are allowed.</para>

		<para>As another example, because of the rule concerning constructs with
			no arguments, both</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( true )</programlisting>

		<para>and</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">false</programlisting>

		<para>are valid constructs of sort <code>bool</code>.</para>

		<para>&tdf; constructs which take lists of arguments are easily dealt with.
			For example:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_nof arg1 ... argn )</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>arg1</code>, ..., <code>argn</code> are all arguments
			of sort <code>exp</code>, is valid. A vertical bar may be used to
			indicate the end of a sequence of repeated arguments.</para>

		<para>Optional arguments should be entered normally if they are present.
			Their absence may be indicated by means of a blank (minus sign), or
			by simply omitting the argument.</para>

		<para>The vertical bar and blank should be used whenever the input is potentially
			ambiguous. Particular care should be taken with <code>apply_proc</code>
			(which is genuinely ambiguous) and <code>labelled</code>.</para>

		<para>The &tdf; specification should be consulted for a full list of valid
			&tdf; constructs and their argument sorts. Alternatively the <code>tnc</code>
			help facility may be used. The command:</para>

		<screen>% tnc -help cmd1 ... cmdn</screen>

		<para>prints sort information on the constructs or sorts <code>cmd1</code>,
			..., <code>cmdn</code>. Alternatively:</para>

		<screen>% tnc -help</screen>

		<para>prints this information for all constructs. (To obtain help on the
			sort <code>alignment</code> as opposed to the construct <code>alignment</code>
			use <code>alignment_sort</code>. This confusion cannot occur elsewhere.)</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Numbers and strings</title>

		<para>Numbers can occur in two contexts, as the argument to the &tdf; constructs
			<code>make_nat</code> and <code>make_signed_nat</code>. In the former
			case the number must be positive. The following shorthands are understood
			by <code>tnc</code>:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">number <emphasis>for</emphasis> ( make_nat number )
number <emphasis>for</emphasis> ( make_signed_nat number )</programlisting>

		<para>depending on whether a construct of sort <code>nat</code> or
			<code>signed_nat</code> is expected.</para>

		<para>Strings are nominally of sort <code>tdfstring</code>. They are taken
			to be simple strings (8 bits per character). Multibyte strings (those
			with other than 8 bits per character) may be represented by means
			of the <code>multi_string</code> construct. This takes the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( multi_string b c1 ... cn )</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>b</code> is the number of bits per character and <code>c1</code>,
			...,<code>cn</code> are the codes of the characters comprising the
			string. These multibyte strings cannot be used as external names.</para>

		<para>In addition, a simple (8 bit) string can be used as a shorthand for
			a &tdf; construct of sort <code>string</code>, as follows:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">string <emphasis>for</emphasis> ( make_string string )</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Tokens, tags, alignment tags and labels</title>

		<para>In &tdf; simple tokens, tags, alignment tags and labels are represented
			by numbers which may, or may not, be associated with external names.
			In <code>tnc</code> however they are represented by identifiers. This
			brings the problem of scoping which does not occur in &tdf;. The rules
			are that all tokens, tags, alignment tags and labels must be declared
			before they are used. Externally defined objects have global scope,
			and the scope of a formal argument in a token definition is the definition
			body. For those constructs which introduce a local tag or label -
			for example, <code>identify</code>, <code>make_proc</code>,
			<code>make_general_proc</code> and <code>variable</code> for tags and <code>conditional</code>,
			<code>labelled</code> and <code>repeat</code> for labels - the scope
			of the object is as set out in the &tdf; specification.</para>

		<para>The following shorthands are understood by <code>tnc</code>, according
			to the argument sort expected:</para>

<programlisting language="tnc">tag_id <emphasis>for</emphasis> ( make_tag tag_id )
al_tag_id <emphasis>for</emphasis> ( make_al_tag al_tag_id )
label_id <emphasis>for</emphasis> ( make_label label_id )</programlisting>

		<para>The syntax for token applications is as follows:</para>

<programlisting language="tnc">( apply_construct ( token_id arg1 ... argn ) )</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>apply_construct</code> is the appropriate &tdf; token application
			construct, for example, <code>exp_apply_token</code> for tokens declared
			to deliver <code>exp</code>'s. The token arguments <code>arg1</code>,
			..., <code>argn</code> must be of the sorts indicated in the token
			declaration or definition. For tokens without any arguments the alternative
			form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( apply_construct token_id )</programlisting>

		<para>is allowed.</para>

		<para>The token application above may be abbreviated to:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( token_id arg1 ... argn )</programlisting>

		<para>the result sort being known from the token declaration. This in turn
			may be abbreviated to:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">token_id</programlisting>

		<para>when there are no token arguments.</para>

		<para>Care needs to be taken with these shorthands, as they can lead to
			confusion, particularly when, due to optional arguments or lists of
			arguments, <code>tnc</code> is not sure what sort is coming next.
			The five categories of objects represented by identifiers - &tdf; constructs,
			tokens, tags, alignment tags and labels - occupy separate name spaces,
			but it is a good idea to try to avoid duplication of names.</para>

		<para>By default all these shorthands are used by <code>tnc</code> in <emphasis>write</emphasis>
			mode. If this causes problems, the <emphasis>-V</emphasis> flag should be passed
			to <code>tnc</code>.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

