<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter>
	<title>Outer level syntax</title>

	<para>At the outer level <code>tnc</code> is expecting a sequence of constructs
		of the following forms:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>an included file,</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>a token declaration,</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>a token definition,</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>an alignment tag declaration,</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>an alignment tag definition,</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>a tag declaration,</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>a tag definition.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<section>
		<title>Included files</title>

		<para>Included files may be of three types&mdash;text, &tdf; capsule or &tdf; library.
			For &tdf; capsules and libraries there are two include modes. The first
			just decodes the given capsule or set of capsules. The second scans
			through them to extract token declaration information. These declarations
			appear in the output file only if they are used elsewhere.</para>

		<para>The syntax for an included text file is:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( include string )</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>string</code> is a string giving the pathname of the file
			to be included. <code>tnc</code> applies <emphasis>read</emphasis> to this sub-file
			before continuing with the present file.</para>

		<para>Similarly, the syntaxes for included &tdf; capsules and libraries are:</para>

<programlisting language="tnc">( code string )
( lib string )</programlisting>

		<para>respectively. <code>tnc</code> applies <emphasis>decode</emphasis> to this capsule
			or set of capsules (provided this mode is available) before continuing
			with the present file.</para>

		<para>The syntaxes for extracting the token declaration information from
			a &tdf; capsule or library are:</para>

<programlisting language="tnc">( use_code string )
( use_lib string )</programlisting>

		<para>Again, these rely on the <emphasis>decode</emphasis> mode being available.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Internal and external names</title>

		<para>All tokens, tags and alignment tags have an internal name, namely
			the associated identifier, but this name does not necessarily appear
			in the corresponding &tdf; capsule. There must firstly be an associated
			declaration or definition at the outer level - tags internal to a
			piece of &tdf; do not have external names. Even then we may not wish
			this name to appear at the outer level, because it is local to this
			file and is not required for linking purposes. Alternatively we may
			wish a different external name to be associated with it in the &tdf;
			capsule.</para>

		<para>As an example of how <code>tnc</code> allows for this, consider token
			declarations (although similar remarks apply to token definitions,
			alignment tag definitions etc.). The basic form of the token declaration
			is:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_tokdec token_id ... )</programlisting>

		<para>This creates a token with both internal and external names equal to
			<code>token_id</code>. Alternatively:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( local make_tokdec token_id ... )</programlisting>

		<para>creates a token with internal name <code>token_id</code> but no external
			name. This allows the creation of tokens local to the current file.
			Again:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_tokdec ( string_extern string ) token_id ... )</programlisting>

		<para>creates a token with internal name <code>token_id</code> and external
			name given by the string <code>string</code>. For example, to create
			a token whose external name is not a valid identifier, it would be
			necessary to use this construct. Finally:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_tokdec ( unique_extern string1 ... stringn ) token_id ... )</programlisting>

		<para>creates a token with internal name <code>token_id</code> and external
			name given by the unique name consisting of the strings <code>string1</code>,
			..., <code>stringn</code>.</para>

		<para>The <code>local</code> quantifier should be used consistently on all
			declarations and definitions of the token, tag or alignment tag. The
			alternative external name should only be given on the first occasion
			however. Thereafter the object is identified by its internal name.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Token declarations</title>

		<para>The basic form of a token declaration is:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_tokdec token_id ( arg1 ... argn ) res )</programlisting>

		<para>where the token <code>token_id</code> is declared to take argument
			sorts <code>arg1</code>, ..., <code>argn</code> and deliver the result
			sort <code>res</code>. These sorts are given by their sort names,
			<code>al_tag</code>, <code>alignment</code>, <code>bitfield_variety</code>
			etc. For a token with no arguments the declaration may be given in
			the form:</para>

<programlisting language="tnc">( make_tokdec token_id res )</programlisting>

		<para>A token may be declared any number of times, provided the declarations
			are consistent.</para>

		<para>This basic declaration may be modified in the ways outlined above
			to specify the external token name.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Token definitions</title>

		<para>The basic form of a token definition is:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_tokdef token_id ( arg1 id1 ... argn idn ) res def )</programlisting>

		<para>where the token <code>token_id</code> is defined to take formal arguments
			<code>id1</code>, ..., <code>idn</code> of sorts <code>arg1</code>,
			..., <code>argn</code> respectively and have the value <code>def</code>,
			which is a construct of sort <code>res</code>. The scope of the tokens
			<code>id1</code>, ..., <code>idn</code> is <code>def</code>.</para>

		<para>For a token with no arguments the definition may be given in the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_tokdef token_id res def )</programlisting>

		<para>A token may be defined more than once. All definitions must be consistent
			with any previous declarations and definitions (the renaming of formal
			arguments is allowed however).</para>

		<para>This basic definition may be modified in the ways outlined above to
			specify the external token name.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Alignment tag declarations</title>

		<para>The basic form of an alignment tag declaration is:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_al_tagdec al_tag_id )</programlisting>

		<para>where the alignment tag <code>al_tag_id</code> is declared to exist.</para>

		<para>This basic declaration may be modified in the ways outlined above
			to specify the external alignment tag name.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Alignment tag definitions</title>

		<para>The basic form of an alignment tag definition is:</para>

		<programlisting language="tnc">( make_al_tagdef al_tag_id def )</programlisting>

		<para>where the alignment tag <code>al_tag_id</code> is defined to be <code>def</code>,
			which is a construct of sort <code>alignment</code>. An alignment
			tag may be declared or defined more than once, provided the definitions
			are consistent.</para>

		<para>This basic definition may be modified in the ways outlined above to
			specify the external alignment tag name.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Tag declarations</title>

		<para>The basic forms of a tag declaration are:</para>

<programlisting language="tnc">( make_id_tagdec tag_id info dec )
( make_var_tagdec tag_id info dec )
( common_tagdec tag_id info dec )</programlisting>

		<para>where the tag <code>tag_id</code> is declared to be an identity, variable
			or common tag with access information <code>info</code>, which is
			an optional construct of sort <code>access</code>, and shape <code>dec</code>,
			which is a construct of sort <code>shape</code>. A tag may be declared
			more than once, provided all declarations and definitions are consistent
			(including agreement of whether the tag is an identity, a variable
			or common).</para>

		<para>These basic declarations may be modified in the ways outlined above
			to specify the external tag name.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Tag definitions</title>

		<para>The basic forms of a tag definition are:</para>

<programlisting language="tnc">( make_id_tagdef tag_id def )
( make_var_tagdef tag_id info def )
( common_tagdef tag_id info def )</programlisting>

		<para>where the tag <code>tag_id</code> is defined to be an identity, variable
			or common tag with value <code>def</code>, which is a construct of
			sort <code>exp</code>. Non-identity tag definitions also have an optional
			<code>access</code> construct, <code>info</code>. A tag must have
			been declared before it is defined, but may be defined any number
			of times. All declarations and definitions must be consistent (except
			that common tags may be defined inconsistently) and agree on whether
			the tag is an identity, a variable, or common.</para>

		<para>These basic definitions may be modified in the ways outlined above
			to specify the external tag name.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

