<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--
  $Id$
-->
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>TenDRA - Frequently Asked Questions</title>

    <corpauthor>The TenDRA Project</corpauthor>
    
    <author>Jeroen Ruigrok van der Werven</author>
    <authorinitials>JRvdW</authorinitials>
    <pubdate>2004</pubdate>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>First draft of the FAQ.  Lame set-up, no nice colours, and so on.
    Also, the order is based on nothing for now.</para>

  <qandaset>
    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>What is/was QinetiQ/Dstl/DERA/DRA?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>The Defence Research Agency (DRA) was an amalgamation (mix) of
          organisations formed in 1991 out of: the Royal Aerospace
          Establishment (RAE), the Royal Armaments Research and Development
          Establishment (RARDE), the Admiralty Research Establishment (ARE),
          and the Royal Signals and Radar Establishment (RSRE).  The purpose
          of DRA was to "provide a more efficient research organisation within
          the MoD." (Source: United Kingdom Parliament's House of Commons'
          Select Committee on Defence's Ninth Report, section 'The Future of
          DERA' and onward)</para>

        <para>through an amalgamation of multiple organisations: the Defence
          Research Agency (DRA), the Chemical and Biological Defence
          Establishment (CBDE), the Defence Operational Analysis Centre
          (DOAC), the Army Personnel Research Establishment and the Test &amp;
          Evaluation Establishments, e.g. the Aeroplane &amp; Armament
          Experimental Establishment (A&amp;AEE).</para>

        <para>On the second of July 2001 DERA split off into QinetiQ
          (http://www.qinetiq.co.uk/) and Defence Science and Technology
          Laboratory (Dstl).</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>What are ANDF and TDF?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>TDF is an Architecture Neutral Distribution Format (ANDF).  It
          is similar to a machine-independent intermediate representation in a
          compiler.  The idea is that software vendors can sell a single
          shrink-wrapped ANDF version (made by a `producer', similar to a
          compiler front-end) of their stuff and anyone with an ANDF
          `installer' (back end) on their machine can buy it and run it.  It
          is a bit like UNCOL in the breadth of its aims but seems to actually
          work.</para>

        <para>Only a subset of TDF was chosen by the OSF for its ANDF. This
          subset is sufficient for ANSI C, but TDF as a whole was designed to
          support (at least) FORTRAN, COBOL, C++, Ada, ML, and LISP
          also.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>What is Ten15?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>We will fill this out soon.</para>
        <para>See <ulink url="http://www.mca-ltd.com/martin/Ten15/">
          An Introduction to Ten15 - A personal retrospective</ulink> in the
          meantime</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Which documents and papers exist for/about TenDRA and ANDF?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>TDF Specification</para>
          </listitem>
          
          <listitem>
            <para>TDF Facts and Figures</para>
          </listitem>
          
          <listitem>
            <para>TDF and portability</para>
          </listitem>
          
          <listitem>
            <para>Introductory Guide to TDF</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>I try to compile the following simple C++ program:
          <programlisting>
            #include &lt;iostream.h&gt;

            int main()
            {
                    cout &lt;&lt; "hello world\n";
                    return (0);
            }
          </programlisting>
          and the compiler is giving me errors.</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
        <para>This release only contains the bare minimum language support
          library, not the fully standard C++ library.  See the C++ producer
          documentation for more details.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</article>
