<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<!--
  $Id$
-->

<article class="faq">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>TenDRA - Frequently Asked Questions</title>

    <corpauthor>The TenDRA Project</corpauthor>
    
    <author>
      <firstname>Jeroen</firstname>
      <surname>Ruigrok van der Werven</surname>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>JRvdW</authorinitials>
    <pubdate>2004</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year>
      <year>2005</year>

      <holder>The TenDRA Project</holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

	<!--
 	TODO First draft of the FAQ.  Lame set-up, no nice colours, and so on.
    Also, the order is based on nothing for now.

	Questions to include: are we dead? what are our plans?
	What happened with the split wrt ten15.org?
	-->

  <qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">
    <qandadiv id="tendra-history">
      <title>TenDRA History</title>

      <qandaentry id="what-is-dera">
        <question>
          <para>What is/was QinetiQ/Dstl/DERA/DRA?</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>According to <ulink
            url="http://www.catalogue.nationalarchives.gov.uk/displaycataloguedetails.asp?CATID=4256&amp;CATLN=3&amp;Highlight=&amp;FullDetails=True#admin">the
            National Archives of the United Kingdom</ulink>:</para> <para>The
            Royal Armament Research and Development Establishment (RARDE) had
            its origins in the Research Department Woolwich, and its Design
            Department which was established in 1922 and was concerned with
            the engineering design and development of weapons.</para>

          <para>At the end of 1942 the Design Department moved to Fort
            Halstead, Kent, followed later by the Research Department. They
            were designated the Armament Design Department and the Armament
            Research Department (ARD) respectively. In 1948 the ARD's name was
            changed to Armament Research Establishment (ARE).</para>

          <para>The two departments were amalgamated in 1955 to form the
            Armament Research and Development Establishment (ARDE), to
            integrate all stages of research, design and development. On 8
            February 1962 the title of Royal Armament Research and Development
            Establishment was granted.</para>

          <para>RARDE moved from MOD (Army) to become part of the new MOD/CER
            (Controllerate of Research and Development Establishments and
            Research) in 1971, its primary concern continuing in the research,
            design and development of conventional armaments for the Royal
            Navy, Army and Royal Air Force, whilst also providing help for the
            Home Office on the hazards of explosives, dangerous chemicals and
            the forensic aspects of explosives.</para>

          <para>During the 1980s RARDE amalgamated with the Military Vehicle
            Engineering Establishment (MVEE), whose main sites were located at
            Chertsey and Christchurch, and the Propellants, Explosives and
            Rocket Motor Establishment which was based at Waltham Abbey and
            Westcott.</para>

          <para>(Further according to <ulink
            url="http://www.catalogue.nationalarchives.gov.uk/displaycataloguedetails.asp?CATID=62012&amp;CATLN=3&amp;Highlight=&amp;FullDetails=True#admin">the
            National Archives of the United Kingdom</ulink>:)  On 1 April 1991
            the Defence Research Agency (DRA) was set up incorporating in one
            organisation the Royal Aerospace Establishment (RAE), the
            Admiralty Research Establishment (ARE), the Royal Armament
            Research and Development Establishment (RARDE), and the Royal
            Signals and Radar Establishment (RSRE). The DRA was established as
            an executive Agency of the Ministry of Defence under the
            Government's Next Steps Initiative.</para>

          <para>The purpose of DRA was to "provide a more efficient research
            organisation within the MoD." (Source: <ulink
            url="http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199899/cmselect/cmdfence/616/61607.htm">United
            Kingdom Parliament's House of Commons' Select Committee on
            Defence's Ninth Report, section 'The Future of DERA' and
            onward</ulink>)</para>

          <para>Having thus brought together its four non-nuclear research
            establishments, MOD then brought together various elements
            concerned with testing and evaluation, creating on 1 April 1992
            the Directorate General of Test and Evaluation. DGT&amp;E, the
            responsibility of the Deputy Under Secretary of State (Defence
            Procurement), was an amalgamation of various range and test
            facilities. These included the Proof and Experimental
            Establishments hitherto under the control of the Master General of
            the Ordnance (MGO), the Armament and Aircraft Experimental
            Establishment (A&amp;AEE) at Boscombe Down (which was already
            under DUS(DP)), DRA Pyestock (previously the National Gas Turbine
            Establishment (NGTE), RAE Propulsion Department from 1983), and
            various ranges that had been incorporated into DRA only a year
            earlier.</para>
          
          <para>Then on 1 April 1995 a further major amalgamation occurred,
            creating the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency (DERA). DERA
            incorporated DRA and DGT&amp;E, along with the Chemical and
            Biological Defence Establishment (CBDE), the Defence Operational
            Analysis Centre (DOAC), the Centre for Human Sciences (CHS), and
            the British Underwater Test and Evaluation Centre (BUTEC). DERA's
            initial structure comprised four operating divisions: CBDE, DRA,
            CDA (Centre for Defence Analysis), and DTEO (Defence Test and
            Evaluation Organisation).</para>

          <para>In 1998, the Strategic Defence Review recommended a Public
            Private Partnership (PPP) arrangement as the best means of
            maximising the strategic value and operational cost effectiveness
            of the United Kingdom's defence research capabilities.
            Accordingly, during 2000/2001 DERA was split into two
            organisations. The business areas to be retained by MOD were
            grouped as R-DERA (i.e. Retained), while those considered
            appropriate for operation in a fully commercial environment became
            New-DERA.</para>

          <para>New-DERA was re-structured to facilitate involvement by the
            private sector and, comprising the greater part of DERA, was
            re-created as the
            <ulink url="http://www.qinetiq.co.uk/">QinetiQ Group</ulink>, a
            wholly government-owned UK plc, in July 2001.  R-DERA was
            meanwhile re-named as the
            <ulink url="http://www.dstl.gov.uk/">Defence Science and
            Technology Laboratory (Dstl)</ulink> and continued as an MOD
            agency, handling certain areas of research which it had been
            decided should remain within the public sector.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry id="what-is-ten15">
        <question>
          <para>What is Ten15?</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>We will fill this out soon.</para>
          <para>See <ulink url="http://www.mca-ltd.com/martin/Ten15/">
            An Introduction to Ten15 - A personal retrospective</ulink> in the
            meantime</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandadiv>

    <qandadiv id="generic-questions">
      <title>Generic</title>

      <qandaentry id="what-are-andf-and-tdf">
        <question>
          <para>What are ANDF and TDF?</para>
        </question>
  
        <answer>
          <para>TDF is an Architecture Neutral Distribution Format (ANDF).  It
            is similar to a machine-independent intermediate representation in a
            compiler.  The idea is that software vendors can sell a single
            shrink-wrapped ANDF version (made by a `producer', similar to a
            compiler front-end) of their stuff and anyone with an ANDF
            `installer' (back end) on their machine can buy it and run it.  It
            is a bit like UNCOL in the breadth of its aims but seems to actually
            work.</para>
  
          <para>Only a subset of TDF was chosen by the OSF for its ANDF. This
            subset is sufficient for ANSI C, but TDF as a whole was designed to
            support (at least) FORTRAN, COBOL, C++, Ada, ML, and LISP
            also.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
  
      <qandaentry id="documents-papers-about-tendra">
        <question>
          <para>Which documents and papers exist for/about TenDRA and
            ANDF?</para>
        </question>
  
        <answer>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>TDF Specification</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <para>TDF Facts and Figures</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <para>TDF and portability</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <para>Introductory Guide to TDF</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandadiv>

    <qandadiv id="compilation-issues">
      <title>Compilation issues</title>

      <qandaentry id="cplusplus-compilation-support">
        <question>
          <para>I try to compile the following simple C++ program:
            <programlisting>
#include &lt;iostream.h&gt;

int main()
{
	cout &lt;&lt; "hello world\n";
	return (0);
}</programlisting>
            and the compiler is giving me errors.</para>
        </question>
  
        <answer>
          <para>This release only contains the bare minimum language support
            library, not the fully standard C++ library.  See the C++ producer
            documentation for more details.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandadiv>
  </qandaset>

  <para>This document was generated on
    <?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d H:M"?>.</para>
</article>
