<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<chapter>
	<title>&api; checking</title>

	<section>
		<title>Including headers</title>

		<!-- TODO: find a home for this -->

		<para>The token syntax described in the previous annex provides the means
			of describing an API specification independently of any particular
			implementation of the API. Every object in the API specification is
			described using the appropriate <code>#pragma</code> token statement. These
			statements are arranged in TenDRA header files corresponding to the
			headers comprising the API. Each API consists of a separate set of
			header files. For example, if the ANSI C89 API is used, the statement:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#include &lt;sys/types.h&gt;</programlisting>

		<para>will lead to a <quote>header not found</quote> error, whereas the
			header will be found in the POSIX API.</para>

		<para>Where relationships exist between APIs these have been made
			explicit in the headers. For example, the POSIX version of stdio.h
			consists of the ANSI version plus some extra objects. This is
			implemented by making the TenDRA header describing the POSIX
			version of <code>stdio.h</code> include the ANSI C89 version of
			<code>stdio.h</code>.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Specifying APIs to tcc</title>

		<para>The API against which a program is to be checked is
			specified to tchk by means of a command-line option of the form
			<code>-Y<replaceable>api</replaceable></code> where <replaceable>api</replaceable> is the API
			name. For example, ANSI X3.159 is specified by <code>-Yc89</code>
			(this is the default API) and POSIX 1003.1 is specified by
			<code>-Yposix</code> (for a full list of the supported APIs
			see Chapter 2).</para>

		<para>Extension APIs, such as X11, require special attention. The API
			for a program is never just X11, but X11 plus some base API, for
			example, X11 plus POSIX or X11 plus XPG3. These composite APIs may
			be specified by, for example, passing the options <code>-Yposix -Yx5_lib</code>
			(in that order) to tcc to specify POSIX 1003.1 plus X11 (Release 5)
			Xlib. The rule is that base APIs, such as POSIX, override the
			existing API, whereas extension APIs, such as X11, extend it. The
			command-line option <code>-info</code> causes tcc to print the
			API currently in use. For example:</para>

		<screen>% tcc -Yposix -Yx5_lib -info file.c</screen>

		<para>will result in the message:</para>

		<screen>tcc: Information: API is X11 Release 5 Xlib plus POSIX (1003.1).</screen>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>API Checking Examples</title>

		<para>As an example of the TenDRA compiler's API checking capacities,
			consider the following program which prints the names and inode
			numbers of all the files in the current directory:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;sys/types.h&gt;
#include &lt;dirent.h&gt;

int main ()
{
	DIR *d = opendir ( "." );
	struct dirent *e;
	if ( d = NULL ) return ( 1 );
	while ( e = readdir(d), e != NULL ) 
	{
		printf ( "%s %lu\n", e-&gt;d_name, e-&gt;d_ino );
	}
	closedir ( d );
	return ( 0 );
}</programlisting>

		<para>A first attempted compilation using strict checking:</para>

		<screen>% tcc -Xs a.c</screen>

		<para>results in messages to the effect that the headers
			<code>&lt;sys/types.h&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;dirent.h&gt;</code>
			cannot be found, plus a number of consequential errors. This is
			because tcc is checking the program against the default API, that
			is against the ANSI API, and the program is certainly not ANSI
			compliant. It does look as if it might be POSIX compliant however,
			so a second attempted compilation might be:</para>

		<screen>% tcc -Xs -Yposix a.c</screen>

		<para>This results in one error and three warnings. Dealing with the
			warnings first, the returns of the calls of <code>printf</code>
			and <code>closedir</code> are being discarded and the variable
			<code>d</code> has been set and not used. The discarded function
			returns are deliberate, so they can be made explicit by casting
			them to <code>void</code>. The discarded assignment to <code>d</code>
			requires a little more thought - it is due to the mistyping
			<code>d = NULL</code> instead of <code>d == NULL</code> on line 9.
			The error is more interesting. In full the error message reads:</para>

		<!-- TODO update this -->
		<screen>"a.c":11
	printf ( "%s %lu\n", e-&gt;d_name, e-&gt;d_ino!!!! );
Error:ISO[6.5.2.1]{ANSI[3.5.2.1]}: The identifier 'd_ino' is not a member of 
	'struct/union posix.dirent.dirent'.
ISO[6.3.2.3]{ANSI[3.3.2.3]}: The second operand of '-&gt;' must be a member of 
	the struct/union pointed to by the first.</screen>

		<para>That is, <code>struct dirent</code> does not have a field called
			<code>d_ino</code>. In fact this is true; while the <code>d_name</code>
			field of <code>struct dirent</code> is specified in POSIX,
			the <code>d_ino</code> field is an XPG3 extension (This example shows
			that the TenDRA representation of APIs is able to differentiate
			between APIs at a very fine level). Therefore a third attempted
			compilation might be:</para>

		<screen>% tcc -Xs -Yxpg3 a.c</screen>

		<para>This leads to another error message concerning the
			<code>printf</code> statement, that the types <code>unsigned long</code>
			and (the promotion of) <code>ino_t</code> are incompatible. This is
			due to a mismatch between the <code>printf</code> format string
			<code>%lu</code> and the type of <code>e-&gt;d_ino</code>. POSIX
			only says that <code>ino_t</code> is an arithmetic type, not a
			specific type like <code>unsigned long</code>. The TenDRA representation
			of POSIX reflects this abstract nature of <code>ino_t</code>, so that
			the potential portability error is detected. In fact it is impossible
			to give a <code>printf</code> string which works for all possible
			implementations of <code>ino_t</code>. The best that can be done is to
			cast <code>e-&gt;d_ino</code> to some fixed type like
			<code>unsigned long</code> and print that.</para>

		<para>Hence the corrected, XPG3 conformant program reads:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;sys/types.h&gt;
#include &lt;dirent.h&gt;

int main ()
{
	DIR *d = opendir ( "." );
	struct dirent *e;
	if ( d == NULL ) return ( 1 );
	while ( e = readdir(d), e != NULL )
	{
		( void ) printf ( "%s %lu\n", e-&gt;d_name, ( unsigned long ) e-&gt;d_ino );
	}
	( void ) closedir ( d );
	return ( 0 );
}</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Redeclaring Objects in APIs</title>

		<para>Of course, it is possible to redeclare the functions declared in
			the TenDRA API descriptions within the program, provided they are
			consistent. However, what constitutes a consistent redeclaration in
			the fully abstract TenDRA machine is not as straightforward as it
			might seem; an interesting example is malloc in the ANSI API. This
			is defined by the prototype:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">void *malloc ( size_t );</programlisting>

		<para>where <code>size_t</code> is a target dependent unsigned integral
			type. The redeclaration:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">void *malloc ();</programlisting>

		<para>is only correct if <code>size_t</code> is its own integral
			promotion, and therefore is not correct in general.</para>

		<para>Since it is not always desirable to remove these redeclarations
			(some machines may not have all the
			necessary functions declared in their system headers) the TenDRA
			compiler has a facility to accept inconsistent redeclarations of
			API functions which can be enabled by using the pragma:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA incompatible interface declaration allow</programlisting>

		<para>This pragma supresses the consistency checking of re-declarations
			of API functions. Replacing allow by warning causes a warning to be
			printed. In both cases the TenDRA API description of the function
			takes precedence. The normal behaviour of flagging inconsistent
			redeclarations as errors can be restored by replacing <code>allow</code>
			by <code>disallow</code> in the pragma above. (There are also
			equivalent command-line options to tcc of the form
			<code>-X:interface_decl=<replaceable>status</replaceable></code>, where
			<replaceable>status</replaceable> can be <code>check</code>,
			<code>warn</code> or <code>dont</code>.)</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Defining Objects in APIs</title>

		<para>Since the program API is meant to define the interface between
			what the program defines and what the target machine defines, the
			TenDRA compiler normally raises an error if any attempt is made
			to define an object from the API in the program itself. A subtle
			example of this is given by compiling the program:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#include &lt;errno.h&gt;
extern int errno;</programlisting>

		<para>with the ANSI API. ANSI states that <code>errno</code> is an
			assignable lvalue of type <code>int</code>, and the TenDRA
			description of the API therefore states precisely that. The
			declaration of <code>errno</code> as an <code>extern int</code>
			is therefore an inconsistent specification of <code>errno</code>,
			but a consistent implementation. Accepting the lesser of two
			evils, the error reported is therefore that an attempt has been
			made to define <code>errno</code> despite the fact that it is
			part of the API.</para>

		<para>Note that if this same program is compiled using the POSIX API,
			in which <code>errno</code> is explicitly specified to be an
			<code>extern int</code>, the program merely contains a consistent
			redeclaration of <code>errno</code> and so does not raise an
			error.</para>

		<para>The neatest workaround for the ANSI case, which preserves the
			declaration for those machines which need it, is as follows: if
			<code>errno</code> is anything other than an <code>extern int</code>
			it must be defined by a macro. Therefore:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#include &lt;errno.h&gt;
#ifndef errno
extern int errno;
#endif</programlisting>

		<para>should always work.</para>

		<para>In most other examples, the definitions are more obvious. For
			example, a programmer might provide a memory allocator containing
			versions of <code>malloc</code>, <code>free</code> etc.:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;

void *malloc ( size_t sz )
{
	....
}

void free ( void *ptr )
{
	....
}</programlisting>

		<para>If this is deliberate then the TenDRA compiler needs to be told
			to ignore the API definitions of these objects and to use those
			provided instead. This is done by listing the objects to be
			ignored using the pragma:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#pragma ignore malloc free ....</programlisting>

		<para>(also see section G.10). This should be placed between the API
			specification and the object definitions. The provided definitions
			are checked for conformance with the API specifications. There are
			special forms of this pragma to enable field selectors and objects
			in the tag namespace to be defined. For example, if we wish to
			provide a definition of the type <code>div_t</code> from
			<code>stdlib.h</code> we need to ignore three objects - the type
			itself and its two field selectors - <code>quot</code> and
			<code>rem</code>. The definition would therefore take the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
#pragma ignore div_t div_t.quot div_t.rem
typedef struct {
	int quot;
	int rem;
} div_t;</programlisting>

		<para>Similarly if we wish to define struct <code>lconv</code> from
			<code>locale.h</code> the definition would take the form:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#include &lt;locale.h&gt;
#pragma ignore TAG lconv TAG lconv.decimal_point 
....
struct lconv {
	char *decimal_point;
	....
};</programlisting>

		<para>to take into account that <code>lconv</code> lies in the tag
			name space. By defining objects in the API in this way, we are
			actually constructing a less general version of the API. This
			will potentially restrict the portability of the resultant
			program, and so should not be done without good reason.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Stepping Outside an API</title>

		<para>Using the TenDRA compiler to check a program against a
			standard API will only be effective if the appropriate API
			description is available to the program being tested (just as a
			program can only be compiled on a conventional machine if the
			program API is implemented on that machine). What can be done for
			a program whose API are not supported depends on the degree to
			which the program API differs from an existing TenDRA API
			description. If the program API is POSIX with a small extension,
			say, then it may be possible to express that extension to the
			TenDRA compiler. For large unsupported program APIs it may be
			possible to use the system headers on a particular machine to
			allow for partial program checking (see section H.7).</para>

		<para>For small API extensions the ideal method would be to use the
			token syntax described in Annex G to express the program API to the
			TenDRA compiler, however this is not currently encouraged because
			the syntax of such API descriptions is not yet firmly fixed. For
			the time being it may be possible to use C to express much of the
			information the TenDRA compiler needs to check the program. For
			example, POSIX specifies that <code>sys/stat.h</code> contains a
			number of macros, <code>S_ISDIR</code>, <code>S_ISREG</code>, and
			so on, which are used to test whether a file is a directory, a
			regular file, etc. Suppose that a program is basically POSIX
			conformant, but uses the additional macro <code>S_ISLNK</code> to
			test whether the file is a symbolic link (this is in COSE and AES,
			but not POSIX). A proper TenDRA description of <code>S_ISLNK</code>
			would contain the information that it was a macro taking a
			<code>mode_t</code> and returning an <code>int</code>, however for
			checking purposes it is sufficient to merely give the types. This
			can be done by pretending that <code>S_ISLNK</code> is a function:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#ifdef __TenDRA__
/* For TenDRA checking purposes only */
extern int S_ISLNK ( mode_t ); 
/* actually a macro */
#endif</programlisting>

		<para>More complex examples might require an object in the API to be
			defined in order to provide more information about it (see H.5).
			For example, suppose that a program is basically ANSI compliant,
			but assumes that <code>FILE</code> is a structure with a field
			<code>file_no</code> of type <code>int</code> (representing the
			file number), rather than a generic type. This might be expressed
			by:</para>

<programlisting language="c">#ifdef __TenDRA__
/* For TenDRA checking purposes only */
#pragma ignore FILE
typedef struct {
	/* there may be other fields here */
	int file_no;
	/* there may be other fields here */
} FILE;
#endif</programlisting>

		<para>The methods of API description above are what might be called
			<quote>example implementations</quote> rather than the
			<quote>abstract implementations</quote> of the actual TenDRA API
			descriptions. They should only be used as a last resort, when
			there is no alternative way of expressing the program within a
			standard API. For example, there may be no need to access the
			<code>file_no</code> field of a <code>FILE</code> directly, since
			POSIX provides a function, <code>fileno</code>, for this purpose.
			Extending an API in general reduces the number of potential target
			machines for the corresponding program.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Using the System Headers</title>

		<para>One possibility if a program API is not supported by the
			TenDRA compiler is to use the set of system headers on the
			particular machine on which tcc happens to be running. Of course,
			this means that the API checking facilities of the TenDRA compiler
			will not be effective, but it is possible that the other program
			checking aspects will be of use.</para>

		<para>The system headers are not, and indeed are not intended to be,
			portable. A simple-minded approach to portability checking with the
			system headers could lead to more portability problems being found
			in the system headers than in the program itself. A more
			sophisticated approach involves applying different compilation
			modes to the system headers and to the program. The program itself
			can be checked very rigorously, while the system headers have very
			lax checks applied.</para>

		<para>This could be done directly, by putting a wrapper around each
			system header describing the mode to be applied to that header.
			However the mechanism of named compilation modes (see 2.2) provides
			an alternative solution. In addition to the normal -Idir
			command-line option, tcc also supports the option -Nname:dir, which
			is identical except that it also associates the identifier name
			with the directory dir. Once a directory has been named in this
			way, the name can be used in a directive:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA directory <replaceable>name</replaceable> use environment <replaceable>mode</replaceable></programlisting>

		<para>which tells tcc to apply the named compilation mode, mode, to
			any files included from the directory, name. This is the mechanism
			used to specify the checks to be applied to the system headers.</para>

		<para>The system headers may be specified to tcc using the
			<code>-Ysystem</code> command-line option. This specifies
			<code>/usr/include</code> as the directory
			to search for headers and passes a system start-up file to tcc.
			This system start-up file contains any macro definitions which are
			necessary for tcc to navigate the system headers correctly, plus a
			description of the compilation mode to be used in compiling the
			system headers.</para>

		<para>In fact, before searching /usr/include, tcc searches another
			directory for system headers. This is intended to hold modified
			versions of any system headers which cause particular problems or
			require extra information. For example:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>A version of stdio.h is provided for all systems, which
					contains the declarations of printf and similar functions necessary
					for tcc to apply its printf-string checks (see 3.3.2).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A version of stdlib.h is provided for all systems which
					includes the declarations of exit and similar functions necessary
					for tcc to apply its flow analysis correctly (see 5.7).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Versions of stdarg.h and varargs.h are provided for all systems
					which work with tcc. Most system headers contain built-in functions
					which are recognised by cc (but not tcc) to deal with these.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>The user can also use this directory to modify any system headers
			which cause problems. For example, not all system headers declare
			all the functions they should, so it might be desirable to add
			these declarations.</para>

		<para>It should be noted that the system headers and the TenDRA API
			headers do not mix well. Both are parts of coherent systems of
			header files, and unless the intersection is very small, it is not
			usually possible to combine parts of these systems sensibly.</para>

		<para>Even a separation, such as compiling some modules of a program
			using a TenDRA API description and others using the system headers,
			can lead to problems in the intermodular linking phase (see Chapter
			9). There will almost certainly be type inconsistency errors since
			the TenDRA headers and the system headers will have different
			representations of the same object.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>API usage analysis</title>

		<para>The abstract standard headers provided with the tool are the
			basis for the API usage analysis checking on dump files described
			in Chapter 9. The declarations in each abstract header file are
			enclosed by the following pragmas:</para>

		<programlisting language="c">#pragma TenDRA declaration block <replaceable>API_name</replaceable> begin
#pragma TenDRA declaration block end</programlisting>

		<para><replaceable>API_name</replaceable> has a standard form e.g.
			<code>api__ansi__stdio</code> for <code>stdio.h</code>
			in the ANSI API.</para>

		<para>This information is output in the dump format as the start and
			end of a header scope, i.e.</para>

		<programlisting language="dump">SSH		 position				ref_no = &lt;API_name&gt;
SEH		 position				ref_no</programlisting>

		<para>The first occurence of each identifier in the dump output
			contains scope information; in the case of an identifier
			declared in the abstract headers, this scope information will
			normally refer to a header scope. Since each use of the identifier
			can be traced back to its declaration, this provides a means of
			tracking API usage within the application when the abstract headers
			are used. The disadvantages of this method are that only APIs for
			which abstract headers are available can be used. Objects which are
			not part of the standard APIs are not available and if an
			application requires such an identifier (or indeed attempts to use
			a standard API identifier for which the appropriate header has not
			been included) the resulting errors may distort or even completely
			halt the dump output resulting in incomplete or incorrect
			analysis.</para>

		<para>The second method of API analysis allows compilation of the
			application against the system headers, thereby overcoming the
			problems of non-standard API usage mentioned above. The dump of the
			application can be scanned to determine the identifiers which are
			used but not defined within the application itself. These
			identifiers form the program's external API with the system headers
			and libraries, and can be compared with API reference information,
			provided by dump output files produced from the abstract standard
			headers, to determine the applications API usage.</para>

		<!-- TODO: probably obsoleted -->
		<para>Analysis performed on the set of dump files produced for an
			entire application can detect the objects, types, etc. from
			external APIs which are used by the application. The API usage
			analysis is enabled by passing one or more
			<code>-api_check<replaceable>API</replaceable></code> flags to tchk
			where <replaceable>API</replaceable> may be any of the standard APIs
			listed in section 2.1.
			The <code>-api_check_out<replaceable>FILE</replaceable></code> flag
			may be used to direct the API analysis information to the file
			<replaceable>FILE</replaceable> (by default it is written to stdout).
			The APIs used to perform API usage analysis may be different
			from those used to process the application. Annex G.8 contains
			details of the methods used to perform the API usage analysis.</para>
	</section>

</chapter>

