<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "minidocbook.dtd">

<!-- $Id$ -->

<article>

	<articleinfo>
		<title>The TDF Linker - Linker Requirements</title>
		<productname>tld</productname>

		<authorgroup>
			<othercredit class="copyeditor">
				<firstname>Katherine</firstname>
				<surname>Flavel</surname>
				<affiliation><orgname>The TenDRA Project</orgname></affiliation>
			</othercredit>

			<author>
				<firstname>Steve</firstname>
				<surname>Folkes</surname>
				<affiliation><orgname>DRA</orgname></affiliation>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>

		<pubdate>1995</pubdate>

		<copyright>
			<year>1994</year>
			<year>1995</year>
			<year>1998</year>

			<holder>DERA</holder>
		</copyright>

		<copyright>
			<year>2007</year>

			<holder>The TenDRA Project</holder>
		</copyright>

		<revhistory>
			<revision role="docs">
				<date>2011-10-29</date>
				<authorinitials>kate</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Removed the &ldquo;tld&rdquo; unit encoding; this is
						given canonically by the &tdf-spec.doc; instead..</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>

			<revision role="version">
				<date>2010-02-21</date>
				<authorinitials>kate</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Moved out TLD as a standalone tool.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>

			<revision role="docs">
				<date>2007-12-02</date>
				<authorinitials>kate</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Converted to DocBook.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>

			<revision role="version">
				<date>2007-10-02</date>
				<authorinitials>kate</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Moved out TLD to join ANDFutils.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>

			<revision role="version">
				<date>1998-07-30</date>
				<revnumber>TLD 4.0#7</revnumber>
				<authorinitials>DERA</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>TenDRA 4.1.2 release.</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>

	<section>
		<title>Purpose</title>

		<para>This document describes the required behaviour of the TDF linker (although
			sometimes it refers to what the linker actually does).  It assumes that the
			reader understands the format of TDF capsules and libraries, as described in
			the tld.5 "File Formats" man page.</para>

		<para>The TDF linker has four uses:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>To bind together a number of TDF capsules (including those in
					libraries) to produce a single capsule.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>To produce a TDF library from a set of capsules.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>To list the contents of a TDF library.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>To extract capsules from a TDF library.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>The most complex part of the linker is the normal linking process, which is
			described in the next section.  Constructing libraries is described in the
			section after the one on linking.  Listing the contents of a library, and
			extracting capsules from a library are not very complicated so they aren't
			described in this document.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>TDF Linking</title>

		<para>This section describes the requirements of linking capsules together.  The
			first sub-section describes the basic linking requirements.  Subsequent
			sub-sections detail the requirements of some more advanced features.</para>

		<para>Before the linking process is described in detail, here is an outline of the
			stages of the link process:</para>

		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The linker is invoked with the following inputs: a set of input
					capsules, a set of libraries, a set of hiding rules, a set of keeping
					rules, a set of renaming rules, and a set of link suppression rules.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The first thing that the linker does is to enter the renaming rules into
					the name hash table.  The name entry lookup routines will automatically
					pick up the new name when a renamed name is looked up in a name table.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The next stage is to load the input capsules, and to bind them together.
					As part of this binding process, the capsule scope identifiers for all
					input capsules are mapped into a single capsule scope (to be output to
					the final capsule).  The rules for this mapping are described below.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>After binding the input capsules together, the linker tries to provide
					definitions for undefined names using the specified libraries.  When a
					definition is found in a library (and it hasn't been suppressed by the
					link suppression rules), the capsule that contains it is loaded and
					bound to the input capsules as if it had been one itself.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>After the library capsules have been bound in, external names are hidden
					according to the hiding rules, and kept according to the keeping rules.
					Hiding means removing an entry from the external name list of the output
					capsule.  Keeping means forcing an entry into the list, if it would
					otherwise be hidden.  It is illegal to hide names that have no
					definition.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Finally the output capsule is written to a file.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<section>
			<title>Basic Linking</title>

			<para>This sub-section describes the process of binding capsules together in
				greater detail.</para>

			<para>The first thing that the linker does when reading a capsule is to read in
				the magic number, and the major and minor version numbers.  Capsules with an
				incorrect magic number are rejected.  The major version number of each
				capsule read in must be at least four.  In addition, the major version
				numbers of all capsules that are read in must be the same.</para>

			<para>After this, the linker reads the unit group type names (also called "prop
				names"), and checks that the they are known and that they are in the correct
				order.  There is a default list of names built into the linker (the list
				specified in the TDF specification) and that should be sufficient for most
				uses of the linker, but it is possible to provide a new list by specifying a
				file containing the new list on the command line.</para>

			<para>The next thing the linker does is to read in the linkable entity names and
				the capsule scope identifier limit for each linkable entity.  It checks that
				there are no duplicate names, and creates a mapping vector for each linkable
				entity, to contain the mapping from the capsule scope identifiers in the
				capsule being read in to the capsule scope identifiers in the capsule that
				will be written out.</para>

			<para>After reading the linkable entity names, the linker reads the external names
				for each linkable entity.  For each name, it checks that its capsule scope
				identifier is in range, and maps that to the next available capsule scope
				identifier (for the same linkable entity) in the output capsule, unless a
				name with the same linkable entity and the same name (subject to the
				renaming rules) has already been read (in which case it is mapped to the
				same capsule scope identifier as the identical name).  The linker also
				checks to ensure that each capsule scope identifier has no more than one
				external name bound to it.</para>

			<para>The final phase of reading a capsule is to read the unit groups.  For normal
				(i.e. not "tld" or "tld2") unit groups, the following occurs for each unit
				in the unit group:</para>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>The unit scope identifier limits for each linkable entity are read and
						saved in the unit data structure (which is appended to the list of units
						in that unit group for all input capsules).  When the unit is written
						out in the output capsule, it may be necessary to add extra unit scope
						identifier limits (and extra mapping tables) as other capsules may have
						different linkable entities, which will also need entries (they will
						just be zero length).</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>The capsule scope to unit scope identifier mapping tables are read, and
						the old capsule scope identifier (which is first checked to see if it is
						in range) is replaced by a new capsule scope identifier.  This
						information is also saved in the unit data structure.  The new capsule
						scope identifiers are either the ones that were allocated when reading
						in the external names (if the old identifier is bound to an external
						name), or the next free capsule scope identifier of the required
						linkable entity.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Finally, the unit body is read, and saved with the unit.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>

			<para>For "tld" and "tld2" unit groups, the unit group count is checked to ensure
				that it is one, and the number of unit scope identifier limits and
				identifier mapping tables are checked to ensure that they are both zero.
				The size of the body is read (and it must be correct as this is checked
				after reading the unit), and then the body is read.  If the unit is a "tld"
				unit, then the type is read, and the body is read depending upon the type;
				if the unit is a "tld2" unit, then the body is read as if it where a type
				zero "tld" unit. See the &tdf-spec.doc; for details of the encoding of
				the "tld" and "tld2" unit groups.</para>

		<para>The linker uses the information provided by this unit to check that names
			do not have multiple
			unique definitions, and to decide whether libraries should be consulted to
			provide a definition for a name.  If a capsule contains no linker
			information unit group, then the names in that capsule will have no
			information, and hence will not receive the extra checking or library
			definition.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Renaming</title>

			<para>Renaming just requires that any occurrence of the name being renamed is
				treated as though it were an occurrence of the name it is being renamed to.
				This includes names read from library indices.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Library Capsules</title>

			<para>After reading in all of the specified capsules, the linker loads the
				libraries.  The library indices are read, and checked to ensure that there
				is no more than one definition for any external name.  If there is no unique
				definition, but there is a single multiple definition, then this is
				considered to be a definition (although this can be turned off with a
				command line option).</para>

			<para>Once the libraries have been loaded, each of the external names in the bound
				capsules that are used, but not defined are looked up in the library index.
				If a definition is found (and it hasn't been suppressed) then the defining
				capsule is loaded from the library.  This process is repeated until
				definitions have been found for all external names that need them (and that
				definitions exist for), including those that are undefined in the capsules
				read in from the libraries.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Hiding</title>

		<para>Hiding and keeping just require that all names which should be hidden, and
			are not required to be kept, are not written to the external name table of
			the output capsule.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Writing out the Capsule</title>

			<para>The magic number is written out, followed by the major and minor version
				numbers.  The major version number is the same as that in each of the loaded
				capsules.  The minor version number is the largest of the minor version
				numbers in the loaded capsules.</para>

			<para>The unit group type names are written out first.  Only those unit groups
				that are non-empty are actually written out.  They are written out in the
				order specified by the current unit group name list.</para>

			<para>The linkable entity names are written out next, followed by their capsule
				scope identifier limit.  Again, only those linkable entity names that are
				non empty (i.e.  have some unit scope or capsule scope identifiers) are
				written out.</para>

			<para>After the linkable entity names have been written out, the external names
				are written out.  These are written out in an arbitrary order within their
				linkable entities, with the linkable entities being written out in the same
				order as in the linkable entity name section (which is itself arbitrary, but
				must be repeatable).  The names are written out with their new capsule scope
				identifiers.  External names that have been hidden must not be written out.</para>

			<para>Finally the unit groups are written out in the same order as the unit group
				type names in the first section.  For normal units, the old counts (plus
				some zero counts that may be necessary if there are new linkable entities
				that weren't in the unit's original capsule) are written out in the same
				order as the linkable entity names in section two.  The counts are followed
				by the new capsule scope to unit scope identifier mapping tables, in the
				same order as the counts.  Finally the old unit content is written out.</para>

			<para>For "tld" unit groups, a single version one "tld" unit is written out
				containing the use information for each of the external names, in the same
				order that the external names were written out in.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Constructing TDF Libraries</title>

		<para>This section describes the requirements of building TDF libraries.  Here is
			an outline of the stages of the construction process:</para>

		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The linker is invoked with the following inputs: a set of input
				capsules, a set of libraries, and a set of link suppression rules.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The first thing that the linker does is to load the input capsules
					(including all capsules that are included in any of the specified
					libraries), and to extract their external name information into a
					central index.  The index is checked to ensure that there is only one
					definition for any given name.  The capsules are read in in the same way
					as for linking them (this checks them for validity).</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The suppression rules are applied, to ensure that no suppressed external
					name will end up in the index in the output library.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The library is written out.  The library consists of a magic number, and
					the major and minor version numbers of the TDF in the library
					(calculated in the same way as for capsules), the type zero, followed by
					the number of capsules.  This is followed by that many capsule name and
					capsule content pairs.  Finally, the index is appended to the library.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The index only contains entries for linkable entities that have external
					names defined by the library.  Only external names for which there is a
					definition are written into the index, although this is not a
					requirement (when linking, the linker will ignore index entries that
					don't provide a definition).  Either a unique definition or a single
					multiple definition are considered to be definitions (although the
					latter can be disabled using a command line option).</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
</article>

